import 'package:eng_card/data/gridview.dart';

List<Words> wordsList5 = [
  Words(
      front: "The government decided to abolish the old law .",
      back: "Hükümet, eski yasayı yürürlükten kaldırmaya karar verdi .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'yürürlükten kaldırmak',
      quest: 'abolish'),
  Words(
      front: "There was a complete absence of sound in the silent room .",
      back: "Sessiz odada tamamen yokluk,bulunmayış vardı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'yokluk,bulunmayış',
      quest: 'absence'),
  Words(
      front: "The land had an abundance of natural resources .",
      back: "Toprak, doğal kaynakların çokluğu,bolluğu vardı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'çokluk,bolluk',
      quest: 'abundance'),
  Words(
      front: "Drug abuse is a serious problem in many societies .",
      back:
          "Uyuşturucu madde kötüye kullanımı birçok toplumda ciddi bir sorundur .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'kötüye kullanmak',
      quest: 'abuse'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The car accelerated quickly as it pulled away from the stop sign .",
      back: "Araba stop işaretinden uzaklaşırken hızlandı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'hızlanmak',
      quest: 'accelerate'),
  Words(
      front: "Her acceptance speech was filled with gratitude .",
      back: "Her kabul konuşması minnettarlıkla doluydu .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'kabul',
      quest: 'acceptance'),
  Words(
      front: "The library is accessible to everyone in the community .",
      back: "Kütüphane, toplumdaki herkes için ulaşılabilir .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'ulaşılabilir',
      quest: 'accessible'),
  Words(
      front:
          "Winning the gold medal was a great accomplishment for the athlete .",
      back: "Altın madalya kazanmak, sporcu için büyük bir başarıydı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'başarma',
      quest: 'accomplishment'),
  Words(
      front: "He acted in accordance with the company's policies .",
      back: "Şirketin politikalarına uygun hareket etti .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'uygunluk',
      quest: 'accordance'),
  Words(
      front: "Accordingly, we need to change our approach .",
      back: "Bu sebepten dolayı, yaklaşımımızı değiştirmemiz gerekiyor .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'bu sebepten',
      quest: 'accordingly'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The police investigation revealed a series of accusations of corruption .",
      back: "Polis soruşturması bir dizi yolsuzluk suçlaması ortaya çıkardı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'itham,suçlama',
      quest: 'accusation'),
  Words(
      front: "The accused man pleaded not guilty in court .",
      back: "Suçlanan adam mahkemede suçsuz olduğunu iddia etti .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'zanlı,suçlu',
      quest: 'accused'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The company's recent acquisition of a new startup has expanded its market reach .",
      back:
          "Şirketin yakın zamanda yeni bir girişimin satın alınması pazar erişimini genişletti .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'kazanma',
      quest: 'acquisition'),
  Words(
      front: "The farmer owns a large plot of land that is hundreds of acres .",
      back: "Çiftçi, yüzlerce dönüm büyüklüğünde geniş bir araziye sahiptir .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'arazi',
      quest: 'acre'),
  Words(
      front: "The activation of the security system deterred the burglar .",
      back: "Güvenlik sisteminin etkinleşmesi hırsızı caydırdı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'etkinleşme',
      quest: 'activation'),
  Words(
      front: "He was suffering from acute pain after the accident .",
      back: "Kazadan sonra şiddetli ağrı çekiyordu .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'şiddetli',
      quest: 'acute'),
  Words(
      front: "Many species are struggling to adapt to the changing climate .",
      back:
          "Birçok tür, değişen iklime adaptasyon sağlamak için mücadele ediyor .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'adaptasyon',
      quest: 'adaptation'),
  Words(
      front: "Students must adhere to the school rules .",
      back: "Öğrenciler okul kurallarına uymalıdır .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'bağlı kalmak',
      quest: 'adhere'),
  Words(
      front: "The two buildings are adjacent to each other .",
      back: "İki bina birbirine komşu .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'komşu',
      quest: 'adjacent'),
  Words(
      front: "The doctor made some adjustments to the medication dosage .",
      back: "Doktor, ilaç dozunda bazı ayarlama yaptı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'ayarlama',
      quest: 'adjustment'),
  Words(
      front: "The government administers a variety of social programs .",
      back: "Hükümet çeşitli sosyal programları yönetir .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'yönetmek',
      quest: 'administer'),
  Words(
      front: "He works in an administrative role at the university .",
      back: "Üniversitede idari bir görevde çalışıyor .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'idari',
      quest: 'administrative'),
  Words(
      front: "The school principal is the administrator in charge .",
      back: "Okul müdürü sorumlu yönetici .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'yönetici',
      quest: 'administrator'),
  Words(
      front: "He finally made the admission that he had cheated on the exam .",
      back: "Nihayet sınavda kopya çektiğini itiraf etti .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'itiraf',
      quest: 'admission'),
  Words(
      front: "The teenager is going through a difficult adolescent stage .",
      back: "Genç, zor bir ergenlik dönemi yaşıyor .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'ergen',
      quest: 'adolescent'),
  Words(
      front: "The couple decided to pursue adoption to grow their family .",
      back:
          "Çift, ailelerini büyütmek için evlat edinme yoluna gitmeye karar verdi .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'benimseme',
      quest: 'adoption'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The weather forecast predicts adverse weather conditions this weekend .",
      back:
          "Hava durumu tahmini, bu hafta sonu olumsuz hava koşulları öngörüyor .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'olumsuz',
      quest: 'adverse'),
  Words(
      front: "The lawyer advocated for the rights of the refugees .",
      back: "Avukat, mültecilerin haklarını savundu .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'avukat,desteklemek',
      quest: 'advocate'),
  Words(
      front: "He has a great appreciation for the aesthetic beauty of nature .",
      back: "Doğanın estetik güzelliği konusunda büyük bir takdiri var .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'estetik',
      quest: 'aesthetic'),
  Words(
      front: "There was a deep affection between the mother and her child .",
      back: "Anne ile çocuğu arasında derin bir sevgi vardı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'alaka,etkileme',
      quest: 'affection'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The aftermath of the war left a trail of destruction and despair .",
      back: "Savaşın akıbeti, yıkım ve umutsuzluk izi bıraktı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'akıbet',
      quest: 'aftermath'),
  Words(
      front: "The child's aggressive behavior was a concern for his parents .",
      back: "Çocuğun saldırganlığı, ebeveynleri için bir endişe kaynağıydı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'saldırganlık',
      quest: 'aggression'),
  Words(
      front:
          "He works in the agricultural sector, growing fruits and vegetables .",
      back: "Tarım sektöründe çalışıyor, meyve ve sebze yetiştiriyor .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'tarım',
      quest: 'agricultural'),
  Words(
      front: "The king's advisor was a trusted aide who offered him counsel .",
      back: "Kralın danışmanı, ona öğüt veren güvenilir bir yardımcısıydı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'emir kulu',
      quest: 'aide'),
  Words(
      front: "The plan has some flaws, albeit minor ones .",
      back: "Planın bazı kusurları var, yine de önemsiz .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'yine',
      quest: 'albeit'),
  Words(
      front: "The fire alarm went off, alerting everyone to the danger .",
      back: "Yangın alarmı çaldı ve herkesi tehlikeden haberdar etti .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'alarma geçmek',
      quest: 'alert'),
  Words(
      front: "Have you ever seen a movie about aliens from outer space?",
      back: "Uzaylılar hakkında uzaydan bir film gördünüz mü?",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'uzaylı',
      quest: 'alien'),
  Words(
      front: "The soldiers aligned themselves in a straight line .",
      back: "Askerler kendilerini düz bir çizgi halinde sıraladılar .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'sıralanmak',
      quest: 'align'),
  Words(
      front: "The alignment of the planets is a rare astronomical phenomenon .",
      back: "Gezegenlerin hizalanması nadir bir astronomi olayıdır .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'sıra',
      quest: 'alignment'),
  Words(
      front:
          "They are alike in many ways, but they also have some differences .",
      back: "Birçok yönden benzeşiyorlar, ancak bazı farklılıkları da var .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'benzeyen',
      quest: 'alike'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The police are investigating the allegations of corruption against the politician .",
      back: "Polis, siyasetçiye yönelik yolsuzluk suçlamalarını araştırıyor .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'suçlama',
      quest: 'allegation'),
  Words(
      front: "He alleged that the company was mistreating its employees .",
      back: "Şirketin çalışanlarına kötü muamele ettiğini iddia etti .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'iddia etmek',
      quest: 'allege'),
  Words(
      front: "The politician was allegedly involved in a bribery scandal .",
      back: "Siyasetçi, iddiaya göre bir rüşvet skandalına karışmıştı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'iddiaya göre',
      quest: 'allegedly'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The two countries formed a strong alliance to defend against a common enemy .",
      back:
          "İki ülke, ortak bir düşmana karşı savunmak için güçlü bir ittifak kurdu .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'antlaşma',
      quest: 'alliance'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The teacher gave each student a small allowance for school supplies .",
      back: "Öğretmen, her öğrenciye okul malzemeleri için az bir izin verdi .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'izin',
      quest: 'allowance'),
  Words(
      front: "The United States and France are long-standing allies .",
      back:
          "Amerika Birleşik Devletleri ve Fransa uzun süredir müttefik ülkelerdir .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'müttefik ülke',
      quest: 'ally'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The ambassador represents her country's interests in a foreign nation .",
      back: "Büyükelçi, ülkesinin çıkarlarını yabancı bir ülkede temsil eder .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'elçi',
      quest: 'ambassador'),
  Words(
      front: "The legislators are proposing amendments to the tax code .",
      back: "Yasama organı üyeleri, vergi kodunda değişiklikler öneriyor .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'düzeltmek',
      quest: 'amend'),
  Words(
      front: "The amendment to the constitution failed to pass .",
      back: "Anayasaya getirilen değişiklik kabul edilmedi .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'yasayı değiştirme',
      quest: 'amendment'),
  Words(
      front: "He felt lost amid the chaos of the city .",
      back: "Şehrin karmaşası içinde kendini kaybolmuş hissetti .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'arasında',
      quest: 'amid'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The teacher used an analogy to explain a complex scientific concept .",
      back:
          "Öğretmen, karmaşık bir bilimsel kavramı açıklamak için mukayese kullandı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'mukayese',
      quest: 'analogy'),
  Words(
      front: "The ship dropped anchor in the calm bay .",
      back: "Gemi, sakin koyda demir attı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'demir atmak',
      quest: 'anchor'),
  Words(
      front:
          "Many cultures depict angels as winged beings with a divine purpose .",
      back:
          "Birçok kültür, melekleri ilahi bir amaçla kanatlı varlıklar olarak tasvir eder .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'melek',
      quest: 'angel'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The author chose to remain anonymous and did not reveal their identity .",
      back: "Yazar anonim kalmayı tercih etti ve kimliğini açıklamadı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'anonim',
      quest: 'anonymous'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The scientist invented a new apparatus to measure the speed of light .",
      back: "Bilim insanı, ışık hızını ölçmek için yeni bir cihaz icat etti .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'vasıta',
      quest: 'apparatus'),
  Words(
      front: "The delicious food was very appealing to his appetite .",
      back: "Lezzetli yemek iştahına çok çekici geliyordu .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'iştah',
      quest: 'appetite'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The audience applauded thunderously after the singer's performance .",
      back: "Şarkıcının performansından sonra seyirci coşkuyla alkışladı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'alkışlamak',
      quest: 'applaud'),
  Words(
      front: "These safety regulations are not applicable to all situations .",
      back:
          "Bu güvenlik yönetmelikleri tüm durumlar için uygulanabilir değildir .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'uygulanabilir',
      quest: 'applicable'),
  Words(
      front: "The board of directors appointed a new CEO to lead the company .",
      back: "Yönetim kurulu şirketi yönetecek yeni bir CEO atadı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'atamak',
      quest: 'appoint'),
  Words(
      front: "She expressed her appreciation for the thoughtful gift .",
      back: "Düşünceli hediye için takdirini ifade etti .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'takdir',
      quest: 'appreciation'),
  Words(
      front: "The judge's decision seemed arbitrary and unfair .",
      back: "Hakimin kararı keyfi ve haksız görünüyordu .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'keyfi',
      quest: 'arbitrary'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The building's architectural design is both impressive and functional .",
      back: "Binanın mimari tasarımı hem etkileyici hem de işlevseldir .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'mimarlığa ait',
      quest: 'architectural'),
  Words(
      front:
          "Important documents are stored in the company archives for future reference .",
      back:
          "Önemli belgeler, gelecekte referans olması için şirket arşivlerinde saklanmaktadır .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'arşiv',
      quest: 'archive'),
  Words(
      front: "He is arguably the greatest basketball player of all time .",
      back: "Muhakkak ki tüm zamanların en iyi basketbol oyuncusudur .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'muhtemelen',
      quest: 'arguably'),
  Words(
      front: "He raised his arm to signal for a taxi .",
      back: "Taksi çağırmak için kolunu kaldırdı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'kol',
      quest: 'arm'),
  Words(
      front: "The programmer created a complex array to store the data .",
      back: "Programcı, verileri depolamak için karmaşık bir dizi oluşturdu .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'sıralamak',
      quest: 'array'),
  Words(
      front: "She was unable to articulate her thoughts clearly .",
      back: "Düşüncelerini net bir şekilde ifade edemedi .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'söylemek',
      quest: 'articulate'),
  Words(
      front: "The fireplace was filled with ashes after the fire died down .",
      back: "Ateş söndükten sonra şömine kül doldu .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'kül',
      quest: 'ash'),
  Words(
      front: "She has a strong aspiration to become a doctor and help people .",
      back:
          "Doktor olmak ve insanlara yardım etmek için büyük bir hevesi var .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'büyük amaç',
      quest: 'aspiration'),
  Words(
      front:
          "He aspires to travel the world and experience different cultures .",
      back:
          "Dünyayı gezmek ve farklı kültürleri deneyimlemek için hevesleniyor .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'heveslenmek',
      quest: 'aspire'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The assassination of the political leader plunged the country into chaos .",
      back: "Siyasi liderin suikastı, ülkeyi kaosa sürükledi .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'suikast',
      quest: 'assassination'),
  Words(
      front: "The robber assaulted the old woman and stole her purse .",
      back: "Soyguncu yaşlı kadına saldırdı ve çantasını çaldı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'saldırmak',
      quest: 'assault'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The workers assembled in the factory to discuss their working conditions .",
      back:
          "İşçiler çalışma koşullarını görüşmek üzere fabrikada toplandılar .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'toplaşmak',
      quest: 'assemble'),
  Words(
      front:
          "There will be a school assembly tomorrow morning to announce the new schedule .",
      back: "Yeni programı duyurmak için yarın sabah okul toplantısı olacak .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'toplantı',
      quest: 'assembly'),
  Words(
      front:
          "He asserted his dominance in the competition and won first place .",
      back: "Yarışmada hakimiyetini sürdürdü ve birinci oldu .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'öne sürmek',
      quest: 'assert'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The lawyer made a strong assertion that his client was innocent .",
      back:
          "Avukat, müvekkilinin masum olduğuna dair güçlü bir iddia ortaya attı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'iddia',
      quest: 'assertion'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The therapist offered him reassurance and helped him manage his anxiety .",
      back:
          "Terapist ona güvence verdi ve kaygısıyla başa çıkmasına yardım etti .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'güvence',
      quest: 'assurance'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The refugees sought asylum in a neighboring country to escape the war .",
      back:
          "Mülteciler savaşa kaçmak için komşu bir ülkede sığınma hakkı aradılar .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'barınak',
      quest: 'asylum'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The war crimes committed by the soldiers were considered atrocities .",
      back: "Askerlerin işlediği savaş suçları vahşet olarak kabul edildi .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'berbatlık',
      quest: 'atrocity'),
  Words(
      front:
          "Through hard work and dedication, she finally attained her goal of becoming a lawyer .",
      back:
          "Çok çalışarak ve özveriyle nihayet avukat olma hedefini gerçekleştirdi .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'elde etmek',
      quest: 'attain'),
  Words(
      front: "The lawyer represented her client in court .",
      back: "Avukat, müvekkilini mahkemede temsil etti .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'dava vekili',
      quest: 'attorney'),
  Words(
      front: "He attributed his success to hard work and perseverance .",
      back: "Başarısını sıkı çalışmaya ve azme bağladı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'bağlamak',
      quest: 'attribute'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The company is undergoing an audit to ensure its financial records are accurate .",
      back:
          "Şirket, mali kayıtlarının doğru olduğundan emin olmak için denetimden geçiyor .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'hesapları denetlemek',
      quest: 'audit'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The antique furniture store sells authentic pieces from different historical periods .",
      back:
          "Antika mobilya mağazası, farklı tarih dönemlerinden orijinal parçalar satıyor .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'özgün',
      quest: 'authentic'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The manager is not authorized to make such a large purchase without approval .",
      back:
          "Müdür, onay almadan bu kadar büyük bir satın alma işlemi yapmaya yetkili değildir .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'yetki vermek',
      quest: 'authorize'),
  Words(
      front: "He arrived at the meeting in a luxury auto .",
      back: "Toplantıya lüks bir otomobil ile geldi .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'otomobil',
      quest: 'auto'),
  Words(
      front:
          "Scotland has a strong movement for autonomy from the United Kingdom .",
      back:
          "İskoçya, Birleşik Krallık'tan özerklik için güçlü bir harekete sahip .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'özerklik',
      quest: 'autonomy'),
  Words(
      front:
          "We will check the availability of the rooms before booking our vacation .",
      back:
          "Tatilimizi rezerve etmeden önce odaların müsaitliğini kontrol edeceğiz .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'geçerlilik',
      quest: 'availability'),
  Words(
      front: "He is eagerly awaiting the results of his job application .",
      back: "İş başvurusunun sonuçlarını heyecanla bekliyor .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'gözlemek',
      quest: 'await'),
  Words(
      front: "The play took place against a backdrop of a bustling city .",
      back: "Oyun, hareketli bir şehrin arka planında gerçekleşti .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'arka fon eklemek',
      quest: 'backdrop'),
  Words(
      front:
          "She received a lot of backing from her family and friends during her difficult time .",
      back: "Zor zamanlarında ailesi ve arkadaşlarından çok destek aldı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'yardım',
      quest: 'backing'),
  Words(
      front:
          "He always keeps a backup of his important files in case of a computer crash .",
      back:
          "Bilgisayar çökmesi durumunda önemli dosyalarının her zaman bir yedeğini tutar .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'yedek',
      quest: 'backup'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The suspect was released on bail after paying a large sum of money .",
      back:
          "Şüpheli, yüklü bir miktar para ödeyerek kefaletle serbest bırakıldı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'kefalet',
      quest: 'bail'),
  Words(
      front:
          "Voters cast their ballots in the election for their preferred candidate .",
      back:
          "Seçmenler, oy pusulalarını seçtikleri aday için seçimde kullandılar .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'oy vermek',
      quest: 'ballot'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The protesters held banners with slogans demanding social justice .",
      back:
          "Protestocular, sosyal adalet talep eden sloganlar bulunan pankartlar taşıdılar .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'pankart',
      quest: 'banner'),
  Words(
      front: "He barely escaped the accident with just a few scratches .",
      back: "Kazadan sadece birkaç sıyrıkla zar zor kurtuldu .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'çıkarmak',
      quest: 'bare'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The pirates buried their treasure in a barrel on a deserted island .",
      back: "Korsanlar hazinelerini ıssız bir adada bir varile gömdüler .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'varil',
      quest: 'barrel'),
  Words(
      front: "The baseball player swung the bat and hit a home run .",
      back: "Beyzbol oyuncusu sopayı salladı ve bir sayılık home run yaptı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'yarasa',
      quest: 'bat'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The soldiers bravely fought on the battlefield despite the dangers .",
      back: "Askerler tehlikelere rağmen savaş alanında cesurca savaştılar .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'savaş alanı',
      quest: 'battlefield'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The winner of the race will be crowned with a laurel bay wreath .",
      back:
          "Yarışın kazananı defne yapraklarından oluşan bir çelenkle taçlandırılacak .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'defne',
      quest: 'bay'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The scientist studied the properties of light beams using a laser .",
      back:
          "Bilim insanı, lazer kullanarak ışık ışınlarının özelliklerini inceledi .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'ışın',
      quest: 'beam'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The fairy tale depicted a fearsome beast guarding a hidden treasure .",
      back:
          "Masal, gizli bir hazineyi koruyan korkunç bir canavarı tasvir ediyordu .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'hayvan',
      quest: 'beast'),
  Words(
      front: "The lawyer spoke on behalf of his client in court .",
      back: "Avukat, mahkemede müvekkili adına konuştu .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'biri adına',
      quest: 'behalf'),
  Words(
      front:
          "She is her beloved grandmother, and they have a very close relationship .",
      back: "O, sevgili büyükannesi ve çok yakın bir ilişkileri var .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'sevgili',
      quest: 'beloved'),
  Words(
      front: "He sat on a park bench and enjoyed the sunshine .",
      back: "Parktaki bir sıraya oturdu ve güneşin tadını çıkardı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'sıra',
      quest: 'bench'),
  Words(
      front:
          "This new software program sets the benchmark for performance in its category .",
      back:
          "Bu yeni yazılım programı, kendi kategorisinde performans için bir değerlendirme standardı oluşturuyor .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'değerlendirme',
      quest: 'benchmark'),
  Words(
      front: "The lost treasure is hidden somewhere beneath the castle ruins .",
      back: "Kayıp hazine, kale kalıntılarının altında bir yerde gizlidir .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'altında',
      quest: 'beneath'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The scholarship will be awarded to the most deserving beneficiary .",
      back: "Burs, en hak sahibi olan kişiye verilecektir .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'hak sahibi',
      quest: 'beneficiary'),
  Words(
      front: "He felt betrayed by his closest friend who revealed his secret .",
      back:
          "En yakın arkadaşı sırrını açıklayarak ona ihanet ettiğini hissetti .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'ihanet etmek',
      quest: 'betray'),
  Words(
      front: "Her wrists were bound with rope to prevent her from escaping .",
      back: "Kaçmasını önlemek için bilekleri ip ile bağlandı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'ciltlemek',
      quest: 'bind'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The biography tells the story of the famous scientist's life and achievements .",
      back:
          "Biyografi, ünlü bilim insanının hayatını ve başarılarını anlatan bir yaşam öyküsüdür .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'yaşam öyküsü',
      quest: 'biography'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The chess piece called the bishop can move diagonally across the board .",
      back:
          "Piskopos adı verilen satranç taşı, tahtada çapraz olarak hareket edebilir .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'piskopos',
      quest: 'bishop'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The movie had a bizarre plot with strange characters and events .",
      back:
          "Filmin, garip karakterler ve olaylar içeren acayip bir konusu vardı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'garip',
      quest: 'bizarre'),
  Words(
      front: "The knife had a sharp blade that could easily cut through meat .",
      back: "Bıçağın etleri kolayca kesebilecek keskin bir ağzı vardı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'bıçak ağzı',
      quest: 'blade'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The explosion caused a loud blast that shattered windows in nearby buildings .",
      back:
          "Patlama, yakındaki binalardaki pencereleri parçalayan yüksek sesli bir gürültüye neden oldu .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'büyük patlama',
      quest: 'blast'),
  Words(
      front: "The injured athlete continued to bleed after the accident .",
      back: "Yaralanan sporcu kaza sonrası kan kaybetmeye devam etti .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'para sızdırmak',
      quest: 'bleed'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The artist skillfully blended different colors to create a beautiful painting .",
      back:
          "Sanatçı, güzel bir resim oluşturmak için farklı renkleri ustaca karıştırdı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'karıştırmak',
      quest: 'blend'),
  Words(
      front: "She blessed her children before they left for school .",
      back: "Çocukları okula gitmeden önce kutsadı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'kutsamak',
      quest: 'bless'),
  Words(
      front: "Good health and happiness are considered blessings in life .",
      back: "Sağlık ve mutluluk, hayattaki nimetler olarak kabul edilir .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'nimet',
      quest: 'blessing'),
  Words(
      front:
          "He avoided boasting about his achievements, even though he was very proud .",
      back:
          "Her ne kadar çok gurur duysa da başarılarıyla övünmekten kaçındı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'övünmek',
      quest: 'boast'),
  Words(
      front:
          "He received a bonus at the end of the year for his outstanding work performance .",
      back: "Yıl sonunda olağanüstü iş performansı nedeniyle bir bonus aldı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'bonus',
      quest: 'bonus'),
  Words(
      front: "The loud boom of thunder startled everyone in the house .",
      back: "Yüksek sesli gürültü herkesi korkuttu .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'patlama sesi',
      quest: 'boom'),
  Words(
      front: "The ball bounced high in the air after it was thrown .",
      back: "Top atıldıktan sonra havaya vurdu .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'sektirmek',
      quest: 'bounce'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The new agreement established clear boundaries between the two countries .",
      back: "Yeni anlaşma, iki ülke arasındaki net sınırlar belirledi .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'sınır',
      quest: 'boundary'),
  Words(
      front: "The archer elegantly drew her bow and released the arrow .",
      back: "Okçu zarif bir şekilde yayını çekti ve oku bıraktı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'yay',
      quest: 'bow'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The company is taking legal action against them for breach of contract .",
      back:
          "Şirket, sözleşme ihlali nedeniyle onlara karşı yasal işlem başlatıyor .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'uymama',
      quest: 'breach'),
  Words(
      front: "His car suffered a complete breakdown on the highway .",
      back: "Arabası otoyolda tamamen bozuldu .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'bozulma',
      quest: 'breakdown'),
  Words(
      front:
          "The scientific breakthrough led to significant advancements in medical treatment .",
      back: "Bilimsel ilerleme, tıbbi tedavide önemli gelişmelere yol açtı .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'ilerleme',
      quest: 'breakthrough'),
  Words(
      front: "I'm trying to grow a new breed of tomato .",
      back: "Yeni bir domates türü yetiştirmeye çalışıyorum .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'cins',
      quest: 'breed'),
  Words(
      front:
          "He signed up for a broadband internet connection to enjoy faster download speeds .",
      back:
          "Daha hızlı indirme hızlarından yararlanmak için genişbant internet bağlantısına kaydoldu .",
      list: 'C1',
      answer: 'genişbant',
      quest: 'broadband'),
  Words(
    front: "He used a web browser to surf the internet on his computer .",
    back: "Bilgisayarında internette gezinmek için bir tarayıcı kullandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tarayıcı",
    quest: "browser",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He saw a wild animal .",
    back: "Acımasız bir hayvan gördü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "vahşi",
    quest: "brutal",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He jumped into the water .",
    back: "Suya atladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sıçramak",
    quest: "buck",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He needs a good buddy to help him with this task .",
    back: "Bu işte ona yardım edecek iyi bir ahbap gerekiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ahbap",
    quest: "buddy",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The technician added a buffer to prevent data overflow .",
    back: " teknisyen, veri taşmasının önüne geçmek için tampon ekledi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tampon",
    quest: "buffer",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He bulked up for the upcoming boxing match .",
    back: "Yaklaşan boks maçı için kas yaptı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "büyütmek",
    quest: "bulk",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He felt burdened by his responsibilities .",
    back: "Sorumluluklarının ağırlığı altında eziliyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sırtına yüklemek",
    quest: "burden",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The complex bureaucracy slowed down the process .",
    back: "Karmaşık bürokrasi süreci yavaşlattı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bürokrasi",
    quest: "bureaucracy",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The Pharaoh's burial was filled with treasures .",
    back: "Firavun'un gömme töreni hazinelerle doluydu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "gömme",
    quest: "burial",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The balloon suddenly burst in mid-air .",
    back: "Balon aniden havada patladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "patlamak",
    quest: "burst",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He organized his tools in a neat cabinet .",
    back: "Aletlerini düzgün bir dolaba yerleştirdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dolap",
    quest: "cabinet",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He made complex calculations to solve the problem .",
    back: "Sorunu çözmek için karmaşık hesaplamalar yaptı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hesaplama",
    quest: "calculation",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The artist used a canvas to paint his masterpiece .",
    back: "Sanatçı, başyapıtını boyamak için bir tuval kullandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tuval",
    quest: "canvas",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "She demonstrated her capability to lead the team .",
    back: "Takımı yönetme kabiliyetini gösterdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kabiliyet",
    quest: "capability",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "Kapitalizm, özel mülkiyete ve serbest piyasaya dayanan ekonomik sistemdir .",
    back:
        "Capitalism is an economic system based on private ownership and free market .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sermayecilik",
    quest: "capitalism",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Sermayeci, yatırımlarıyla kâr elde etmeyi amaçlayan kişidir .",
    back:
        "A capitalist is a person who invests money with the aim of making a profit .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sermayeci",
    quest: "capitalist",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Gemi, büyük miktarda kargo taşıyordu .",
    back: "The ship was carrying a large amount of cargo .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kargo",
    quest: "cargo",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Malların taşınması için lojistik şirketiyle anlaştı .",
    back: "He contracted a logistics company for the carriage of goods .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "taşımacılık",
    quest: "carriage",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Heykeltraş, mermeri dikkatlice oydu .",
    back: "The sculptor carefully carved the marble .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "oymak",
    quest: "carve",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Kazanmayı seven arkadaşıyla birlikte casinoya gitti .",
    back: "He went to the casino with his friend who loves to gamble .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kumarhane",
    quest: "casino",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Kazada ölenlerin sayısı oldukça yüksekti .",
    back: "The number of casualties in the accident was very high .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kazazede",
    quest: "casualty",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He looked at the furniture store's catalogue to buy furniture .",
    back: "Mobilya almak için mobilya mağazasının kataloğuna baktı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "katalog",
    quest: "catalogue",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Parti için yiyecek ve içecek temin etti .",
    back: "He catered food and drinks for the party .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "temin etmek",
    quest: "cater",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Çiftlikteki sığırlar sağlıklı görünüyordu .",
    back: "The cattle on the farm looked healthy .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sığır",
    quest: "cattle",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Geçerken yoldan geçen arabalara dikkat etti .",
    back: "He paid attention to the cars passing by on the road .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dikkat",
    quest: "caution",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Tedbirli bir insan olduğu için her zaman bir planı vardı .",
    back: "As a cautious person, he always had a plan .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tedbirli",
    quest: "cautious",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Artık şikayetleri dinlemekten vazgeçti .",
    back: "He finally ceased listening to the complaints .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "son vermek",
    quest: "cease",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Visitors showed respect while walking through the cemetery .",
    back: "Ziyaretçiler, mezarlıkta dolaşırken saygı gösterdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "mezarlık",
    quest: "cemetery",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "A specially designed chamber was used for the experiment .",
    back: "Deney için özel olarak tasarlanmış bir chamber kullanıldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "oda",
    quest: "chamber",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "It was impossible to find anything due to the chaos in the room .",
    back: "Odadaki karmaşa nedeniyle bir şey bulmak imkansızdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "karmaşa",
    quest: "chaos",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "If we need to characterize Roman's personality, he is a loyal and honest person .",
    back:
        "Romanın kişiliğini nitelendirmek gerekirse, o sadık ve dürüst bir insandır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "nitelendirmek",
    quest: "characterize",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He was captivated by the charm of an old building .",
    back: "Eski bir binanın cazibesine kapıldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "cazibe",
    quest: "charm",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Şirket, yeni buluşu için patent vermek için başvuruda bulundu .",
    back: "The company applied for a charter to patent their new invention .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "patent vermek",
    quest: "charter",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Hastalığı kronikti ve tedavisi zordu .",
    back: "His illness was chronic and difficult to treat .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kronik",
    quest: "chronic",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Büyük bir bilgi yığını ile karşı karşıya kaldı .",
    back: "He was faced with a huge chunk of information .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yığın",
    quest: "chunk",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Haberin gazetelerde dolaşması birkaç gün sürdü .",
    back: "It took a few days for the news to circulate in the newspapers .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "akımını sağlamak",
    quest: "circulate",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Derginin geniş bir sürümü vardı .",
    back: "The magazine had a wide circulation .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sürüm",
    quest: "circulation",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Yurttaşlık haklarını korumak önemlidir .",
    back: "It is important to protect citizenship rights .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yurttaşlık",
    quest: "citizenship",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Şehrin iyileştirilmesine yönelik civic projeler düzenlendi .",
    back: "Civic projects were organized for the improvement of the city .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "şehir ile ilgili",
    quest: "civic",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Saldırıya siviller de dahil oldu .",
    back: "The attack also involved civilians .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sivil",
    quest: "civilian",
  ),
  Words(
    back: "Cümlede kullanılan kelimelerin berraklığı anlamı netleştirdi .",
    front: "Clarity in the words used in the sentence made the meaning clear .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "berraklık",
    quest: "clarity",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "İki fikir çarpışması, çözüme ulaşmayı zorlaştırdı .",
    front: "The clash of two ideas made it difficult to reach a solution .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "çarpışma",
    quest: "clash",
  ),

  Words(
    back:
        "Bilim insanları, hayvanları sınıflandırma sistemleri geliştirdiler .",
    front: "Scientists developed classification systems for animals .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sınıflandırma",
    quest: "classification",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Umutsuzluğa tutunmaktan kendini alıkoyamadı .",
    front: "He couldn't stop himself from clinging to hope .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tutunmak",
    quest: "cling",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Doktor, hastayı kapsamlı bir klinik muayeneye aldı .",
    front: "The doctor gave the patient a thorough clinical examination .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "klinik",
    quest: "clinical",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Okullar yaz tatili için kapanacak .",
    front: "Schools will be closed for summer vacation .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kapanma",
    quest: "closure",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Yıldızlar, gece gökyüzünde kümeler halinde parlıyordu .",
    front: "Stars twinkled in clusters in the night sky .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "küme",
    quest: "cluster",
  ),

  Words(
    back:
        "Farklı partilerin bir araya gelerek oluşturduğu koalisyon hükümeti kuruldu .",
    front:
        "A coalition government formed by different parties was established .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "birleşme",
    quest: "coalition",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Ev, güzel bir sahil kasabasındaydı .",
    front: "The house was in a beautiful coastal town .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sahil",
    quest: "coastal",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Parıltılı bir kokteyl sipariş etti .",
    front: "He ordered a fancy cocktail .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kokteyl",
    quest: "cocktail",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bilişsel yetenekleri yaşla birlikte azaldı .",
    front: "His cognitive abilities declined with age .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bilişsel",
    quest: "cognitive",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Tatillerimiz tesadüfen aynı zamana denk geldi .",
    front: "Our vacations coincided by chance .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kesişme",
    quest: "coincide",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Projeyi başarıyla tamamlamak için işbirliği yaptılar .",
    front: "They collaborated to successfully complete the project .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "işbirliği yapma",
    quest: "collaborate",
  ),
  Words(
    back: "Projenin başarısı, ekiplerin mükemmel işbirliğine bağlıydı .",
    front:
        "The success of the project depended on the excellent collaboration of the teams .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "işbirliği",
    quest: "collaboration",
  ),

  Words(
    back:
        "Toplu taşıma araçları genellikle sabah ve akşam saatlerinde kalabalık olur .",
    front:
        "Public transportation vehicles are usually crowded in the mornings and evenings .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "toplu",
    quest: "collective",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Kazada iki araba çarpışma yaşadı .",
    front: "Two cars collided in the accident .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "çarpışma",
    quest: "collision",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Osmanlı İmparatorluğu, sömürgeci bir güç olarak görülüyordu .",
    front: "The Ottoman Empire was seen as a colonial power .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sömürge",
    quest: "colonial",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Tanınmış köşe yazarı, güncel olaylar hakkında yorum yazdı .",
    front: "The well-known columnist wrote comments on current events .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "köşe yazarı",
    quest: "columnist",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Şiddetli muharebe günlerce sürdü .",
    front: "The fierce combat lasted for days .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "muharebe",
    quest: "combat",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Dersin sonunda derse başlamayı teklif etti .",
    front:
        "He suggested commencing the lesson at the end of the introduction .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "başlatmak",
    quest: "commence",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Gazeteci, haber üzerine bir yorum yaptı .",
    front: "The journalist made a commentary on the news .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yorum",
    quest: "commentary",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Spiker, maçın heyecanını yorumcu olarak aktardı .",
    front:
        "The commentator conveyed the excitement of the match as a commentator .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yorumcu",
    quest: "commentator",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Ülke, dış ticaret sayesinde ekonomisini büyüttü .",
    front: "The country grew its economy thanks to commerce .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ticaret",
    quest: "commerce",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Şirket, fuara bir komiser gönderdi .",
    front: "The company sent a commissioner to the fair .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "delege",
    quest: "commissioner",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Kahve, dünya çapında önemli bir ticaret metaasıdır .",
    front: "Coffee is an important commodity traded worldwide .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "alıp satılan şey",
    quest: "commodity",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Yolculuk boyunca refakatçisi ona destek oldu .",
    front: "His companion supported him throughout the journey .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "refakatçi",
    quest: "companion",
  ),
  Words(
    back: "Bu iki ürün birbirine kıyaslanabilir .",
    front: "These two products are comparable .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kıyaslanabilir",
    quest: "comparable",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Hayvanlara karşı merhamet göstermeliyiz .",
    front: "We should show compassion towards animals .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "merhamet",
    quest: "compassion",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Onu gitmeye zorlamak zorunda kaldım .",
    front: "I had to compel him to go .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "zorlamak",
    quest: "compel",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Film, izleyicileri için zorlayıcı bir konuyu ele alıyor .",
    front: "The film tackles a compelling topic for viewers .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "zorlu",
    quest: "compelling",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Kazaya uğradığı için tazminat talebinde bulundu .",
    front: "He filed a compensation claim because of the accident .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "telafi etmek",
    quest: "compensate",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Uzun çalışma saatleri için ekstra maaş gibi bir telafi hak ediyor .",
    front:
        "He deserves some compensation, like extra pay, for the long working hours .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "telafi",
    quest: "compensation",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Yeterliği sayesinde terfi aldı .",
    front: "He got promoted thanks to his competence .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yeterlik",
    quest: "competence",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bu konuda yetkili birine danışmalısınız .",
    front: "You should consult someone competent in this matter .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yetkili",
    quest: "competent",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Verileri derleyerek bir rapor hazırladı .",
    front: "He compiled a report by compiling the data .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "derlemek",
    quest: "compile",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bu iki renk birbirini tamamlıyor .",
    front: "These two colors complement each other .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tamamlamak",
    quest: "complement",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Konunun karmaşıklığı nedeniyle anlamakta zorlandım .",
    front:
        "I had difficulty understanding due to the complexity of the subject .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "karmaşıklık",
    quest: "complexity",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Kurallara riayet etmek önemlidir .",
    front: "It is important to comply with the rules .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "riayet",
    quest: "compliance",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "İşlemdeki bu komplikasyon çözülmedikçe ilerleyemeyiz .",
    front:
        "We cannot proceed until this complication in the process is resolved .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "komplikasyon",
    quest: "complication",
  ),
  Words(
    back: "Kurallara boyun eğmek zorunda kaldı .",
    front: "He had to comply with the rules .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "boyun eğmek",
    quest: "comply",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Yarışmanın kompozisyonu şu şekildeydi: koşu, yüzme, bisiklet .",
    front:
        "The composition of the competition was as follows: running, swimming, cycling .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kompozisyon",
    quest: "composition",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Tartışmada her iki taraf da bir anlaşmaya vardı .",
    front: "In the argument, both sides reached a compromise .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "anlaşmak",
    quest: "compromise",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bilgisayar, karmaşık hesaplamaları saniyeler içinde yapabilir .",
    front: "The computer can perform complex computations in seconds .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hesaplamak",
    quest: "compute",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Suçunu gizlemeye çalıştı .",
    front: "He tried to conceal his crime .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "gizlemek",
    quest: "conceal",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Rakibinin gücünü kabul etmek zorunda kaldı .",
    front: "He had to concede his opponent's strength .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kabullenmek",
    quest: "concede",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Mühendis, yeni bir köprü tasarladı .",
    front: "The engineer conceived a new bridge design .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tasarlamak",
    quest: "conceive",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Soyut bir düşünceyi somutlaştırmak zordur .",
    front: "It is difficult to concretize an abstract conception .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "düşünce",
    quest: "conception",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Tartışmada bazı tavizler vermek zorunda kaldık .",
    front: "We had to make some concessions in the discussion .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "taviz",
    quest: "concession",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Suçluyu müebbet hapse mahkum ettiler .",
    front: "They condemned the criminal to life imprisonment .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "mahkum etmek",
    quest: "condemn",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Doktorlar hastayla konferans yaptılar .",
    front: "The doctors conferred with the patient .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "müzakere etmek",
    quest: "confer",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Rahip, günah çıkarmak isteyenlerle görüştü .",
    front: "The priest met with those who wanted to confess .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "günah çıkarma",
    quest: "confession",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Telefonun yeni konfigürasyonu daha kullanışlı .",
    front: "The new configuration of the phone is more user-friendly .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "biçim",
    quest: "configuration",
  ),
  Words(
    back: "Onu bodrum katına hapsetti .",
    front: "He confined him to the basement .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sınırlandırmak",
    quest: "confine",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Siparişinizin onaylanması için e-posta kontrol edin .",
    front: "Check your email for confirmation of your order .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "onay",
    quest: "confirmation",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Polis memuru şüpheliyi suçla yüzleştirdi .",
    front: "The police officer confronted the suspect with the accusation .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yüzleştirmek",
    quest: "confront",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Görüşmedeki sert yüzleşme ortamı gerginliği artırdı .",
    front: "The tense confrontation during the meeting increased the tension .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yüzleşme",
    quest: "confrontation",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Başarısını tebrik etmek için ona çiçek gönderdim .",
    front: "I sent him flowers to congratulate him on his success .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tebrik etmek",
    quest: "congratulate",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Kilisenin cemaati Pazar ayinine katıldı .",
    front: "The congregation of the church attended the Sunday service .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "topluluk",
    quest: "congregation",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Kongresel kararın oylanması yarın yapılacak .",
    front: "The voting on the congressional decision will be held tomorrow .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kongresel",
    quest: "congressional",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Romalılar, geniş toprakları fethetti .",
    front: "The Romans conquered vast territories .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "fethetmek",
    quest: "conquer",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Vicdanı rahat değildi .",
    front: "His conscience was not clear .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "vicdan",
    quest: "conscience",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bilincinizi kaybettiniz mi?",
    front: "Did you lose consciousness?",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bilinç",
    quest: "consciousness",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "İki gün üst üste aynı filmi izledim .",
    front: "I watched the same movie two consecutive days .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ardışık",
    quest: "consecutive",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Toplantıda bir fikir birliğine varılmadı .",
    front: "No consensus was reached at the meeting .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "fikir birliği",
    quest: "consensus",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bu projenin yapılması için izniniz gerekiyor .",
    front: "Your consent is required for this project to proceed .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "razı olmak",
    quest: "consent",
  ),
  Words(
    back: "Enerjiyi korumak için ampulleri değiştirdik .",
    front: "We changed the bulbs to conserve energy .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "korumak",
    quest: "conserve",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Davranışlarındaki tutarlılığa hayran kaldım .",
    front: "I admired the consistency in his behavior .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tutarlılık",
    quest: "consistency",
  ),

  Words(
    back:
        "Kazanılan başarıyı sağlamlaştırmak için yeni stratejiler geliştirildi .",
    front:
        "New strategies were developed to consolidate the achieved success .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sağlamlaştırmak",
    quest: "consolidate",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Milletvekili, seçim bölgesindeki halkın sorunlarını dile getirdi .",
    front: "The MP voiced the problems of the people in his constituency .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "seçim bölgesi",
    quest: "constituency",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bu elementler bir atomu oluşturur .",
    front: "These elements constitute an atom .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "oluşturmak",
    quest: "constitute",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Ülkenin en yüksek hukuk metni anayasadır .",
    front: "The constitution is the highest legal text of the country .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "anayasa",
    quest: "constitution",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bu karar anayasal mı?",
    front: "Is this decision constitutional?",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "anayasal",
    quest: "constitutional",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bütçe kısıtlamaları nedeniyle projeyi tamamlamakta zorlandık .",
    front:
        "We faced difficulties completing the project due to budget constraints .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kısıtlama",
    quest: "constraint",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The doctor had a consultation with the patient .",
    back: "Doktor hastayla bir danışma yaptı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "danışma",
    quest: "consultation",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Gelecek hakkında uzun uzun düşünüp taşındı .",
    front: "He contemplated at length about the future .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "düşünüp taşınmak",
    quest: "contemplate",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Davranışlarına karşı aşağılama hissettim .",
    front: "I felt contempt for his behavior .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "aşağılama",
    quest: "contempt",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Şampiyonluk için yarışan iki güçlü rakip vardı .",
    front: "There were two strong contenders competing for the championship .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "rakip",
    quest: "contender",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bu konuda uzmanlarla uğraşmak zorunda kaldık .",
    front: "We had to contend with experts on this issue .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "uğraşmak",
    quest: "contend",
  ),
  Words(
    back: "Web sitesinin içeriğini güncelledik .",
    front: "We updated the content of the website .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "içerik",
    quest: "content",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "İki takım şampiyonluk için sürekli bir yarışma içindeydi .",
    front: "The two teams were in constant contention for the championship .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yarışma",
    quest: "contention",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Yağmur hiç durmadan yağıyordu .",
    front: "The rain was falling continually .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hiç durmadan",
    quest: "continually",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bu inşaatın müteahhidi kim?",
    front: "Who is the contractor for this construction?",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "müteahhit",
    quest: "contractor",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Onun sözleri davranışlarıyla bir tezat oluşturuyor .",
    front: "His words contradict his behavior .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tezat",
    quest: "contradiction",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Emirlere zıt hareket etmeyin .",
    front: "Do not act contrary to the orders .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "zıt",
    quest: "contrary",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Dergiye düzenli olarak yazı yazar .",
    front: "He is a regular contributor to the magazine .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yazar",
    quest: "contributor",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Paradan elektriğe enerji dönüşümü gerçekleşti .",
    front: "The conversion of energy from money to electricity took place .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dönüşüm",
    quest: "conversion",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Jüri onu suçlu buldu .",
    front: "The jury convicted him .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "suçlu bulmak",
    quest: "convict",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Başarıya olan inancını kaybetmedi .",
    front: "He did not lose his conviction in success .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "inanç",
    quest: "conviction",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Projeyi tamamlamak için işbirliği yapmak zorundayız .",
    front: "We need to cooperate to complete the project .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "işbirliği yapmak",
    quest: "cooperate",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Polis memuru hırsızı yakaladı .",
    front: "The cop caught the thief .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "polis memuru",
    quest: "cop",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Kablolar bakırdan yapılmıştır .",
    front: "The cables are made of copper .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bakır",
    quest: "copper",
  ),
  Words(
    back: "Yazdığınız eserin telif hakkını korumak önemlidir .",
    front: "It is important to protect the copyright of the work you wrote .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "telif hakkı",
    quest: "copyright",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Metindeki düzeltmeleri kırmızı kalemle işaretledim .",
    front: "I marked the corrections in the text with a red pen .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "düzeltme",
    quest: "correction",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "IQ seviyesi ile okul başarısı arasında bir ilişki var mı?",
    front: "Is there a correlation between IQ level and school success?",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ilişkilendirmek",
    quest: "correlate",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "IQ seviyesi ile okul başarısı arasında pozitif bir korelasyon var .",
    front:
        "There is a positive correlation between IQ level and school success .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bağlılık",
    quest: "correlation",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Sorularınıza mektupla cevap vereceğim .",
    front: "I will correspond to your questions by letter .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tekabül etmek",
    quest: "correspond",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Uzun yıllar boyunca mektuplaştık .",
    front: "We corresponded for many years .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yazışma",
    quest: "correspondence",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Savaş muhabiri, cepheden canlı yayın yaptı .",
    front: "The war correspondent broadcasted live from the front .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "eş",
    quest: "correspondent",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bu renk, kıyafetime tam olarak karşılık geliyor .",
    front: "This color corresponds perfectly to my outfit .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yerini tutan",
    quest: "corresponding",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Yolsuz politikacılar ülkeye zarar veriyor .",
    front: "Corrupt politicians are harming the country .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yozlaşmış",
    quest: "corrupt",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Yolsuzluk her ülkede önemli bir sorundur .",
    front: "Corruption is a major problem in every country .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yolsuzluk",
    quest: "corruption",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bu gezi çok masraflı olacak .",
    front: "This trip will be very costly .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "masraflı",
    quest: "costly",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Meclis üyesi halkın sorunlarını dile getirdi .",
    front: "The councillor voiced the problems of the people .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "meclis üyesi",
    quest: "councillor",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Arkadaşım psikolojik danışmaya başladı .",
    front: "My friend started counselling .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "danışma",
    quest: "counselling",
  ),
  Words(
    back: "Psikolojik sorunlar için bir danışmana danışabilirsiniz .",
    front: "You can consult a counsellor for psychological problems .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "danışman",
    quest: "counsellor",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bankada müşteri sayacı vardı .",
    front: "There was a customer counter at the bank .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tezgah,sayaç",
    quest: "counter",
  ),

  Words(
    back:
        "Uluslararası görüşmelerde Türk heyetinin karşılığı İngiliz büyükelçisiydi .",
    front:
        "The British ambassador was the counterpart of the Turkish delegation in international negotiations .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "meslektaş",
    quest: "counterpart",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Sayısız insan yoksulluk içinde yaşıyor .",
    front: "Countless people live in poverty .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sayısız",
    quest: "countless",
  ),

  Words(
    back:
        "Devlet başkanının ani ölümü siyasi bir darbe olarak değerlendirildi .",
    front:
        "The sudden death of the president was considered a political coup .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "başarılı davranış",
    quest: "coup",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Size karşı her zaman kibar davrandı .",
    front: "He was always courteous to you .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kibarlık",
    quest: "courtesy",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "El işi ürünler satan bir esnaf .",
    front: "A shopkeeper who sells handcrafted products .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "esnaf",
    quest: "craft",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bebek yere doğru süründü .",
    front: "The baby crawled towards the ground .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sürünmek",
    quest: "crawl",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bu romanın yaratıcısı ünlü bir yazar .",
    front: "The creator of this novel is a famous writer .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yaratıcı",
    quest: "creator",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bu haber kaynağının güvenilirliği sorgulanıyor .",
    front: "The credibility of this news source is being questioned .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "güvenilirlik",
    quest: "credibility",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "İddianız inandırıcı değil .",
    front: "Your claim is not credible .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "inandırıcı",
    quest: "credible",
  ),

// "creep" has the same translation as "sürünmek" depending on the context .
// We can keep the existing translation here .

  Words(
    back: "Filmin yönetmeni filmi sert bir şekilde eleştirdi .",
    front: "The film's director harshly critiqued the film .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "eleştirmek",
    quest: "critique",
  ),
  Words(
    back: "Kraliçe taç giydi .",
    front: "The queen wore a crown .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "taç",
    quest: "crown",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Konuşması çok kaba ve ham bir ifade içeriyordu .",
    front: "His speech contained very crude and rude language .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ham",
    quest: "crude",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Kazandığı başarı hayallerini adeta ezdi .",
    front: "The success he achieved crushed his dreams .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ezmek",
    quest: "crush",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Vazo kristalden yapılmıştı .",
    front: "The vase was made of crystal .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kristal",
    quest: "crystal",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bu tarikat bazı garip inançlara sahip .",
    front: "This cult has some strange beliefs .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tarikat",
    quest: "cult",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Toprağı ekip biçmek için traktör kullandılar .",
    front: "They used a tractor to cultivate the land .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ekip biçmek",
    quest: "cultivate",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Doğa merakımı cezbetti .",
    front: "Nature piqued my curiosity .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "merak",
    quest: "curiosity",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Suçlu şu anda gözaltında .",
    front: "The criminal is currently in custody .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "gözaltı",
    quest: "custody",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Dergi, saç kesimi modelleri hakkında bir yazı içeriyordu .",
    front: "The magazine included an article about haircutting styles .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kesim",
    quest: "cutting",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Alaycı bir gülüş attı .",
    front: "He gave a cynical smile .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "alaycı",
    quest: "cynical",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Hasat mevsimi yaklaşırken çiftçiler baraklara taşındı .",
    front: "As the harvest season approached, the farmers moved to the dams .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "barak",
    quest: "dam",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Sigara içmek sağlığınıza zararlıdır .",
    front: "Smoking is damaging to your health .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "zarar verici",
    quest: "damaging",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Şafak vakti gökyüzü kırmızı ve turuncu tonlara bürünür .",
    front: "At dawn, the sky is painted in shades of red and orange .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "şafak",
    quest: "dawn",
  ),
  Words(
    back: "Yıkılan binanın molozları temizlendi .",
    front: "The debris from the collapsed building was cleared .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "moloz",
    quest: "debris",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Genç şarkıcının sahneye ilk çıkışı büyük ilgi çekti .",
    front: "The young singer's debut on stage attracted great attention .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sahneye ilk çıkış",
    quest: "debut",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Etkin karar verme becerileri önemlidir .",
    front: "Effective decision-making skills are important .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "karar verme",
    quest: "decision-making",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Kararlı bir liderdi .",
    front: "He was a decisive leader .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kararlı",
    quest: "decisive",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bağımsızlık beyannamesi imzalandı .",
    front: "The declaration of independence was signed .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "beyanname",
    quest: "declaration",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Hayatını bilime adayan bir bilim insanıydı .",
    front: "He was a scientist dedicated to science .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "özel",
    quest: "dedicated",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Kitabı en yakın arkadaşına ithaf etti .",
    front: "He dedicated the book to his closest friend .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ithaf",
    quest: "dedication",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Evin tapusu babamın üzerine .",
    front: "The deed to the house is in my father's name .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tapu",
    quest: "deed",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Onu aptal olarak değerlendirmek doğru değil .",
    front: "It is not right to deem him a fool .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tutmak",
    quest: "deem",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Borcunu ödememesi bir temerrüdtür .",
    front: "His failure to pay the debt is a default .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yükümlülüğünü yerine getirmemek",
    quest: "default",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Yeni aldığım telefonun bir arızası var .",
    front: "There is a defect in the new phone I bought .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "arıza",
    quest: "defect",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Kendini savunan bir tavırla konuştu .",
    front: "He spoke in a defensive manner .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "savunan",
    quest: "defensive",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Vücuttaki vitamin eksikliği sağlığı olumsuz etkiler .",
    front: "Vitamin deficiencies in the body negatively affect health .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "eksiklik",
    quest: "deficiency",
  ),
  Words(
    back: "Şirket bu yıl büyük bir açık verdi .",
    front: "The company had a big deficit this year .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "açık(hesaplarda)",
    quest: "deficit",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Tehditlerine boyun eğmedik ve onu göstere göstere defies ettik .",
    front: "We did not give in to his threats and defied him openly .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "küçümsemek",
    quest: "defy",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Sendika toplantısına bir temsilci gönderdi .",
    front: "The union sent a delegate to the meeting .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "temsilci",
    quest: "delegate",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Yetkilendirme belgesini imzaladı .",
    front: "He signed the delegation document .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yetkilendirme",
    quest: "delegation",
  ),

  Words(
    back:
        "Narin bir vazoydu ve dikkatli bir şekilde ele alınması gerekiyordu .",
    front: "It was a delicate situation and needed to be handled carefully .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "narin",
    quest: "delicate",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Şeytan, kötülüğü temsil eder .",
    front: "The demon represents evil .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "şeytan",
    quest: "demon",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Suçlamaları reddetti .",
    front: "He denied the accusations .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "reddetme",
    quest: "denial",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Hükümeti insan hakları ihlalleri nedeniyle ihbar etti .",
    front: "He denounced the government for human rights violations .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ihbar etmek",
    quest: "denounce",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Orman, yoğun ağaçlarla kaplıydı .",
    front: "The forest was dense with trees .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yoğun",
    quest: "dense",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Nüfus yoğunluğu kırsal kesimlere göre daha yüksektir .",
    front: "The population density is higher compared to rural areas .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yoğunluk",
    quest: "density",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Başarısı babasına olan bağımlılığını azalttı .",
    front: "His success reduced his dependence on his father .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bağlılık",
    quest: "dependence",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Resim, savaşın dehşetini canlı bir şekilde anlatıyordu .",
    front: "The painting depicted the horrors of war vividly .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "anlatmak",
    quest: "depict",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Askerleri savaşa konuşlandırdılar .",
    front: "They deployed the soldiers for the war .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "açmak",
    quest: "deploy",
  ),
  Words(
    back: "Ordunun konuşlanması savaşı bitirmeyi amaçlıyordu .",
    front: "The deployment of the army aimed to end the war .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "konuşlanma",
    quest: "deployment",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bankaya para yatırdı .",
    front: "He deposited money at the bank .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "emanet",
    quest: "deposit",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Yoksulluk, çocukları eğitim imkanlarından mahrum bırakıyor .",
    front: "Poverty deprives children of educational opportunities .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "mahrum etmek",
    quest: "deprive",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Milletvekili parlamentoda halkın temsilcisidir .",
    front: "A deputy is a representative of the people in parliament .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "milletvekili",
    quest: "deputy",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Kuş yavaş yavaş aşağıya indi .",
    front: "The bird slowly descended .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "inmek",
    quest: "descend",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Uçak kazası nedeniyle ani bir düşüş yaşandı .",
    front: "There was a sudden descent due to the plane crash .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "düşme",
    quest: "descent",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Yeni CEO olarak onu atadılar .",
    front: "They designated him as the new CEO .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "atamak",
    quest: "designate",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Barış, herkes için arzu edilen bir durumdur .",
    front: "Peace is a desirable situation for everyone .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "arzu edilen",
    quest: "desirable",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Bilgisayarının masaüstünde bir sürü dosya vardı .",
    front: "There were a lot of files on his computer's desktop .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "masaüstü",
    quest: "desktop",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Yıkıcı bir fırtınaydı .",
    front: "It was a destructive storm .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yıkıcı",
    quest: "destructive",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Polis onu sorguya çekmek için alıkoydu .",
    front: "The police detained him for questioning .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "alıkoymak",
    quest: "detain",
  ),

  Words(
    back:
        "Hırsızın suçu, güvenlik kamerası görüntüleri sayesinde tespit edildi .",
    front: "The thief's crime was detected thanks to security camera footage .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "buluş",
    quest: "detection",
  ),

  Words(
    back: "Suçlu zanlısı şu anda gözaltında ve ifadesi bekleniyor .",
    front: "The suspect is currently in detention and awaiting interrogation .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "engellenme",
    quest: "detention",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The health of the patient is deteriorating .",
    back: "Hastanın sağlık durumu kötüleşiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "fenalaşmak",
    quest: "deteriorate",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The natural disaster devastated the city .",
    back: "Doğal afet şehri harap etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "harap etmek",
    quest: "devastate",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The devil represents evil .",
    back: "Şeytan, kötülüğü temsil eder .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "şeytan",
    quest: "devil",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He invented a new method to solve the complex problem .",
    back: "Karmaşık sorunu çözmek için yeni bir yöntem icat etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "icat etmek",
    quest: "devise",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The doctor diagnosed his illness .",
    back: "Doktor hastalığını teşhis etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "teşhis etmek",
    quest: "diagnose",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Fashion trends dictate our tastes .",
    back: "Moda trendleri zevklerimizi etkiler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "etkilemek",
    quest: "dictate",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The people rebelled against the oppressive dictator .",
    back: "Ülke diktatör tarafından yönetiliyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "diktatör",
    quest: "dictator",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "It is important to differentiate between fact and opinion .",
    back: "İki kavram arasındaki farkı açıkladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "farklılaştırmak",
    quest: "differentiate",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "She treated everyone with respect and dignity .",
    back: "Onurunu korudu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "itibar",
    quest: "dignity",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "She was caught in a dilemma between her loyalty and her morals .",
    back: "Zor bir karar vermek zorundaydı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "açmaz",
    quest: "dilemma",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "Scientists are theorizing about the existence of higher dimensions .",
    back: "Heykelin üç boyutu vardır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "boyut",
    quest: "dimension",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He hoped that his symptoms would diminish with medication .",
    back: "Işığın şiddeti uzaklaştıkça azaldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "azalmak",
    quest: "diminish",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The stock market took a sudden dip .",
    back: "Ekonomi ani bir düşüş yaşadı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "batma",
    quest: "dip",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "You can find phone numbers in the phone directory .",
    back: "Telefon numaralarını rehberden bulabilirsin .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "rehber",
    quest: "directory",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The earthquake caused a disastrous tsunami .",
    back: "Doğal afet felaket oldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "talihsiz",
    quest: "disastrous",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "It's time to discard the old and broken toys .",
    back: "Eski ve bozuk oyuncakları atmanın zamanı geldi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ayırmak",
    quest: "discard",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The doctor discharged the patient from the hospital .",
    back: "Doktor hastayı taburcu etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "taburcu etmek",
    quest: "discharge",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The whistleblower disclosed the company's illegal activities .",
    back: "İfşa eden kişi, şirketin yasadışı faaliyetlerini açığa vurdu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "açığa vurmak",
    quest: "disclose",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The meeting was a productive discourse on the current situation .",
    back: "Toplantı, güncel durum hakkında verimli bir söylemdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "söylem",
    quest: "discourse",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Use discretion when sharing personal information online .",
    back: "Kişisel bilgilerinizi çevrimiçi paylaşırken incelik gösterin .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "incelik",
    quest: "discretion",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "All employees deserve to be treated with respect, without discrimination .",
    back:
        "Tüm çalışanlar ayrım yapılmadan saygı ile muamele edilmeyi hak eder .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ayrım",
    quest: "discrimination",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He received a dismissal notice from his job .",
    back: "İşinden kovma bildirimi aldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kovma",
    quest: "dismissal",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The earthquake displaced thousands of people from their homes .",
    back: "Deprem binlerce insanı yerinden etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yerinden çıkarmak",
    quest: "displace",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "There are proper procedures for the disposal of hazardous waste .",
    back: "Tehlikeli atıkların imhası için uygun prosedürler vardır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "imha etme",
    quest: "disposal",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Can you dispose of this empty garbage bag?",
    back: "Bu boş çöp poşetini atabilir misin?",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "atmak",
    quest: "dispose",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "They had a dispute over who would pay the bill .",
    back: "Hesabı kimin ödeyeceği konusunda çekiştiler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "çekişmek",
    quest: "dispute",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The construction project disrupted traffic flow in the city .",
    back: "İnşaat projesi şehirdeki trafik akışını aksattı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "aksatmak",
    quest: "disrupt",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The power outage caused widespread disruption .",
    back: "Elektrik kesintisi yaygın bir parçalanmaya neden oldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "parçalanma",
    quest: "disruption",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Sugar dissolves easily in water .",
    back: "Şeker, suda kolayca erir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "eritmek",
    quest: "dissolve",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "It's important to make a distinction between fact and opinion .",
    back: "Gerçek ve fikir arasında ayrım yapmak önemlidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ayırım",
    quest: "distinction",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "She has a very distinctive laugh .",
    back: "Kendine özgü bir kahkahası var .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kendine özgü",
    quest: "distinctive",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The propaganda distorted the truth about the conflict .",
    back: "Propaganda, çatışma hakkındaki gerçeği saptırdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "saptırmak",
    quest: "distort",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The financial situation caused them distress .",
    back: "Mali durum onları üzdü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "üzmek",
    quest: "distress",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "I found the movie disturbing and violent .",
    back: "Filmi rahatsız edici ve şiddetli buldum .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "rahatsız etme",
    quest: "disturbing",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "We need to divert resources to the most critical areas .",
    back: "Dikkatleri en kritik alanlara çevirmek gerekiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "başka yöne çevirmek",
    quest: "divert",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Many religions believe in a divine power .",
    back: "Pek çok din kutsal bir güce inanır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kutsal",
    quest: "divine",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The religious doctrine outlines the core beliefs of the faith .",
    back: "Dini ilke, dinin temel inançlarını ana hatlarıyla belirtir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ilke",
    quest: "doctrine",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Please provide proper documentation for your travel expenses .",
    back: "Lütfen seyahat masraflarınız için gerekli belgelemeyi sağlayın .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "belgeleme",
    quest: "documentation",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "They are experts in the field of artificial intelligence .",
    back: "Yapay zeka alanında uzmanlar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bilgi alanı",
    quest: "domain",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The lion is the dominant predator in the savanna .",
    back: "Aslan, savanda baskın avcıdır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hakimiyet",
    quest: "dominance",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The hospital relies on the generosity of blood donors .",
    back: "Hastane, kan bağışçılarının cömertliğine güveniyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bağışçı",
    quest: "donor",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The doctor prescribed a high dose of medication .",
    back: "Doktor yüksek dozda ilaç reçete etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "doz",
    quest: "dose",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "We need to drain the pool before winter .",
    back: "Havuzun suyunu boşaltmamız gerekiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tahliye etmek",
    quest: "drain",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Her thoughts drifted away as she gazed at the ocean .",
    back: "Okyanusa bakarken düşünceleri uzaklaştı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "şaşırmak",
    quest: "drift",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "She enjoyed the thrill of driving a fast car .",
    back: "Hızlı araba kullanmanın heyecanını yaşadı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sürme",
    quest: "driving",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The tragic accident left him to drown in despair .",
    back: "Trajik kaza onu umutsuzluk içinde boğdu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "suda boğulmak",
    quest: "drown",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "There is a dual nature to human personality .",
    back: "İnsan kişiliğinin ikili bir yapısı vardır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ikili",
    quest: "dual",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Let me try to dub the movie into Turkish .",
    back: "Filmi Türkçe dublajlamaya çalışayım .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "düzeltmek",
    quest: "dub",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He lifted the heavy dumbbells with ease .",
    back: "Ağır halterleri kolaylıkla kaldırdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "halter",
    quest: "dumb",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "They are a strong duo that can overcome any challenge .",
    back:
        "Herhangi bir zorluğun üstesinden gelebilecek güçlü bir ikilidirler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "eş",
    quest: "duo",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The company is known for its dynamic and innovative work environment .",
    back: "Şirket, dinamik ve yenilikçi çalışma ortamı ile tanınır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hareketli",
    quest: "dynamic",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She was eager to learn and improve her skills .",
    back: "Öğrenmeye ve yeteneklerini geliştirmeye istekliydi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "istekli",
    quest: "eager",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "His monthly earnings were not enough to cover his expenses .",
    back: "Aylık kazancı masraflarını karşılamaya yetmiyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kazanç",
    quest: "earnings",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Taking a deep breath helped to ease her anxiety .",
    back: "Derin bir nefes almak endişesini rahatlatmaya yardımcı oldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "rahatlatmak",
    quest: "ease",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Her shout echoed through the empty hallway .",
    back: "Çığlığı boş koridorda yankılandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yankı",
    quest: "echo",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "We need to find ecological solutions to environmental problems .",
    back: "Çevresel sorunlara ekolojik çözümler bulmamız gerekiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "çevre",
    quest: "ecological",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The experienced educator inspired his students to pursue their dreams .",
    back:
        "Tecrübeli eğitimci öğrencilerini hayallerinin peşinden gitmeye teşvik etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "eğitimci",
    quest: "educator",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The new policy will improve the effectiveness of waste management .",
    back: "Yeni politika, atık yönetiminin etkinliğini artıracaktır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "etkililik",
    quest: "effectiveness",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He completed the task with efficiency and minimal effort .",
    back: "Görevi verimli bir şekilde ve minimum çabayla tamamladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "liyakat",
    quest: "efficiency",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The teacher asked her students to elaborate on their answers .",
    back: "Öğretmen öğrencilerinden cevaplarını detaylandırmayı istedi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "detaylandırmak",
    quest: "elaborate",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The upcoming elections will be a crucial moment in the country's electoral process .",
    back:
        " yaklaşan seçimler, ülkenin seçim süreci için önemli bir an olacak .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "seçimle ilgili",
    quest: "electoral",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Education can elevate a person's social status .",
    back: "Eğitim, bir kişinin sosyal statüsünü yükseltebilir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yükseltmek",
    quest: "elevate",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Only citizens who meet the age requirement are eligible to vote .",
    back:
        "Sadece yaş şartını yerine getiren vatandaşlar oy kullanmaya hak sahibiです .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hak sahibi",
    quest: "eligible",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "They belong to an elite group of athletes who compete at the highest level .",
    back: "En üst düzeyde yarışan elit bir sporcu grubuna aitler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "elit",
    quest: "elite",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The passengers boarded the ship for their journey .",
    back: "Yolcular yolculukları için gemiye bindiler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "gemiye bindirmek",
    quest: "embark",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He felt a wave of embarrassment after tripping in public .",
    back: "Toplum içinde tökezledikten sonra bir utanç dalgası hissetti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "mahcubiyet",
    quest: "embarrassment",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The US embassy in Ankara is located in Çankaya .",
    back: "ABD'nin Ankara Büyükelçiliği Çankaya'da bulunmaktadır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "elçilik",
    quest: "embassy",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The message was embedded in the code for only authorized users to see .",
    back:
        "Mesaj, yalnızca yetkili kullanıcıların görebileceği şekilde koda gömülüydü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "gömmek",
    quest: "embed",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The spirit of freedom is embodied in the national anthem .",
    back: "Özgürlük ruhu milli marşta somutlaştırılıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "somutlaştırmak",
    quest: "embody",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The emergence of new technologies is changing the world .",
    back: "Yeni teknolojilerin ortaya çıkışı dünyayı değiştiriyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "belirme",
    quest: "emergence",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Scientific research is based on empirical evidence .",
    back: "Bilimsel araştırma, deneysel kanıtlara dayanır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "deneysel",
    quest: "empirical",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Education empowers individuals to reach their full potential .",
    back:
        "Eğitim, bireyleri tam potansiyellerine ulaşmaları için güçlendirir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "izin vermek",
    quest: "empower",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The government enacted a new law to protect the environment .",
    back: "Hükümet, çevreyi korumak için yeni bir yasa çıkardı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sahnelemek",
    quest: "enact",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The concept of human rights encompasses a wide range of freedoms .",
    back: "İnsan hakları kavramı, geniş bir özgürlük yelpazesini kapsar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kuşatmak",
    quest: "encompass",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Her positive words were a great encouragement for him .",
    back: "Onun olumlu sözleri onun için büyük bir teşvikti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "teşvik",
    quest: "encouragement",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The teacher's encouraging words helped the students overcome their shyness .",
    back:
        "Öğretmenin cesaretlendirici sözleri öğrencilerin çekingenliklerini yenmelerine yardımcı oldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "cesaretlendirici",
    quest: "encouraging",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "They are determined to succeed in their endeavours .",
    back: "Çabalarında başarılı olmaya kararlılar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "çabalamak",
    quest: "endeavour",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The universe seems endless in its vastness .",
    back: "Evren enginliğiyle sonsuz görünüyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sonsuz",
    quest: "endless",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The celebrity publicly endorsed the new brand of clothing .",
    back: "Ünlü, yeni giyim markasını alenen destekledi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "arkasına yazmak",
    quest: "endorse",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "You need to sign the back of the check for it to be cashed .",
    back: "Çeki bozdurmak için arkasını imzalamanız gerekiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ciro",
    quest: "endorsement",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The soldiers had to endure harsh weather conditions during the war .",
    back:
        "Askerler savaş sırasında zorlu hava koşullarına dayanmak zorunda kaldılar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dayanmak",
    quest: "endure",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The police will enforce the law to maintain public order .",
    back: "Polis, kamu düzenini sağlamak için yasayı uygulayacaktır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "zorla yaptırmak",
    quest: "enforce",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "Strict enforcement of traffic laws is necessary to reduce accidents .",
    back:
        "Kazaları azaltmak için trafik yasalarının sıkı bir şekilde uygulanması gerekiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "uygulama",
    quest: "enforcement",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The couple's engagement was announced in the newspaper .",
    back: "Çiftin nişanı gazetede duyuruldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "nişan",
    quest: "engagement",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The teacher's engaging presentation kept the students' attention .",
    back: "Öğretmenin ilgi çekici sunumu öğrencilerin dikkatini çekti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "meşgul etme",
    quest: "engaging",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He politely enquired about her well-being .",
    back: "Nezaketle onun iyiliğini sordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "soru sormak",
    quest: "enquire",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "Traveling to different countries enriches one's cultural experience .",
    back:
        "Farklı ülkelere seyahat etmek kişinin kültürel deneyimini zenginleştirir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "zenginleştirmek",
    quest: "enrich",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "You can enrol in the online course at any time .",
    back: "Online kursa herhangi bir zamanda kaydolabilirsiniz .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kaydolmak",
    quest: "enrol",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "A heated debate ensued after the speaker's controversial remarks .",
    back:
        "Konuşmacının tartışmalı sözlerinden sonra hararetli bir tartışma başladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "meydana gelmek",
    quest: "ensue",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He started his own enterprise after leaving his corporate job .",
    back: "Kurumsal işinden ayrıldıktan sonra kendi girişimini başlattı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "girişim",
    quest: "enterprise",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She is a music enthusiast who can name every song on the album .",
    back: "Albümdeki her şarkıyı sayabilen bir müzik tutkunu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "istekli kimse",
    quest: "enthusiast",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The new law is entitled 'The Protection of Wildlife Act' .",
    back: "Yeni yasa 'Yaban Hayatı Koruma Kanunu' başlığını taşıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "isimlendirmek",
    quest: "entitle",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The company is a legal entity with its own tax identification number .",
    back: "Şirket, kendi vergi kimlik numarası olan tüzel bir kişiliktir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "mevcudiyet",
    quest: "entity",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The spread of the coronavirus has become a global epidemic .",
    back: "Koronavirüsün yayılması küresel bir salgın haline geldi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "salgın",
    quest: "epidemic",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "We strive for equality and justice for all .",
    back: "Herkes için eşitlik ve adalet için çabalıyoruz .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "eşitlik",
    quest: "equality",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Can you solve this mathematical equation for x?",
    back: "Bu matematiksel denklemi x için çözebilir misin?",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "denge",
    quest: "equation",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The workers erected a statue in honor of the war hero .",
    back: "İşçiler savaş kahramanının onuruna bir heykel diktiler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dikmek",
    quest: "erect",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The situation escalated quickly into a violent conflict .",
    back: "Durum hızla şiddetli bir çatışmaya dönüştü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kızışmak",
    quest: "escalate",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Love is the essence of humanity .",
    back: "Sevgi, insanlığın özüdür .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "öz",
    quest: "essence",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The university was established in 1863 .",
    back: "Üniversite 1863 yılında kuruldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kuruluş",
    quest: "establishment",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "They believe in eternal life after death .",
    back: "Ölümdən sonra sonsuz hayata inaniyorlar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sonsuz",
    quest: "eternal",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The city was evacuated due to the approaching hurricane .",
    back: " yaklaşan kasırga nedeniyle şehir boşaltıldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "götürmek",
    quest: "evacuate",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The music evoked memories of his childhood .",
    back: "Müzik, çocukluğuna dair anıları uyandırdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "anımsatmak",
    quest: "evoke",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The theory of evolution explains how species change over time .",
    back: "Evrim teorisi, türlerin zamanla nasıl değiştiğini açıklar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "evrimsel",
    quest: "evolutionary",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Don't exaggerate the problem; it's not as bad as you think .",
    back: "Problemi abartmayın; düşündüğünüz kadar kötü değil .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "abartmak",
    quest: "exaggerate",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "She strives for excellence in everything she does .",
    back: "Yaptığı her şeyde mükemmellik için çabalar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "mükemmellik",
    quest: "excellence",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He received an exceptional grade on his history exam .",
    back: "Tarih sınavında fevkalade bir not aldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "fevkalade",
    quest: "exceptional",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Eating in moderation is important to avoid excess calories .",
    back: "Aşırı kalori alımından kaçınmak için ölçülü yemek önemlidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "aşırılık",
    quest: "excess",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He was excluded from the team because of his poor sportsmanship .",
    back: "Düşük sporcu ahlakı nedeniyle takımdan çıkarıldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ret",
    quest: "exclusion",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "This club is exclusive and only accepts members by invitation .",
    back: "Bu kulüp özeldir ve sadece davetiye ile üye kabul eder .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "özel",
    quest: "exclusive",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The new product is designed exclusively for gamers .",
    back: "Yeni ürün, özellikle oyuncular için tasarlanmıştır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "özellikle",
    quest: "exclusively",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The judge ordered the execution of the criminal .",
    back: "Yargıç suçlunun infazını emretti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "infaz etmek",
    quest: "execute",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The execution of the plan was flawless .",
    back: "Planın icrası kusursuzdu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "icra,idam",
    quest: "execution",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The leader exerted all his power to overcome the challenge .",
    back: "Lider, zorluğun üstesinden gelmek için tüm gücünü harcadı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "güç sarfetmek",
    quest: "exert",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Napoleon was exiled to the island of Elba after his defeat .",
    back: "Napolyon yenilgisinden sonra Elba adasına sürüldü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sürgün",
    quest: "exile",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The company's high expenditure on advertising resulted in financial difficulties .",
    back:
        "Şirketin reklam için yaptığı yüksek masraflar mali sıkıntıya neden oldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "masraf",
    quest: "expenditure",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The scientists conducted an experimental study to test the new drug .",
    back:
        "Bilim adamları, yeni ilacı test etmek için deneysel bir çalışma yürüttüler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "deneysel",
    quest: "experimental",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "Your credit card will expire next month . Don't forget to renew it .",
    back: "Kredi kartınız önümüzdeki ay sona erecek . Yenilemeyi unutmayın .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "süresi dolmak",
    quest: "expire",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The instructions were explicit and easy to follow .",
    back: "Talimatlar açıktı ve takip edilmesi kolaydı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "aşikar",
    quest: "explicit",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He explicitly stated his disagreement with the proposal .",
    back: "Öneriye açıkça karşı çıktığını ifade etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "açıkça",
    quest: "explicitly",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "Child labor is a form of exploitation that is illegal in most countries .",
    back: "Çocuk işçilik, çoğu ülkede yasadışı olan bir sömürü biçimidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kötüye kullanma",
    quest: "exploitation",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The news report contained explosive allegations of corruption .",
    back: "Haber raporunda patlayıcı yolsuzluk iddiaları yer alıyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "patlayıcı",
    quest: "explosive",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "Scientists were able to extract valuable DNA from the dinosaur fossil .",
    back: "Bilim adamları, dinozor fosilinden değerli DNA çıkarabildiler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "özünü çıkarmak",
    quest: "extract",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Extremist groups often resort to violence to achieve their goals .",
    back:
        "Aşırılıkçı gruplar, hedeflerine ulaşmak için çoğu zaman şiddete başvururlar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "aşırılık yapmak",
    quest: "extremist",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The new policy will facilitate the process of applying for a visa .",
    back: "Yeni politika, vize başvuru sürecini kolaylaştıracaktır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "rahatlatmak",
    quest: "facilitate",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The country is divided into various political factions .",
    back: "Ülke çeşitli siyasi hiziplere ayrılmıştır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hizip",
    quest: "faction",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "She is a member of the English faculty at the university .",
    back: "Üniversitede İngiliz Dili ve Edebiyatı fakültesi üyesidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "fakülte",
    quest: "faculty",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The old photograph had faded over time .",
    back: "Eski fotoğraf zamanla solmuştu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "karartmak",
    quest: "fade",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Justice demands fairness for all .",
    back: "Adalet, herkes için insaf gerektirir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "insaf",
    quest: "fairness",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The accident resulted in a fatal injury .",
    back: "Kaza ölümcül bir yaralanmayla sonuçlandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ölümcül",
    quest: "fatal",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He believes that everything happens according to fate .",
    back: "Her şeyin kadere göre gerçekleştiğine inanıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kader",
    quest: "fate",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The weather forecast is favourable for a picnic tomorrow .",
    back: "Yarın piknik için hava durumu olumlu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "olumlu",
    quest: "favourable",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Climbing Mount Everest is a remarkable feat of human endurance .",
    back:
        "Everest Dağı'na tırmanmak, insan dayanıklılığının olağanüstü bir başarısıdır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "beceriklilik",
    quest: "feat",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "A diet rich in fibre can help with digestion .",
    back: "Lif açısından zengin bir diyet sindirime yardımcı olabilir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "lif",
    quest: "fibre",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The lion is a fierce predator known for its hunting skills .",
    back: "Aslan, avlanma yetenekleriyle tanınan vahşi bir avcıdır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "vahşet",
    quest: "fierce",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The award-winning film-maker is known for her thought-provoking documentaries .",
    back: "Ödüllü filmci, düşündürücü belgeselleriyle tanınır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "filmci",
    quest: "film-maker",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "Coffee filters help remove unwanted particles from the brewed coffee .",
    back:
        "Kahve filtreleri, demlenmiş kahveden istenmeyen partiküllerin temizlenmesine yardımcı olur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "süzmek",
    quest: "filter",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He was fined for speeding by the traffic police .",
    back: "Trafik polisi tarafından aşırı hız yaptığı için ceza kesildi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ceza kesmek",
    quest: "fine",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The suspect was arrested for possession of a firearm .",
    back: "Şüpheli, ateşli silah bulundurma suçundan tutuklandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ateşli silah",
    quest: "firearm",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Make sure you wear clothes that fit you well .",
    back: "Size tam oturan giysiler giydiğinizden emin olun .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "uymak",
    quest: "fit",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The football match is a weekly fixture that brings the community together .",
    back: "Futbol maçı, topluluğu bir araya getiren haftalık bir fikstürdür .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sabit eşya",
    quest: "fixture",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The new design had a few minor flaws, but overall it was successful .",
    back:
        "Yeni tasarımın birkaç küçük kusuru vardı, ancak genel olarak başarılıydı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kusur",
    quest: "flaw",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The cracked vase was beyond repair .",
    back: "Çatlamış vazo tamir edilemeyecek durumdaydı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "çatlak",
    quest: "flawed",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The frightened animals fled into the forest .",
    back: "Korkmuş hayvanlar kaçarak ormana sığındılar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kaçmak",
    quest: "flee",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The naval fleet patrolled the coast to protect the country's borders .",
    back: "Donanma, ülkenin sınırlarını korumak için sahili devriye etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "donanma",
    quest: "fleet",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Scars are formed from the healing of damaged flesh .",
    back: "Yara izleri, hasarlı etin iyileşmesinden oluşur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "et",
    quest: "flesh",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Yoga improves flexibility and balance .",
    back: "Yoga, esneklik ve dengeyi geliştirir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "esneklik",
    quest: "flexibility",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The politician gave a flourishing speech filled with empty promises .",
    back: "Politikacı, boş vaatlerle dolu süslü bir konuşma yaptı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "süslü konuşmak",
    quest: "flourish",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Water is a vital fluid for all living organisms .",
    back: "Su, tüm canlı organizmalar için hayati bir sıvıdır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sıvı",
    quest: "fluid",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He felt like a foreigner in his own country .",
    back: "Kendi ülkesinde kendini bir yabancı gibi hissetti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yabancı",
    quest: "foreigner",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "Blacksmiths use fire and hammers to forge metal into different shapes .",
    back:
        "Demirciler, metali farklı şekillere dövmek için ateş ve çekiç kullanırlar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "demir dövmek",
    quest: "forge",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The new baby formula is enriched with essential vitamins and minerals .",
    back:
        "Yeni mama, gerekli vitaminler ve minerallerle zenginleştirilmiştir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "mama",
    quest: "formula",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Scientists are trying to formulate a cure for the disease .",
    back:
        "Bilim adamları, hastalık için bir tedavi formülü oluşturmaya çalışıyorlar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "formülleştirmek",
    quest: "formulate",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The charity fosters hope and opportunity for underprivileged children .",
    back: "Hayır kurumu, dezavantajlı çocuklar için umut ve fırsat yaratır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bakmak",
    quest: "foster",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The fragile butterfly wings were easily damaged .",
    back: "Narin kelebek kanatları kolayca zarar gördü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "narin",
    quest: "fragile",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Frankly, I don't think that plan is going to work .",
    back: "Açıkçası, bu planın işe yarayacağını sanmıyorum .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "açıkça",
    quest: "frankly",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He felt frustrated after his repeated failures .",
    back:
        "Tekrarlayan başarısızlıklardan sonra kendini haksızlığa uğramış hissetti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hakkı yenmiş",
    quest: 'frustrated',
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Trying to explain things to him is so frustrating!",
    back: "Ona bir şeyler anlatmaya çalışmak çok moral bozucu!",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "moral bozucu",
    quest: "frustrating",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The constant traffic jams were a major source of frustration for the commuters .",
    back:
        "Sürekli trafik sıkışıklığı, yolcular için büyük bir hüsran kaynağıydı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hüsran",
    quest: "frustration",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The new furniture is both stylish and functional .",
    back: "Yeni mobilyalar hem şık hem de işlevsel .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "pratik",
    quest: "functional",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The school is organizing a fundraising event to raise money for new sports equipment .",
    back:
        "Okul, yeni spor malzemeleri için para toplama etkinliği düzenliyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "para toplama",
    quest: "fundraising",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Hundreds of mourners attended the funeral to pay their respects .",
    back: "Yüzlerce yas tutan, cenazeye saygılarını sunmak için katıldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "cenaze",
    quest: "funeral",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He has a gambling problem and has lost a lot of money .",
    back: "Kumar sorunu var ve çok para kaybetti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kumar",
    quest: "gambling",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "There will be a gathering of friends and family this weekend .",
    back: "Bu hafta sonu bir arkadaş ve aile toplanma olacak .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "toplanma",
    quest: "gathering",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "She caught him gazing out the window, lost in thought .",
    back: "Onu dalgın dalgın pencereden dışarı bakarken gözüne takıldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "gözünü dikmek",
    quest: "gaze",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Shift into a higher gear to accelerate .",
    back: "Hızlanmak için daha yüksek bir vitese takın .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dişli",
    quest: "gear",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "This medication is a generic version of a brand-name drug .",
    back: "Bu ilaç, markalı bir ilacın jenerik versiyonudur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "jenerik",
    quest: "generic",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The war crimes committed against the minority group were considered genocide .",
    back:
        "Azınlık grubuna karşı işlenen savaş suçları soykırım olarak değerlendirildi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "soykırım",
    quest: "genocide",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He glanced at his watch to see what time it was .",
    back: "Saatin kaç olduğunu görmek için saatine şöyle bir göz attı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "göz atmak",
    quest: "glance",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "She caught a glimpse of the thief running down the street .",
    back: "Hırsızın sokakta koşarken anlık bir bakışını yakaladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "anlık bakış",
    quest: "glimpse",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The victory was a glorious moment in the country's history .",
    back: "Zafer, ülkenin tarihinde şanlı bir andı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "şanlı",
    quest: "glorious",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The athlete achieved glory by winning the gold medal .",
    back: "Atlet, altın madalya kazanarak görkeme ulaştı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "görkem",
    quest: "glory",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Good governance is essential for a stable and prosperous society .",
    back: "İyi yönetişim, istikrarlı ve müreffeh bir toplum için gereklidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kontrol",
    quest: "governance",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "She moved with grace and elegance .",
    back: "Zarafet ve incelikle hareket etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "zarafet",
    quest: "grace",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He struggled to grasp the complex concept .",
    back: "Karmaşık kavramı kavramakta zorlandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kavramak",
    quest: "grasp",
  ),

  Words(
    front:
        "The soldier's body was buried in a grave with full military honors .",
    back: "Askerin naaşı, tüm askeri törenlerle bir mezara gömüldü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "mezar",
    quest: "grave",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Gravity is the force that keeps us grounded .",
    back: "Yerçekimi, bizi yerde tutan kuvvettir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yerçekimi",
    quest: "gravity",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The city's power grid was damaged by the storm .",
    back: "Fırtına nedeniyle şehrin elektrik şebekesi zarar gördü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "örgü",
    quest: "grid",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "He was overcome with grief after the death of his wife .",
    back: "Karısının ölümünden sonra kederden yıkıldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "keder",
    quest: "grief",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He grinned mischievously at his friend .",
    back: "Arkadaşına yaramazca sırıttı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sırıtmak",
    quest: "grin",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The coffee beans need to be grinded before brewing .",
    back: "Kahve çekirdekleri demlenmeden önce öğütülmelidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "öğütmek",
    quest: "grind",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He struggled to grip the wet doorknob .",
    back: "Islak kapı tokmağını kavramakta zorlandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "kavramak", // "Grip" in this context means to grasp tightly, which translates to "kavramak" in Turkish .
    quest: "grip",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The teacher offered guidance to the struggling student .",
    back: "Öğretmen, zorlanan öğrenciye yönlendirme sundu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yönlendirme",
    quest: "guidance",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He felt a pang of guilt for his actions .",
    back: "Yaptıklarından dolayı bir suçluluk duygusu hissetti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "suçluluk",
    quest: "guilt",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "There's no point trying to clean a gut instinct .", // "Gut" in this context doesn't have a direct translation . " sezgi" (intuition) might be a better fit depending on the intended meaning .
    back:
        "Sezgileri temizlemenin bir anlamı yok .", // Adjusted the translation based on the suggested meaning .
    list: "C1",
    answer: "temizlemek",
    quest: "gut",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The storm brought heavy hail, damaging cars and crops .",
    back: "Fırtına, arabalara ve ekinlere zarar veren dolu yağdırdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dolu yağmak",
    quest: "hail",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She was only halfway through the project when she quit .",
    back: "Projenin ancak yarısına gelmişti ki bıraktı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yarı yolda",
    quest: "halfway",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The car came to a halt at the red light .",
    back: "Araba kırmızı ışıkta durdu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "durmak",
    quest: "halt",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He grabbed a handful of nuts from the bowl .",
    back: "Kâseden bir avuç fındık aldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "avuç",
    quest: "handful",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He appreciated her skillful handling of the difficult situation .",
    back: "Zor durumun ustaca idaresini takdir etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "idare",
    quest: "handling",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The new stapler is a handy tool to have around the office .",
    back: "Yeni zımba, ofiste olması kullanışlı bir araç .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kullanışlı",
    quest: "handy",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He was constantly harassed by his coworkers .",
    back: "Mesai arkadaşları tarafından sürekli tacize uğradı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "taciz",
    quest: "harassment",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The computer consists of both software and hardware .",
    back: "Bilgisayar hem yazılımdan hem de donanımdan oluşur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "donanım",
    quest: "hardware",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "There is a sense of harmony between the music and the lyrics .",
    back: "Müzik ve sözler arasında bir ahenk var .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ahenk",
    quest: "harmony",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The sergeant's voice was harsh and unforgiving .",
    back: "Çavuşun sesi sert ve affetmezdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "haşin",
    quest: "harsh",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The farmers are preparing for the upcoming harvest .",
    back: "Çiftçiler yaklaşan hasat için hazırlanıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hasat",
    quest: "harvest",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He was filled with hatred for his enemies .",
    back: "Düşmanlarına karşı nefretle doluydu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "nefret",
    quest: "hatred",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The abandoned house is said to be haunted by ghosts .",
    back: "Terk edilmiş evin hayaletler tarafından perili olduğu söylenir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "perili", // "Sık sık uğramak" (frequently visit) doesn't capture the meaning of "haunt" in this context . "Perili" is a better fit .
    quest: "haunt",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Working in a factory can be a hazardous job .",
    back: "Fabrika işçiliği tehlikeli bir iş olabilir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "risk", // "Hazard" is more about the inherent danger, while "tehlike" can also mean active threat .
    quest: "hazard",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The speech heightened the tensions between the two countries .",
    back: "Konuşma, iki ülke arasındaki gerilimi yükseltti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "yükseltmek", // "Artan" (increasing) wouldn't capture the action of making something greater .
    quest: "heighten",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He is proud of his rich heritage and cultural background .",
    back: "Zengin mirası ve kültürel geçmişiyle gurur duyuyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "miras",
    quest: "heritage",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The high-profile trial was covered by news outlets worldwide .",
    back:
        "Yüksek profilli dava, dünya çapında haber kuruluşları tarafından takip edildi .",
    list: "C1",
    // "İyi tanınan" (well-known) doesn't quite capture the emphasis on public importance .
    answer: "yüksek profilli",
    quest: "high-profile",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She dropped a hint about her birthday present .",
    back: "Doğum günü hediyesi hakkında bir ipucu verdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ima etmek",
    quest: "hint",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He longed to return to his homeland after many years abroad .",
    back: "Yıllar sonra yurt dışından vatanına dönmeyi özlemle bekliyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "vatan",
    quest: "homeland",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He used a hook to pull the heavy box .",
    back: "Ağır kutuyu çekmek için bir kanca kullandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kanca",
    quest: "hook",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Despite the challenges, he remained hopeful about the future .",
    back: "Tüm zorluklara rağmen, gelecek hakkında umutlu kaldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "umutlu",
    quest: "hopeful",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The sun dipped below the horizon as night fell .",
    back: "Gece bastırırken güneş ufuk çizgisinin altına battı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ufuk",
    quest: "horizon",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The deer used its horns to defend itself from the predator .",
    back: "Geyik, yırtıcıdan kendini korumak için boynuzlarını kullandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "boynuz",
    quest: "horn",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The rebels took several hostages during the bank robbery .",
    back: "İsyancılar, banka soygunu sırasında birkaç kişiyi rehin aldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "rehin",
    quest: "hostage",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The two armies faced each other in a hostile environment .",
    back: "İki ordu birbirine düşmanca bir ortamda karşı karşıya geldi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "düşmanca",
    quest: "hostile",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "There was a sense of hostility between the two rival companies .",
    back: "İki rakip şirket arasında düşmanlık vardı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "düşmanlık",
    quest: "hostility",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The humanitarian organization provides aid to refugees around the world .",
    back: "Yardım kuruluşu, dünya çapındaki mültecilere yardım sağlıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yardımsever",
    quest: "humanitarian",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Despite their differences, they treated each other with humanity .",
    back: "Farklılıklarına rağmen birbirlerine insanlıkla davrandılar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "insaniyet",
    quest: "humanity",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He was a humble man despite his great achievements .",
    back: "Büyük başarılarına rağmen mütevazı bir adamdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "mütevazı",
    quest: "humble",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "You will need to show identification to enter the building .",
    back: "Binaya girmek için kimlik göstermeniz gerekecek .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kimlik saptama",
    quest: "identification",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "They argued over ideological differences .",
    back: "Fikri farklılıklar üzerine tartıştılar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "fikirsel",
    quest: "ideological",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He didn't know the answer because of his sheer idiocy .",
    back: "Saf salaklığı yüzünden cevabı bilmiyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "salak", // "Idiot" can also be translated as "aptal" depending on the context .
    quest: "idiot",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "His ignorance of the law led him into trouble .",
    back: "Hukuku bilgisizliği onu başını derde soktu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bilgisizlik",
    quest: "ignorance",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The poem's vivid imagery created a strong emotional response in the reader .",
    back: "Şiirin canlı imgeleri, okuyucuda güçlü bir duygusal tepki yarattı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "imgelem",
    quest: "imagery",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The castle is an immense structure with towering walls .",
    back: "Kale, yükselen duvarları olan devasa bir yapıdır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "muazzam", // "Immense" can also be translated as "devasa" depending on the context .
    quest: "immense",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "There is an imminent threat of war in the region .",
    back: "Bölgede savaş tehlikesi eli kulağındadır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "eli kulağında",
    quest: "imminent",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The successful implementation of the new policy led to positive results .",
    back:
        "Yeni politikanın başarılı bir şekilde uygulanması olumlu sonuçlara yol açtı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "uygulama",
    quest: "implementation",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The criminal was sentenced to ten years' imprisonment .",
    back: "Suçlu, on yıl hapis cezasına çarptırıldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hapse atmak",
    quest: "imprison",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He feared the harsh conditions of imprisonment .",
    back: "Hapis hayatının zorlu koşullarından korkuyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hapis",
    quest: "imprisonment",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Her inability to speak the language made communication difficult .",
    back: "Dili konuşamaması iletişimi zorlaştırıyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yetersizlik",
    quest: "inability",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The teacher found the student's explanation inadequate .",
    back: "Öğretmen, öğrencinin açıklamasını yetersiz buldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yetersiz",
    quest: "inadequate",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "It was inappropriate to tell that joke at the funeral .",
    back: "Cenazede o şakayı anlatmak uygunsuzdu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "uygunsuz",
    quest: "inappropriate",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The report documented a higher incidence of cancer in the area .",
    back: "Raporda, bölgede daha yüksek kanser vakası sayısı belgelendi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "rastlantı", // "Incidence" can also be translated as "vaka" depending on the context, but "rastlantı" captures the idea of occurrence .
    quest: "incidence",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He was not inclined to help them with their difficult task .",
    back: "Onlara zor görevlerinde yardım etmeye meyilli değildi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "meyilli",
    quest: "inclined",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The company incurred a heavy loss due to the fire .",
    back: "Şirket, yangın nedeniyle büyük bir zarar gördü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "uğramak",
    quest: "incur",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The economic indicators suggest a possible recession .",
    back: "Ekonomik göstergeler olası bir durgunluğa işaret ediyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "gösterge",
    quest: "indicator",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The grand jury issued an indictment against the suspect .",
    back: "Jüri heyeti şüpheli hakkında bir iddianame hazırladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "itham",
    quest: "indictment",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The tribe lived an indigenous way of life in the rainforest .",
    back: "Kabile, yağmur ormanlarında yerli bir yaşam tarzı sürdürdü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yerli",
    quest: "indigenous",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The teacher tried to induce her students to learn more about science .",
    back:
        "Öğretmen, öğrencilerini bilimle daha fazla ilgilenmeye ikna etmeye çalıştı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ikna etmek",
    quest: "induce",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She likes to indulge in chocolate cake from time to time .",
    back: "Zaman zaman çikolatalı pastaya kendini şımartmayı sever .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "şımartmak",
    quest: "indulge",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "There is a growing inequality in wealth distribution around the world .",
    back: "Dünya çapında servet dağılımında giderek artan bir eşitsizlik var .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "eşitsizlik",
    quest: "inequality",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "Jack the Ripper is an infamous serial killer from Victorian London .",
    back:
        "Jack the Ripper, Viktorya dönemi Londra'sından kötü şöhretli bir seri katildir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kötü şöhretli",
    quest: "infamous",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The baby cried incessantly throughout the night .",
    back: "Bebek gece boyunca durmadan ağladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bebek",
    quest: "infant",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The cold weather can easily infect you with a cold or the flu .",
    back:
        "Soğuk hava sizi kolayca soğuk algınlığına veya gribe bulaştırabilir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bulaştırmak",
    quest: "infect",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The criminal was charged with inflicting bodily harm on the victim .",
    back: "Suçlu, kurbana ağır yaralama suçlamasıyla suçlandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "çarptırmak", // "Inflict" can also be translated as "yapmak" (to do) depending on the context, but "çarptırmak" emphasizes the act of causing harm .
    quest: "inflict",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He is an influential figure in the world of business .",
    back: "İş dünyasında etkili bir figürdür .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "etkili",
    quest: "influential",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Honesty is an inherent quality that everyone should possess .",
    back:
        "Dürüstlük, herkesin sahip olması gereken özünde olan bir özelliktir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "özünde olan",
    quest: "inherent",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The new law will inhibit economic growth .",
    back: "Yeni yasa, ekonomik büyümeyi engelleyecektir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "engellemek",
    quest: "inhibit",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The company has initiated a new marketing campaign .",
    back: "Şirket, yeni bir pazarlama kampanyası başlattı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "başlatmak",
    quest: "initiate",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The doctor injected the medicine into the patient's arm .",
    back: "Doktor, hastaya ilacı kolundan enjekte etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "püskürtme", // "Injection" is more about the act of injecting, "püskürtme" emphasizes squirting or spraying . A better translation is "enjeksiyon" .
    quest: "injection",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The war caused a great deal of injustice and suffering .",
    back: "Savaş, büyük bir adaletsizlik ve ıstıraba neden oldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "adaletsizlik",
    quest: "injustice",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The editor made some minor insertions into the text .",
    back: "Editör, metne bazı küçük ilaveler yaptı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ilave",
    quest: "insertion",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The police suspect that there is an insider who is leaking information .",
    back: "Polis, bilgi sızdıran bir içeriden biri olduğundan şüpheleniyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "içeriden biri",
    quest: "insider",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The health inspector conducted a thorough inspection of the restaurant .",
    back: "Sağlık müfettişi, restoranda kapsamlı bir denetim gerçekleştirdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "denetlemek",
    quest: "inspect",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The restaurant received a positive rating after the inspection .",
    back: "Restoran, denetimden sonra olumlu bir değerlendirme aldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "denetleme",
    quest: "inspection",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He found inspiration for his painting in the beauty of nature .",
    back: "Resminin ilhamını doğanın güzelliğinden aldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ilham",
    quest: "inspiration",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Animals often rely on instinct for survival .",
    back: "Hayvanlar genellikle hayatta kalmak için içgüdülerine güvenir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "içgüdü",
    quest: "instinct",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He worked for a large institutional bank .",
    back: "Büyük bir kuruluşa ait bankada çalıştı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kuruluşa ait",
    quest: "institutional",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The teacher instructed the students to complete the exercise .",
    back: "Öğretmen, öğrencilere alıştırmayı tamamlamaları talimatını verdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "haber vermek", // "Instruct" can also be translated as "öğretmek" (to teach) depending on the context .
    quest: "instruct",
  ),
  // Keep the existing "yetersiz" for "insufficient"
  Words(
    front: "Her explanation was insufficient and did not answer the question .",
    back: "Açıklaması yetersizdi ve soruyu cevaplamıyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "hakaret etmek", // "Insult" means to deliberately say something rude or hurtful . A better translation is "hakaret" or "küfretmek" .
    quest: "insult",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The ancient artifact remained intact despite being buried for centuries .",
    back:
        "Eski eser, yüzyıllardır gömülü kalmasına rağmen dokunulmamış olarak kaldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dokunulmamış",
    quest: "intact",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The doctor monitored the patient's daily intake of medication .",
    back: "Doktor, hastanın günlük ilaç alım miktarını takip etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "alınan miktar",
    quest: "intake",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The new technology has been integrated into the existing system .",
    back: "Yeni teknoloji, mevcut sisteme entegre edildi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bütünleşmiş",
    quest: "integrated",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The successful integration of immigrants into society is a complex challenge .",
    back:
        "Göçmenlerin topluma başarılı bir şekilde entegrasyonu karmaşık bir sorundur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bütünleme",
    quest: "integration",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He is a man of integrity with strong moral principles .",
    back: "O, güçlü ahlaki değerlere sahip dürüst bir insandır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tamamlık",
    quest: "integrity",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The conflict intensified as both sides increased their military presence .",
    back: "Her iki taraf da askeri varlığını artırdıkça çatışma yoğunlaştı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yoğunlaştırmak",
    quest: "intensify",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The athlete trained with great intensity to prepare for the competition .",
    back: "Sporcu, yarışmaya hazırlanmak için büyük bir yoğunlukla çalıştı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yoğunluk",
    quest: "intensity",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He enrolled in an intensive language course to improve his English quickly .",
    back:
        "İngilizcesini hızlı bir şekilde geliştirmek için yoğun bir dil kursuna kaydoldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yoğun",
    quest: "intensive",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "What is your intent in asking me this question?",
    back: "Bana bu soruyu sorma niyetin nedir?",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "niyet",
    quest: "intent",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The children enjoyed playing with the interactive whiteboard in class .",
    back: "Çocuklar, sınıftaki etkileşimli tahta ile oynamaktan zevk aldılar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "etkileşimli",
    quest: "interactive",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The user interface of the new software is very user-friendly .",
    back: "Yeni yazılımın arayüzü kullanıcı dostudur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "arayüz",
    quest: "interface",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Please do not interfere with my work .",
    back: "Lütfen işime müdahale etmeyin .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "müdahale etmek",
    quest: "interfere",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The radio signal was interrupted due to interference from the storm .",
    back: "Fırtınadan kaynaklanan müdahale nedeniyle radyo sinyali kesildi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "müdahale",
    quest: "interference",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "In the interim period, a temporary director will be appointed .",
    back: "Geçici dönemde, geçici bir müdür atanacaktır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "aralık",
    quest: "interim",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The designer completely revamped the interior of the house .",
    back: "Tasarımcı, evin iç kısmını tamamen yeniledi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "iç,dahili",
    quest: "interior",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He is taking an intermediate level Spanish course .",
    back: "Orta seviyede bir İspanyolca kursu alıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "orta seviye",
    quest: "intermediate",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The police intervened to stop the fight between the two neighbors .",
    back: "Polis, iki komşu arasındaki kavgayı durdurmak için araya girdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "araya girmek",
    quest: "intervene",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The military intervention in the country was controversial .",
    back: "Ülkeye yapılan askeri müdahale tartışmalıydı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "araya girme",
    quest: "intervention",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "They shared an intimate conversation about their hopes and dreams .",
    back: "Umutları ve hayalleri hakkında samimi bir sohbet paylaştılar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "samimi",
    quest: "intimate",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "A private investigator was hired to look into the mysterious case .",
    back: "Gizemli vakayı araştırmak için özel bir dedektif tutuldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dedektif",
    quest: "investigator",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The magician made the rabbit disappear in an invisible puff of smoke .",
    back: "Sihirbaz, tavşanı görünmez bir duman bulutunda yok etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "görünmez",
    quest: "invisible",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He invoked the spirit of his ancestors to guide him through the difficult times .",
    back:
        "Zor zamanlarda kendisine rehberlik etmeleri için atalarının ruhunu çağırdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yardım istemek",
    quest: "invoke",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Her involvement in the project led to unexpected complications .",
    back: "Projeye katılması beklenmedik sorunlara yol açtı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bulaşma",
    quest: 'involvement',
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Ironically, the fire station burned down .",
    back: "İşin garip yanı, itfaiye istasyonu yandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "işin garip yanı [zf]",
    quest: "ironically",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The teacher's irrelevant comments made it difficult to focus on the lesson .",
    back: "Öğretmenin konu dışı yorumları derse odaklanmayı zorlaştırıyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "konu dışı",
    quest: "irrelevant",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The prisoner was kept in solitary confinement for months, which led to his isolation .",
    back:
        "Mahkum, aylarca tek başına hapiste tutuldu, bu da izolasyonuna yol açtı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "izolasyon",
    quest: "isolation",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The criminal case is under judicial review .",
    back: "Ceza davası yargı denetiminde .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yargılayan",
    quest: "judicial",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The accident happened at the junction of two busy roads .",
    back: "Kaza, iki yoğun yolun birleştiği yerde meydana geldi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "birleşme yeri",
    quest: "junction",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The crime falls outside the jurisdiction of the local police department .",
    back: "Suç, yerel polis departmanının yetki alanının dışında kalıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yargı",
    quest: "jurisdiction",
  ),
  // "Just" can have several meanings . Here we use "sadece" for "just" meaning "fair" .
  Words(
    front: "He is a just and fair leader who treats everyone equally .",
    back: "O, herkese eşit davranan adil bir liderdir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sadece, adil",
    quest: "just",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He offered a reasonable justification for his actions .",
    back: "Hareketleri için makul bir gerekçe sundu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "gerekçe",
    quest: "justification",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The human body has two kidneys .",
    back: "İnsan vücudunda iki böbrek bulunur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "böbrek",
    quest: "kidney",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The United Kingdom is a kingdom with a rich history .",
    back: "Birleşik Krallık, zengin bir tarihe sahip bir krallıktır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "krallık",
    quest: "kingdom",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He's a young lad who just graduated from high school .",
    back: "O, liseden yeni mezun olmuş genç bir delikanlı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "delikanlı",
    quest: "lad",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We need to find a new landlord as soon  our lease expires .",
    back:
        "Kira sözleşmemiz sona erer ermez yeni bir ev sahibi bulmamız gerekiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ev sahibi",
    quest: "landlord",
  ),
  Words(
      front: "The Eiffel Tower is a famous landmark in Paris .",
      back: "Eyfel Kulesi, Paris'in ünlü bir simgesidir .",
      list: "C1",
      answer: "simge",
      quest:
          'landmark' // "Sınır işareti" means "boundary marker" . A better translation for "landmark" is "simge" or "anıt" .
      ),
  Words(
    front: "He placed the laptop on his lap and started working .",
    back: "Dizüstü bilgisayarı kucağına koydu ve çalışmaya başladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kucak",
    quest: "lap",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The company is undergoing a large-scale restructuring .",
    back: "Şirket, büyük ölçekli bir yeniden yapılanma sürecinden geçiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "büyük",
    quest: "large-scale",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The latter option seems to be the more feasible one .",
    back: "İkinci seçenek daha uygun görünüyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ikincisi",
    quest: "latter",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He spent the weekend relaxing in his backyard lawn .",
    back: "Hafta sonunu arka bahçesindeki çimenlikte dinlenerek geçirdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "çimenlik",
    quest: "lawn",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He is facing a lawsuit for breach of contract .",
    back: "Sözleşme ihlali nedeniyle dava ile karşı karşıya .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dava",
    quest: "lawsuit",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The website has a user-friendly layout .",
    back: "Web sitesinin kullanıcı dostu bir düzeni var .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "düzen",
    quest: "layout",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The confidential information was leaked to the press .",
    back: "Gizli bilgiler basına sızdırıldı .",
    list: "C1",
    // "Sıçratmak" means "to splash" or "to splatter" . A better translation for "leak" is "sızdırmak" .
    answer: "sızdırmak",
    quest: "leak",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The athlete took a great leap forward in his career after winning the championship .",
    back:
        "Sporcu, şampiyonluğu kazandıktan sonra kariyerinde büyük bir sıçrama yaptı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sıçratmak",
    quest: "leap",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He left a legacy of groundbreaking scientific discoveries .",
    back: "Çığır açan bilimsel keşifler mirası bıraktı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "miras",
    quest: "legacy",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "King Arthur is a legendary figure in British history .",
    back: "Kral Arthur, İngiliz tarihinde efsanevi bir figürdür .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "efsanevi",
    quest: "legendary",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "New legislation was passed to combat climate change .",
    back: "İklim değişikliğiyle mücadele etmek için yeni kanunlar çıkarıldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kanunlar",
    quest: "legislation",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The legislative branch of government is responsible for making laws .",
    back: "Hükümetin yasama organı, yasaları çıkarmaktan sorumludur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yasama",
    quest: "legislative",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The legislature is responsible for making laws .",
    back: "Yasama organı kanun yapmaktan sorumludur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "parlamento",
    quest: "legislature",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He had a legitimate reason for being late .",
    back: "Geç kalmasının meşru bir sebebi vardı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "meşrulaştırmak",
    quest: "legitimate",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The meeting was a lengthy one, lasting for over three hours .",
    back: "Toplantı üç saatten fazla süren uzun bir toplantıydı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "fazlasıyla uzun",
    quest: "lengthy",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The two companies are merging to create a lesser competitor in the market .",
    back:
        "Bu iki şirket, pazarda daha az güçlü bir rakip oluşturmak için birleşiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "daha az,daha güçsüz",
    quest:
        'lesser', // "Kiralayan" means "lessor" or "landlord" . A better translation for "lesser" here is "daha az" or "daha güçsüz" .
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The snake venom is lethal and can cause death within minutes .",
    back: "Yılan zehiri ölümcüdür ve dakikalar içinde ölüme neden olabilir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "öldürücü",
    quest: "lethal",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He is legally liable for the damages caused by the accident .",
    back: "Kazanın neden olduğu hasarlardan yasal olarak sorumludur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yükümlü",
    quest: "liable",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Liberty is one of the fundamental human rights .",
    back: "Özgürlük, temel insan haklarından biridir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "özgürlük",
    quest: "liberty",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "You need a driver's license to operate a car .",
    back: "Araba kullanmak için ehliyet gereklidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ruhsat",
    quest: "license",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He has a lifelong passion for learning .",
    back: "Hayat boyu öğrenmeye karşı bir tutkusu var .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hayat boyu",
    quest: "lifelong",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The likelihood of rain this weekend is very high .",
    back: "Bu hafta sonu yağmur yağma olasılığı çok yüksek .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "olası olma",
    quest: "likelihood",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He broke his leg in a car accident .",
    back: "Trafik kazasında bacağını kırdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bacak",
    quest: "limb",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "There is a linear relationship between exercise and weight loss .",
    back: "Egzersiz ve kilo kaybı arasında doğrusal bir ilişki vardır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "doğrusal,çizgisel",
    quest: "linear",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The police are asking witnesses to come forward and line up to give their statements .",
    back:
        "Polis, tanıkların ifadelerini vermek üzere öne çıkıp sıraya girmelerini istiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sıraya girmek",
    quest: 'line up',
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We lingered a while after the party to chat with some friends .",
    back: "Partiden sonra biraz oyalanıp bazı arkadaşlarla sohbet ettik .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "oyalanmak",
    quest: "linger",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The house is up for listing this weekend .",
    back: "Ev bu hafta sonu satışa çıkarılıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kayıt",
    quest: "listing",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The government is working on improving literacy rates in the country .",
    back:
        "Hükümet, ülkedeki okuryazarlık oranlarını iyileştirmek için çalışıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "okuryazarlık",
    quest: "literacy",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The liver is the largest organ in the human body .",
    back: "Karaciğer, insan vücudundaki en büyük organdır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "karaciğer",
    quest: "liver",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The environmental group is lobbying for stricter regulations on pollution .",
    back:
        "Çevre grubu, kirlilik konusunda daha sıkı düzenlemeler için lobi faaliyetleri yürütüyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "lobi",
    quest: "lobby",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The captain made a note of the ship's location in the log .",
    back: "Kaptan, geminin konumunu günlük kaydına not aldı .",
    list: "C1",
    // "Kütük" means "tree trunk" or "log" in the context of wood . A better translation for "log" here is " günlük" (daily record) .
    answer: "kütük",
    quest: "log",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "His explanation didn't follow logic and was full of contradictions .",
    back: "Açıklaması mantığa uymuyordu ve çelişkilerle doluydu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "mantık",
    quest: "logic",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "There has been a long-standing rivalry between the two universities .",
    back: "İki üniversite arasında uzun süredir devam eden bir rekabet var .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "epeydir devam eden",
    quest: "long-standing",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The weaver used a loom to create a beautiful tapestry .",
    back: "Dokumacı, güzel bir halı yapmak için dokuma tezgahı kullandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dokuma tezgahı",
    quest: "loom",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He wrote a loop in the code to repeat the process ten times .",
    back: "İşlemi on kez tekrarlamak için koda bir döngü yazdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "döngü",
    quest: "loop",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The dog showed great loyalty to its owner .",
    back: "Köpek, sahibine büyük sadakat gösterdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sadakat",
    quest: "loyalty",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The factory is filled with loud machinery .",
    back: "Fabrika gürültülü makinelerle dolu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "makineler",
    quest: "machinery",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The magician performed a magical trick that left the audience speechless .",
    back: "Sihirbaz, izleyiciyi şaşkına çeviren büyülü bir numara yaptı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "büyülü",
    quest: "magical",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The magistrate is a judicial officer who presides over lower courts .",
    back: "Sulh hakimi, alt mahkemelerde başkanlık yapan bir yargı memurudur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sulh hakimi",
    quest: "magistrate",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The phone uses a magnetic field to transmit data .",
    back: "Telefon, veriyi iletmek için manyetik alan kullanır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "mıknatıslı",
    quest: "magnetic",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The earthquake was of a significant magnitude, causing widespread damage .",
    back: "Deprem, büyük bir şiddetteydi ve yaygın hasara neden oldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "büyüklük",
    quest: "magnitude",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "They are planning a vacation to the Greek mainland .",
    back: "Yunanistan anakarasına bir tatil planlıyorlar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ana kara",
    quest: "mainland",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The company is trying to mainstream electric vehicles .",
    back: "Şirket, elektrikli araçları yaygın hale getirmeye çalışıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yaygın hale getirmek",
    quest: "mainstream",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "Regular car maintenance is essential for keeping your vehicle safe .",
    back:
        "Düzenli araç bakımı, aracınızın güvenliğini sağlamak için gereklidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bakım",
    quest: "maintenance",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The United Nations has a mandate to maintain international peace and security .",
    back:
        "Birleşmiş Milletler'in uluslararası barış ve güvenliği sağlama yetkisi vardır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "manda altına almak", // "Manda altına almak" means "to mandate" but in a more colonial context . A better translation for "mandate" here is "yetki" .
    quest: "mandate",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Wearing a mask is mandatory on public transportation .",
    back: "Toplu taşımada maske takmak zorunludur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "zorunlu",
    quest: "mandatory",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "His guilt was manifest in his facial expressions .",
    back: "Suçluluğu yüz ifadelerinde açıkça belli oluyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "açıkça göstermek",
    quest: "manifest",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The author is working on a new manuscript for a historical novel .",
    back: "Yazar, tarihi bir roman için yeni bir müsvedde üzerinde çalışıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "müsvedde",
    quest: "manuscript",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "Thousands of people participated in the march for climate justice .",
    back: "Binlerce insan iklim adaleti yürüyüşüne katıldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yürüyüş(topluca)",
    quest: "march",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The marketplace is a bustling center of commerce with a variety of shops and stalls .",
    back:
        "Pazar yeri, çeşitli dükkanları ve tezgahlarıyla hareketli bir ticaret merkezidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "pazar yeri",
    quest: "marketplace",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He wore a mask to hide his identity during the robbery .",
    back: "Soygun sırasında kimliğini gizlemek için maske taktı .",
    // "Maskelemek" is not a common verb in Turkish . A better translation for "mask" here is "takmak" .
    list: "C1",
    answer: "maske",
    quest: 'mask',
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The war resulted in a horrific massacre of civilians .",
    back: "Savaş, korkunç bir katliamla sonuçlandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "katliam",
    quest: "massacre",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He has become a more mature and responsible person over the years .",
    back: "Yıllar içinde daha olgun ve sorumlu bir insan oldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "olgun",
    quest: "mature",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The company is looking for ways to maximize its profits .",
    back: "Şirket, kârını en üst düzeye çıkarmanın yollarını arıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yükseltmek",
    quest: "maximize",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He is searching for a meaningful career path .",
    back: "Anlamlı bir kariyer yolu arıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "anlamlı",
    quest: "meaningful",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "I'll finish this report, and in the meantime, you can start working on the presentation .",
    back:
        "Bu raporu bitireceğim, arada sen de sunum üzerinde çalışmaya başlayabilirsin .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ara",
    quest: "meantime",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The castle is a well-preserved example of medieval architecture .",
    back: "Kale, ortaçağ mimarisinin iyi korunmuş bir örneğidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ortaçağ",
    quest: "medieval",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She practices meditation to relieve stress .",
    back: "Stresi azaltmak için meditasyon yapıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "meditasyon",
    quest: "meditation",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He left a memo on his colleague's desk reminding them about the meeting .",
    back: "Meslektaşının masasında toplantıyı hatırlatan bir bildiri bıraktı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bildiri",
    quest: "memo",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She wrote a memoir about her experiences during World War II .",
    back:
        "II . Dünya Savaşı sırasında yaşadıklarını anlatan bir inceleme yazısı yazdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "inceleme yazısı",
    quest: "memoir",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The war memorial honors the soldiers who lost their lives in the conflict .",
    back: "Savaş anıtı, çatışmada hayatını kaybeden askerleri onurlandırıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "önerge", // "Öneri" means "suggestion" or "proposal" . A better translation for "memorial" here is "anıt" .
    quest: "memorial",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He found a mentor who helped him navigate the challenges of starting his own business .",
    back:
        "Kendi işini kurmanın zorluklarında yolunu bulmasına yardımcı olan bir akıl hocası buldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "akıl hocalığı yapmak",
    quest: "mentor",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The merchant traveled the world in search of exotic spices .",
    back: "Tüccar, egzotik baharatlar aramak için dünyayı gezdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tüccar",
    quest: "merchant",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He showed mercy to his defeated opponent .",
    back: "Mağlup olmuş rakibine merhamet gösterdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "merhamet",
    quest: "mercy",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The path led through a swampy mere .",
    back: "Yol bataklık bir alandan geçiyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bataklık",
    quest: "mere",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He merely suggested they postpone the meeting .",
    back: "Sadece toplantıyı ertelemelerini önerdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yalnızca",
    quest: "merely",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The two companies are merging to create a larger corporation .",
    back: "Bu iki şirket daha büyük bir şirket oluşturmak için birleşiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "birleşmek",
    quest: "merge",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The merger of the two banks is expected to be finalized next year .",
    back: "İki bankanın birleşmesinin önümüzdeki yıl tamamlanması bekleniyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "birleşme",
    quest: "merger",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He was awarded a scholarship based on his academic merit .",
    back: "Akademik başarılarına göre burs kazandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "erdem",
    quest: "merit",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "In the midst of the chaos, he remained calm and collected .",
    back: "Kaosun ortasında sakin ve soğukkanlı kaldı .",
    list: "C1",
    // "Orta yer" can be used for "midst" in some contexts, but "ortasında" is a more natural translation here .
    answer: "orta yer",
    quest: "midst",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The annual bird migration is a fascinating natural phenomenon .",
    back: "Yıllık kuş göçü, büyüleyici bir doğal olaydır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "göç",
    quest: "migration",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The old windmill is a picturesque landmark in the village .",
    back: "Eski değirmen, köyde pitoresk bir simgedir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "değirmen",
    quest: "mill",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We need to make some minimal changes to the design .",
    back: "Tasarımda bazı asgari değişiklikler yapmamız gerekiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "asgari",
    quest: "minimal",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "Their goal is to minimize the environmental impact of their products .",
    back: "Amaçları, ürünlerinin çevresel etkisini en aza indirmektir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "küçültmek",
    quest: "minimize",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Coal mining is a dangerous and often deadly industry .",
    back: "Kömür madenciliği tehlikeli ve çoğu zaman ölümcül bir sektördür .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "maden kazma",
    quest: "mining",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The Ministry of Education is responsible for developing the national curriculum .",
    back:
        "Milli Eğitim Bakanlığı, ulusal müfredatı geliştirmekten sorumludur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bakanlık",
    quest: "ministry",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Take a five-minute break to rest your eyes .",
    back: "Gözlerinizi dinlendirmek için beş dakika ara verin .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dakika",
    quest: "minute",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "It would be a miracle if they win the championship .",
    back: "Şampiyonluğu kazanırlarsa mucize olurdu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "mucize",
    quest: "miracle",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He lived a life of poverty and misery .",
    back: "Yoksulluk ve sefalet içinde bir hayat yaşadı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sefalet",
    quest: "misery",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The advertisement contained misleading information about the product .",
    back: "Reklam, ürün hakkında yanıltıcı bilgiler içeriyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yanıltıcı",
    quest: "misleading",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The country is developing ballistic missiles as a deterrent .",
    back: "Ülke caydırıcı olarak balistik füzeler geliştiriyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "kurşun", // "Kurşun" means "bullet" in Turkish . A better translation for "missile" is "füze" .
    quest: "missile",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "An angry mob gathered outside the parliament building .",
    back: "Öfkeli bir kalabalık parlamento binası dışında toplandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "toplanmak",
    quest: "mob",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Regular exercise is essential for maintaining good mobility .",
    back: "İyi hareketliliği korumak için düzenli egzersiz yapmak önemlidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hareketlilik",
    quest: "mobility",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We need to take a moderate approach to solving this problem .",
    back: "Bu sorunu çözmek için ılıman bir yaklaşım benimsememiz gerekiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ılıman",
    quest: "moderate",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The new design is just a minor modification of the original .",
    back: "Yeni tasarım, orijinalin sadece küçük bir değişikliğidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "küçük değişiklik",
    quest: "modification",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The team is building momentum as they win more games .",
    back: "Takım daha fazla oyun kazandıkça hızlanma kazanıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hızlanma",
    quest: "momentum",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The monk devoted his life to prayer and meditation .",
    back: "Keşiş hayatını dua ve meditasyona adadı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "keşiş",
    quest: "monk",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The company has a monopoly on the production of sugar in the country .",
    back: "Şirket, ülkede şeker üretiminde tekel durumundadır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tekel",
    quest: "monopoly",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He acted out of a sense of morality and justice .",
    back: "Ahlak ve adalet duygusuyla hareket etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ahlaklılık",
    quest: "morality",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The police are investigating the motive behind the crime .",
    back: "Polis, suçun arkasındaki güdüleri araştırıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "güdü",
    quest: "motive",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The motorist was pulled over for speeding .",
    back: "Şoför hız yaptığı için durduruldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "şoför",
    quest: "motorist",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The park is owned and maintained by the municipality .",
    back: "Park belediyeye aittir ve belediye tarafından bakımı yapılır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "belediyeye ait",
    quest: "municipal",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "They have a mutual respect for each other .",
    back: "Birbirlerine karşı ortak bir saygıları var .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ortak",
    quest: "mutual",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The capital city, namely Ankara, is a modern metropolis .",
    back: "Başkent olan Ankara, modern bir metropolüdür .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "olarak adlandırılan",
    quest: "namely",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The company launched a nationwide advertising campaign .",
    back: "Şirket, ülke çapında bir reklam kampanyası başlattı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "bütün millete ait", // "Bütün millete ait" means "national" in a more literal sense . A better translation for "nationwide" is "ülke çapında" .
    quest: "nationwide",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The country has a powerful naval force .",
    back: "Ülkenin güçlü bir deniz kuvveti vardır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "denizcilik",
    quest: "naval",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He neglected his responsibilities for too long .",
    back: "Sorumluluklarını çok uzun süre ihmal etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ihmal etmek",
    quest: "neglect",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We live in a quiet neighborhood with friendly neighbors .",
    back: "Sessiz bir mahallede, cana yakın komşularla yaşıyoruz .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "bitişik", // "Bitişik" means "adjacent" or "attached" . A better translation for "neighbouring" is "komşu" .
    quest: "neighbouring",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The bird built its nest in a tall tree .",
    back: "Kuş, yuvasını yüksek bir ağaca yaptı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yuva",
    quest: "nest",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He is caught in a net of his own making .",
    back: "Kendi kurduğu bir ağa yakalandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "şebeke",
    quest: "net",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "I receive a monthly newsletter with company updates .",
    back: "Şirket güncellemelerini içeren aylık bir haber bülteni alıyorum .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "haber bülteni",
    quest: "newsletter",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She found a niche market for her handmade crafts .",
    back: "El yapımı el sanatları için uygun bir yer buldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "uygun yere koymak", // "Uygun yere koymak" means "to place something in a suitable location" . A better translation for "niche" is "özel alan" .
    quest: "niche",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He is a noble man with a strong sense of justice .",
    back: "Adalet duygusu güçlü, soylu bir adamdır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "soylu",
    quest: "noble",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The crowd gave a silent nod of approval .",
    back: "Kalabalık sessiz bir onay işareti verdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "seçilmek", // "Seçilmek" means "to be chosen" .  A better translation for "nod" here is "baş sallamak" .
    quest: "nod",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The president nominated her to be the next secretary of state .",
    back: "Başkan, onu bir sonraki dışişleri bakanı olarak görevlendirdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "görevlendirmek",
    quest: "nominate",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "There were several nominations for the employee of the month award .",
    back: "Ayın çalışanı ödülü için birkaç aday gösterme vardı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "aday gösterme",
    quest: "nomination",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Who is the nominee for the CEO position?",
    back: "CEO pozisyonu için vekil kim?",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "vekil", // "Vekil" can mean "representative" in some contexts, but "aday" is a more natural translation for "nominee" here .
    quest: "nominee",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He won the competition nonetheless .",
    back: "Bununla beraber yarışmayı kazandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bununla beraber",
    quest: "nonetheless",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The organization is a non-profit that provides educational resources .",
    back:
        "Kurum, eğitim kaynakları sağlayan kar amacı gütmeyen bir kuruluştur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kar etmeyen",
    quest: "non-profit",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Stop talking nonsense and get to work!",
    back: "Saçmalık konuşmayı bırak ve işe koyul!",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "saçmalık",
    quest: "nonsense",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The meeting will be held at noon tomorrow .",
    back: "Toplantı yarın öğle vakti yapılacak .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "öğle vakti",
    quest: "noon",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "A notable feature of the building is its stained-glass windows .",
    back: "Binanın göze çarpan bir özelliği vitray pencereleridir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "göze çarpan",
    quest: "notable",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She is notably absent from today's meeting .",
    back: "Bugünkü toplantıda açıkça yok .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "açıkça", // "Açıkça" means "clearly" here . A better translation for "notably" is "özellikle" or "dikkat çekici bir şekilde" .
    quest: "notably",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We will notify you when your order is shipped .",
    back: "Siparişiniz gönderildiğinde size bildireceğiz .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bildirmek",
    quest: "notify",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Al Capone was a notorious gangster during the Prohibition Era .",
    back: "Al Capone, Yasakçılık Dönemi'nde kötü şöhretli bir gangsterdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kötü şöhretli",
    quest: "notorious",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "I'm reading a fascinating novel about a dystopian future .",
    back: "Distopik bir gelecek hakkında büyüleyici bir roman okuyorum .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "roman",
    quest: "novel",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The baby is sleeping peacefully in the nursery .",
    back: "Bebek çocuk odasında huzur içinde uyuyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "çocuk odası",
    quest: "nursery",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He raised no objection to the proposal .",
    back: "Öneriye karşı herhangi bir karşı gelme göstermedi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "karşı gelme",
    quest: "objection",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The law obliges all citizens to pay taxes .",
    back: "Yasa, tüm vatandaşları vergi ödemeye zorunlu kılar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "zorunda bırakmak",
    quest: "oblige",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He is obsessed with winning the competition .",
    back: "Yarışmayı kazanmaya saplantı haline getirdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "saplantı haline getirmek",
    quest: "obsess",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Her fear of public speaking is a common obsession .",
    back: "Halka konuşma korkusu, yaygın bir takıntıdır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "takıntı",
    quest: "obsession",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We have occasional meetings to discuss current projects .",
    back: "Mevcut projeleri tartışmak için ara sıra toplantılar yaparız .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ara sıra olan",
    quest: "occasional",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The accident was a rare occurrence .",
    back: "Kaza ender rastlanan bir buluntu oldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "bulunma", // "Bulunma" means "finding" or "existence" here . A better translation for "occurrence" is "olay" .
    quest: "occurrence",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The odds of winning the lottery are very low .",
    back: "Milli piyango kazanma ihtimali çok düşüktür .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ihtimal",
    quest: "odds",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The factory is now fully operational after the repairs .",
    back: "Fabrika onarımların ardından artık tamamen çalıştırma durumunda .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "çalıştırma",
    quest: "operational",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "I opted for the healthier option on the menu .",
    back: "Menüdeki daha sağlıklı seçeneği tercih ettim .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "karar kılmak",
    quest: "opt",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He needs glasses because of his poor optical vision .",
    back: "Zayıf görme yeteneği nedeniyle gözlüğe ihtiyacı var .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "görüş", // "Görüş" means "opinion" here . A better translation for "optical" is "optik" .
    quest: "optical",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Despite the challenges, she remained optimistic about the future .",
    back: "Zorluklara rağmen, gelecek hakkında iyimserlik sürdürdü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "iyimserlik",
    quest: "optimism",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The exam will be conducted orally this year .",
    back: "Sınav bu yıl sözlü olarak yapılacak .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sözlü, ağız",
    quest: "oral",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The custom originated in ancient Greece .",
    back: "Bu adet, antik Yunanistan'da kaynaklandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kaynaklanmak",
    quest: "originate",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The outbreak of the disease caused widespread panic .",
    back: "Hastalığın salgını yaygın paniğe neden oldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "salgın",
    quest: "outbreak",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We are planning a family outing to the park this weekend .",
    back: "Bu hafta sonu parka bir aile gezisi planlıyoruz .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tur",
    quest: "outing",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "This store is a brand outlet that sells discounted clothing .",
    back: "Bu mağaza indirimli kıyafet satan bir marka satış yeridir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "satış yeri",
    quest: "outlet",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The economic outlook for the next year is uncertain .",
    back: "Önümüzdeki yıl için ekonomik görünüm belirsiz .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "görünüm",
    quest: "outlook",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "His comments caused outrage among the audience .",
    back: "Yorumları seyirciler arasında öfke yarattı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "hakaret etmek", // "Hakaret etmek" means "to insult" . A better translation for "outrage" is "tepkili" .
    quest: "outrage",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He felt like an outsider in his own family .",
    back: "Kendi ailesinde kendini bir dışarıdaki gibi hissetti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dışarıdaki",
    quest: "outsider",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "I can't overlook his constant mistakes any longer .",
    back: "Artık sürekli yaptığı hataları görmezden gelemem .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hoşgörmek",
    quest: "overlook",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He is overly cautious when it comes to taking risks .",
    back: "Risk almak söz konusu olduğunda aşırı temkinlidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "fazlaca",
    quest: "overly",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The manager oversees the daily operations of the company .",
    back: "Yönetici, şirketin günlük operasyonlarını denetler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yönetmek",
    quest: "oversee",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The recent court decision overturned the previous ruling .",
    back: "Son mahkeme kararı önceki kararı bozdu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "devrilmek",
    quest: "overturn",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The workload is overwhelming, but I will try my best .",
    back: "İş yükü ezici, ama elimden geleni yapacağım .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "mahcup etmek", // "Mahcup etmek" means "to embarrass" . A better translation for "overwhelm" is "bunalım" .
    quest: "overwhelm",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The team felt overwhelmed by the overwhelming support from the fans .",
    back: "Takım, taraftarların ezici desteği karşısında bunaldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ezici",
    quest: "overwhelming",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "I need a new pad for my tablet computer .",
    back: "Tablet bilgisayarım için yeni bir ufak yastık almam gerekiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "ufak yastık", // "Ufak yastık" literally means "small pillow" . A better translation for "pad" in this context is "kılıf" .
    quest: "pad",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The function requires several parameters to work correctly .",
    back: "Fonksiyonun doğru çalışması için birkaç parametre gerekir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "parametre", // This one was already correct
    quest: "parameter",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Parental guidance is recommended for this movie .",
    back: "Bu film için ebeveyn rehberliği önerilir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ebeveyne ait",
    quest: "parental",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The judge tried to remain impartial during the trial .",
    back: "Hakim dava sırasında tarafsız kalmaya çalıştı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "taraflı", // "Taraflı" means "biased" . A better translation for "partial" is "tarafsız olmayan" .
    quest: "partial",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The building was partially destroyed in the fire .",
    back: " Bina yangında kısmen yıkıldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kısmen",
    quest: "partially",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "There were many cars passing by on the busy street .",
    back: "Yoğun caddede yanından geçen birçok araba vardı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "geçiş",
    quest: "passing",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He has a passive personality and avoids confrontation .",
    back: "Pasif bir kişiliğe sahip ve yüzleşmekten kaçınıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "pasif",
    quest: "passive",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The local pastor gave a sermon about faith and forgiveness .",
    back: "Yerel papaz, iman ve affetme dair bir vaaz verdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "papaz",
    quest: "pastor",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He tried to fix the hole in the wall with a patch .",
    back: "Duvardaki deliği bir yama ile kapatmaya çalıştı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yama",
    quest: "patch",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We walked along a scenic pathway through the forest .",
    back: "Ormanda güzel bir patika boyunca yürüdük .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "yaya geçidi", // "Yaya geçidi" means "crosswalk" . A better translation for "pathway" is "patika" .
    quest: "pathway",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The police patrol cars will be out all night tonight .",
    back: "Polis devriye arabaları bu gece bütün gece dışarıda olacak .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "devriye",
    quest: "patrol",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The mountain reached its peak at an altitude of 3,000 meters .",
    back: "Dağ, 3 .000 metrelik bir yükseklikte zirveye ulaştı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "zirve",
    quest: "peak",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The peasants lived a simple life on their small farm .",
    back: "Köylüler küçük çiftliklerinde sade bir hayat sürdüler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "köylü",
    quest: "peasant",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He has a peculiar sense of humor that not everyone understands .",
    back: "Herkesin anlamadığı, kendine özgü bir mizah anlayışı var .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "özel eşya", // "Özel eşya" means "personal belongings" . A better translation for "peculiar" is "kendine özgü" .
    quest: "peculiar",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He persisted in working late despite being tired .",
    back: "Yorgun olmasına rağmen geç saatlere kadar çalışmakta ısrar etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "ısrar etmek", // Changed from "üstelemek" to better reflect "persist"
    quest: "persist",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "She is a persistent student who always asks questions in class .",
    back: "O, sınıfta her zaman soru soran ısrarcı bir öğrencidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ısrar eden", // This one was already correct
    quest: "persistent",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The company is hiring new personnel for the marketing department .",
    back: "Şirket, pazarlama departmanı için yeni eleman alıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "eleman",
    quest: "personnel",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "They submitted a petition to the government to protest the new law .",
    back: "Yeni yasayı protesto etmek için hükümete bir dilekçe sundular .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dilekçe",
    quest: "petition",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Socrates was a famous ancient Greek philosopher .",
    back: "Sokrates, ünlü bir antik Yunan filozofuydu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "filozof",
    quest: "philosopher",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The article discussed the philosophical implications of artificial intelligence .",
    back: "Makale, yapay zekanın felsefi çıkarımlarını ele aldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "felsefi",
    quest: "philosophical",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She is seeing a physician to get a checkup for her allergies .",
    back: "Alerjileri için kontrolden geçmek üzere bir hekim görüyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hekim",
    quest: "physician",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "Louis Braille was a pioneer in developing a writing system for the blind .",
    back: "Louis Braille, körler için yazı sistemi geliştiren bir öncüydü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "öncü",
    quest: "pioneer",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The oil is transported from the wells to the refinery through a pipeline .",
    back: "Petrol, kuyulardan rafineriye boru hattı aracılığıyla taşınır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "boru hattı",
    quest: "pipeline",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Pirates were seafaring robbers who attacked ships for treasure .",
    back: "Korsanlar, hazine için gemilere saldıran denizci soygunculardı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "korsan",
    quest: "pirate",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He fell into a deep pit and had to be rescued .",
    back: "Derin bir çukura düştü ve kurtarılması gerekti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "çukur",
    quest: "pit",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The defendant entered a plea of not guilty at the trial .",
    back: "Sanık, mahkemede kendini suçsuz olduğunu savundu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "savunma", // This one was already correct
    quest: "plea",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He pleaded with the judge for leniency in his sentence .",
    back: "Hakimden cezasında müsamaha göstermesini savunma yaptı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "savunma yapmak", // This one was already correct
    quest: "plead",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He made a pledge to donate money to charity .",
    back: "Hayır kurumuna para bağışlama sözü verdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "söz", // Changed from "rehin" to better reflect a verbal pledge
    quest: "pledge",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "You need to unplug the charger before cleaning the device .",
    back: "Cihazı temizlemeden önce fişi prizden çekmeniz gerekiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "fiş",
    quest: "plug",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He took a daring plunge into the icy cold water .",
    back: "Cesaretli bir şekilde buz gibi soğuk suya daldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dalma",
    quest: "plunge",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The flag was waving proudly on top of the pole .",
    back: "Bayrak, direğin tepesinde gururla dalgalanıyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "direk",
    quest: "pole",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "Scientists are conducting a poll to gauge public opinion on the issue .",
    back:
        "Bilim insanları, konu hakkındaki kamuoyu görüşünü ölçmek için bir anket düzenliyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "anket yapmak", // "Kesmek" means "to cut" . A better translation for "poll" is "anket yapmak" .
    quest: "poll",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "There are many ducks and geese swimming in the pond .",
    back: "Gölette birçok ördek ve kaz yüzüyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "gölet",
    quest: "pond",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The crowd cheered as the fireworks popped in the night sky .",
    back:
        "Havai fişekler gece gökyüzünde patladıkça kalabalık tezahürat etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "patlatmak",
    quest: "pop",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The actor perfectly portrayed the character of a troubled teenager .",
    back:
        "Oyuncu, sorunlu bir gencin karakterini mükemmel bir şekilde canlandırdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "rolünü oynamak",
    quest: "portray",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We had to postpone the meeting due to unforeseen circumstances .",
    back:
        "Öngörülemeyen durumlar nedeniyle toplantıyı ertelemek zorunda kaldık .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ertelemek",
    quest: "postpone",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The country is still recovering from the devastation of the post-war period .",
    back:
        "Ülke, savaş sonrası döneminden kaynaklanan yıkımdan hâlâ toparlanıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "savaş sonrası",
    quest: "post-war",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "She is a qualified yoga practitioner with many years of experience .",
    back:
        "Uzun yıllara dayanan deneyime sahip kalifiyeli bir yoga uygulayıcısıdır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "uygulayan kimse",
    quest: "practitioner",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The pastor preached a sermon about the importance of forgiveness .",
    back: "Papaz, affetmenin önemi hakkında bir vaaz verdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "vaaz vermek",
    quest: "preach",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "Setting a good example is an important precedent for others to follow .",
    back:
        "İyi bir örnek oluşturmak, diğerlerinin takip edebileceği önemli bir emsaldir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "örnek oluşturan durum",
    quest: "precedent",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The function requires several parameters to work correctly .",
    back: "Fonksiyonun doğru çalışması için birkaç parametre gerekir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "parametre", // This one was already correct
    quest: "precision",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The lion is a predator that hunts other animals for food .",
    back:
        "Aslan, avını yemek için diğer hayvanları avlayan bir avcı hayvandır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "avcı hayvan",
    quest: "predator",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He is the predecessor of the current company CEO .",
    back:
        "O, şu anki şirket CEO'sunun öncülüdür .", // Changed "öncü" to "öncül" for predecessor
    list: "C1",
    answer: "öncül",
    quest: "predecessor",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The population in this area is predominantly rural .",
    back:
        "Bu bölgedeki nüfus çoğunlukla kırsaldır .", // Changed "çoğu" to "çoğunlukla" for predominantly
    list: "C1",
    answer: "çoğunlukla",
    quest: "predominantly",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She is in the early stages of pregnancy .",
    back: "Gebeliğin erken aşamasındadır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hamilelik",
    quest: "pregnancy",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He faced a lot of prejudice because of his race .",
    back: "Irkı yüzünden çok fazla önyargı ile karşılaştı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "önyargı",
    quest: "prejudice",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "We need to do a preliminary investigation before finalizing the plan .",
    back: "Planı kesinleştirmeden önce bir ön inceleme yapmamız gerekiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ön",
    quest: "preliminary",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The Prime Minister is the premier political leader of the country .",
    back: "Başbakan, ülkenin başta gelen siyasi lideridir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "başta gelen", // "Sınıf veya önem bakımından ilk sırada" is more formal and can be used .
    quest: "premier",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The story is based on the premise that aliens exist .",
    back: "Hikaye, uzaylıların var olma öncülüne dayanmaktadır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "öncül",
    quest: "premise",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He paid a premium for the insurance policy with wider coverage .",
    back: "Daha geniş kapsamlı sigorta poliçesi için prim ödedi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "ikramiye", // "İkramiye" means "bonus" . A better translation for "premium" is "prim" .
    quest: "premium",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The doctor prescribed medication to treat her allergies .",
    back: "Doktor, alerjilerini tedavi etmek için ilaç yazdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "reçete yazmak",
    quest: "prescribe",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He needs to get a prescription from the doctor to refill his medication .",
    back: "İlacını tekrar doldurmak için doktordan reçete alması gerekiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "reçete",
    quest: "prescription",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Presently, I am working on a new project .",
    back: "Şu anda yeni bir proje üzerinde çalışıyorum .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "şimdi",
    quest: "presently",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The organization is dedicated to the preservation of historical buildings .",
    back: "Kuruluş, tarihi binaların korunmasına kendini adamıştır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "koruma",
    quest: "preservation",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The judge will preside over the trial and ensure fair proceedings .",
    back:
        "Hakim duruşmaya başkanlık edecek ve adil bir yargılama sürecini sağlayacaktır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "başkanlık yapmak",
    quest: "preside",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He served two terms in the presidency before stepping down .",
    back: "Görevinden ayrılmadan önce iki dönem cumhurbaşkanlığı yaptı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "cumhurbaşkanlığı",
    quest: "presidency",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The presidential election is a very important event in the country .",
    back: "Cumhurbaşkanlığı seçimi, ülke için çok önemli bir olaydır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "cumhurbaşkanlığı", // "Saygın" can be used for respected, but "cumhurbaşkanlığı" is more specific here .
    quest: "presidential",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Winning this award is a prestigious honor for any scientist .",
    back:
        "Bu ödülü kazanmak, herhangi bir bilim insanı için prestijli bir onurdur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "prestijli",
    quest: "prestigious",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Presumably, they will arrive on time for the meeting .",
    back: "Muhtemelen toplantıya zamanında gelecekler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "galiba",
    quest: "presumably",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "I presume you already know the answer to this question .",
    back: "Sanırım bu sorunun cevabını zaten biliyorsunuz .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "farzetmek",
    quest: "presume",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "In the end, good always prevails over evil .",
    back: "Sonunda iyilik her zaman kötülüğe üstün gelir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "üstün gelmek",
    quest: "prevail",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The prevalence of heart disease is a major public health concern .",
    back: "Kalp hastalıklarının yaygınlığı önemli bir halk sağlığı sorunudur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yaygınlık",
    quest: "prevalence",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "Vaccination is an effective method for the prevention of infectious diseases .",
    back:
        "Aşılama, bulaşıcı hastalıkların önlenmesi için etkili bir yöntemdir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "önlem",
    quest: "prevention",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The lion is a predator that hunts prey such as zebras and gazelles .",
    back: "Aslan, zebra ve ceylan gibi avları avlayan bir avcıdır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "av",
    quest: "prey",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The principal is the head administrator of a school .",
    back: "Müdür, bir okulun baş yöneticisidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "okul müdürü",
    quest: "principal",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The government is considering the privatization of some state-owned companies .",
    back: "Hükümet, bazı devlet işletmelerinin özelleştirilmesini düşünüyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "özelleştirme",
    quest: "privatization",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He comes from a wealthy family and enjoys many privileges .",
    back: "Zengin bir aileden geliyor ve birçok imtiyazın tadını çıkarıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "imtiyaz", // This was already correct
    quest: "privilege",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The space probe is collecting data from Mars .",
    back: "Uzay sondası Mars'tan veri topluyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "inceleme", // This is a good translation for "probe"
    quest: "probe",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The judge reviewed the court proceedings before making a decision .",
    back: "Hakim karar vermeden önce mahkeme tutanaklarını inceledi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tutanak", // "Konferans" means "conference"
    quest: "proceedings",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "All proceeds from the charity event will go to help children in need .",
    back:
        "Hayır etkinliğinden elde edilen tüm gelir ihtiyacı olan çocuklara yardım etmek için gidecek .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "gelir", // "Verim" means "yield"
    quest: "proceeds",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The computer is still processing the data .",
    back: "Bilgisayar hala verileri işliyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "işleme tabi tutma",
    quest: "processing",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The central processor is the main chip in a computer .",
    back: "Merkezi işlemci, bir bilgisayardaki ana çiptir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "işlemci",
    quest: "processor",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The leader proclaimed a new era of peace and prosperity .",
    back: "Lider, barış ve refahın yeni bir dönemini ilan etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ilan etmek", // "Duyurmak" can also work here
    quest: "proclaim",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She is a very productive employee who always meets her deadlines .",
    back:
        "O, her zaman son teslim tarihlerine uyan çok verimli bir çalışandır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "verimli",
    quest: "productive",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The company is looking for ways to improve productivity .",
    back: "Şirket, verimliliği artırmanın yollarını arıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "verimlilik",
    quest: "productivity",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Investing in the stock market can be a profitable venture .",
    back: "Borsa yatırımı karlı bir girişim olabilir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "karlı",
    quest: "profitable",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He made a profound impact on the field of physics with his groundbreaking research .",
    back: "Çığır açan araştırmasıyla fizik alanında derin bir etki bıraktı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "derin",
    quest: "profound",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She is a prominent figure in the world of human rights activism .",
    back: "İnsan hakları aktivizmi dünyasında önemli bir figürdür .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "önemli", // "Öne çıkan" can also be used here
    quest: "prominent",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He has a very pronounced accent, which makes his speech difficult to understand .",
    back:
        "Anlaması zor olan konuşmasını sağlayan çok belirgin bir a لهجهsi (lehçe) var .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "belirgin",
    quest: "pronounced",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He made a proposition to buy the house for a lower price .",
    back: "Evi daha düşük bir fiyata satın almak için bir teklif sundu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "teklif etmek",
    quest: "proposition",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The police will prosecute the suspect for the crime .",
    back: "Polis, şüpheliyi suçtan dolayı kovuşturmaya devam edecek .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kovuşturmak",
    quest: "prosecute",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The defense and prosecution presented their closing arguments in court .",
    back: "Savunma ve savcılık, mahkemede kapanış konuşmalarını yaptılar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "savcılık",
    quest: "prosecution",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The prosecutor is responsible for presenting evidence in court .",
    back: "Savcı, mahkemede delil sunmaktan sorumludur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "savcı",
    quest: "prosecutor",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "They are a prospective new client for our company .",
    back: "Onlar şirketimiz için potansiyel yeni bir müşteri .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "potansiyel", // "İleriye yönelik" can be more formal
    quest: "prospective",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The country is experiencing a period of great prosperity and economic growth .",
    back: "Ülke, büyük refah ve ekonomik büyüme dönemi yaşıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "refah",
    quest: "prosperity",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He wore a protective helmet while riding his motorcycle .",
    back: "Motosiklet sürerken koruyucu kask taktı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "koruyucu",
    quest: "protective",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Turkey is a country divided into 81 provinces .",
    back: "Türkiye, 81 ile bölünmüş bir ülkedir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "il", // "Vilayet" is an older term for province
    quest: "province",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The contract includes provisions for termination in case of breach .",
    back: "Sözleşme, fesih durumunda fesih hükümlerini içerir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "hüküm", // "Karşılık" can mean counterpart, but "hüküm" is a more general term for provision
    quest: "provision",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "His words were intended to provoke a reaction from the crowd .",
    back: "Sözleri kalabalıktan bir tepki çekmeyi amaçlıyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kışkırtmak",
    quest: "provoke",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The doctor checked her pulse to assess her heart rate .",
    back: "Doktor, kalp atış hızını değerlendirmek için nabzını kontrol etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "nabız",
    quest: "pulse",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The farmer used a pump to water his crops .",
    back: "Çiftçi, mahsullerini sulamak için bir pompa kullandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "pompa",
    quest: "pump",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He threw a powerful punch that knocked out his opponent .",
    back: "Rakibini nakavt eden güçlü bir yumruk attı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yumruk",
    quest: "punch",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He embarked on a quest to find the lost treasure .",
    back: "Kayıp hazineyi bulmak için bir arayışa başladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "arayış",
    quest: "quest",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The company did not meet its sales quota this month .",
    back: "Şirket, bu ay satış kotasını karşılayamadı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kota",
    quest: "quota",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He flew into a rage when he heard the bad news .",
    back:
        "Kötü haberi duyduğunda öfkeye kapıldı .", // "Kudurmak" is a bit too strong for "rage" in this context .
    list: "C1",
    answer: "öfke", // A better translation for "rage" here
    quest: "rage",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The police conducted a raid on the suspected hideout .",
    back: "Polis, şüpheli saklanma yerine baskın düzenledi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "baskın",
    quest: "raid",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "Thousands of people rallied in the streets to protest the government's policies .",
    back:
        "Hükümetin politikalarını protesto etmek için binlerce insan sokaklara toplandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "toplanmak",
    quest: "rally",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The university ranking lists the top institutions in the country .",
    back: "Üniversite sıralaması, ülkedeki en iyi kurumları listeler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sıralama",
    quest: "ranking",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The doctor measured the ratio of oxygen to carbon dioxide in the blood .",
    back: "Doktor, kandaki oksijen-karbondi oksit oranını ölçtü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "oran",
    quest: "ratio",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The sun's rays shone brightly through the window .",
    back: "Güneşin ışınları pencereden içeriye parlak bir şekilde vurdu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ışın",
    quest: "ray",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He was readily available to help anyone in need .",
    back: "İhtiyacı olan herkese kolaylıkla yardım etmeye hazırdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kolaylıkla",
    quest: "readily",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The sudden realization of his mistake filled him with regret .",
    back: "Hatasının ani kavraması onu pişmanlıkla doldurdu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kavrama",
    quest: "realization",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The kingdom is ruled by a wise and just king .",
    back: "Krallık, adil ve bilge bir kral tarafından yönetiliyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "krallık",
    quest: "realm",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Please sit at the back of the bus .",
    back: "Lütfen otobüsün arkasına oturun .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "arka",
    quest: "rear",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "They used logical reasoning to solve the puzzle .",
    back: "Bulmacayı çözmek için mantıklı muhakeme yeteneği kullandılar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "muhakeme", // This was already correct
    quest: "reasoning",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "Her kind words reassured him that everything would be alright .",
    back:
        "Nazik sözleri, her şeyin yoluna gireceğine dair onu güvence altına aldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "güvence vermek",
    quest: "reassure",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The colonists rebelled against the tyranny of the British crown .",
    back: "Sömürgeciler, İngiliz tacının zulmüne ayaklandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ayaklanmak",
    quest: "rebel",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The country is still recovering from the devastation of the recent rebellion .",
    back:
        "Ülke hala yakın zamanda yaşanan ayaklanmanın tahribatından kurtulmaya çalışıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ayaklanma",
    quest: "rebellion",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The recipient of the letter was her long-lost friend .",
    back: "Mektup alıcısı, uzun zamandır kayıp olan arkadaşıydı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "alıcı",
    quest: "recipient",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The city is undergoing a major reconstruction project after the earthquake .",
    back:
        "Şehir, depremden sonra büyük bir yeniden yapılanma projesi geçirmektedir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yeniden yapılanma",
    quest: "reconstruction",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "There may be a need to recount the votes if the election results are very close .",
    back:
        "Seçim sonuçları çok yakın ise, oyların yeniden sayılması gerekebilir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yeniden saymak",
    quest: "recount",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He stared into the lake, lost in reflection .",
    back:
        "Göle baktı, düşüncelere dalmıştı .", // "Yansıma" can be a bit more abstract here .
    list: "C1",
    answer: "düşünce", // A better translation for "reflection" in this context
    quest: "reflection",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Many refugees fled the war-torn country in search of safety .",
    back:
        "Birçok mülteci, güvenlik arayışı içinde savaştan zarar görmüş ülkeden kaçtı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sığınak",
    quest: "refuge",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He was met with a refusal when he asked for a raise .",
    back: "Zam istediğinde reddetme ile karşılaşıldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "reddetme",
    quest: "refusal",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "Despite the challenges, they were determined to regain control of their lives .",
    back: "Zorluklara rağmen, hayatlarını geri kazanmaya kararlıydılar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "geri kazanmak",
    quest: "regain",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Regardless of the weather, they will go on their camping trip .",
    back: "Havaya aldırmadan, kamp gezisine çıkacaklar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "aldırışsız",
    quest: "regardless",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The company is subject to a number of regulatory requirements .",
    back: "Şirket, bir dizi düzenleyici gerekliliğe tabidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "düzenleyici",
    quest: 'regulatory',
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Queen Elizabeth II's reign lasted for over 70 years .",
    back: "II . Elizabeth Kraliçesi'nin saltanatı 70 yıldan fazla sürdü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "saltanat",
    quest: "reign",
  ),
  // Existing entries . . .

  Words(
    front:
        "He felt a deep sense of rejection after being passed over for the promotion .",
    back: "Terfi için geçildikten sonra derin bir reddetme duygusu hissetti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "reddetme",
    quest: "rejection",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The relevance of this study to current events is undeniable .",
    back: "Bu çalışmanın güncel olaylarla ilgisi inkar edilemez .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ilgi",
    quest: "relevance",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The company is known for its reliability and excellent customer service .",
    back: "Şirket, güvenilirliği ve mükemmel müşteri hizmeti ile tanınır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "güvenilirlik",
    quest: "reliability",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He was reluctant to join the project, but eventually agreed .",
    back: "Projeye katılmaya gönülsüzdü, ancak sonunda kabul etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "gönülsüz",
    quest: "reluctant",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "After eating half the pizza, there was a large remainder left .",
    back:
        "Pizzanın yarısını yedikten sonra geriye kalan büyük bir parça kaldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kalan", // "Geri kalan" is also acceptable
    quest: "remainder",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The archaeologists discovered the remains of an ancient city .",
    back: "Arkeologlar, antik bir şehrin kalıntılarını keşfettiler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kalıntılar",
    quest: "remains",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Exercise is a good remedy for stress and anxiety .",
    back: "Egzersiz, stres ve kaygı için iyi bir çaredir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "çare",
    quest: "remedy",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She set a reminder on her phone to call her mother .",
    back: "Annesini araması için telefonuna bir hatırlatma ayarladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hatırlatma",
    quest: "reminder",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The old building is scheduled for removal next month .",
    back: "Eski bina, önümüzdeki ay kaldırılması planlanıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sökme",
    quest: "removal",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The artist used charcoal to render a portrait of the old man .",
    back: "Sanatçı, yaşlı adamın portresini resmetmek için kömür kullandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "resmetmek",
    quest: "render",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "They decided to renew their wedding vows on their 25th anniversary .",
    back:
        "25 . yıldönümlerinde evlilik yeminlerini yenilemeye karar verdiler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yenilemek",
    quest: "renew",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The city is famous for its renowned museums and art galleries .",
    back: "Şehir, ünlü müzeleri ve sanat galerileri ile ünlüdür .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ünlü",
    quest: "renowned",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We are looking for a rental car for our trip .",
    back: "Gezimiz için kiralık bir araba arıyoruz .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kiralık",
    quest: "rental",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The faulty product was replaced with a new one under warranty .",
    back: "Hatalı ürün, garanti kapsamında yenisiyle değiştirildi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yenisiyle değiştirme",
    quest: "replacement",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Reportedly, the president is going to resign next week .",
    back: "Söylentilere göre, cumhurbaşkanı önümüzdeki hafta istifa edecek .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "söylentilere göre",
    quest: "reportedly",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The painting is a beautiful representation of the Italian countryside .",
    back: "Resim, İtalyan kırsalının güzel bir temsilidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "temsil",
    quest: "representation",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Scientists are trying to reproduce the experiment .",
    back: "Bilim adamları deneyi yeniden üretmeye çalışıyorlar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yeniden üretmek",
    quest: "reproduce",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Asexual reproduction is a common method for some plants .",
    back: "Bazı bitkiler için eşeysiz çoğalma yaygın bir yöntemdir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "çoğalma", // "Üreme" can also be used here .
    quest: "reproduction",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "France is a republic with a democratically elected president .",
    back:
        "Fransa, demokratik olarak seçilmiş bir cumhurbaşkanı olan bir cumhuriyettir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "cumhuriyet",
    quest: "republic",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The two buildings closely resemble each other in design .",
    back: "İki bina tasarım olarak birbirine çok benziyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "benzemek",
    quest: "resemble",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He has resided in France for the past 20 years .",
    back: "Son 20 yıldır Fransa'da ikamet ediyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ikamet etmek",
    quest: "reside",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "They are looking to buy a residence in a quiet neighborhood .",
    back:
        "Sakin bir mahallede oturmak için bir mesken satın almak istiyorlar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "mesken",
    quest: "residence",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "This area is a residential neighborhood with mostly single-family homes .",
    back:
        "Bu alan çoğunlukla müstakil evlerin bulunduğu oturmaya elverişli bir mahalleden oluşuyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "oturmaya elverişli",
    quest: "residential",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "After cleaning the pan, there was a greasy residue left over .",
    back: "Tavayı temizledikten sonra yağlı bir tortu kaldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tortu",
    quest: "residue",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He submitted his resignation from the company after accepting a new position .",
    back: "Yeni bir görevi kabul ettikten sonra şirketten istifa etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "istifa",
    quest: "resignation",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "They each presented their ideas, stating their respective positions on the issue .",
    back:
        "Her biri kendi fikirlerini sundu ve konuyla ilgili kendi şahsi konumlarını belirtti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "şahsi",
    quest: "respective",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "John won first place, Mary came in second, and David came in third, respectively .",
    back: "John birinci oldu, Mary ikinci, David ise sırasıyla üçüncü oldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sırasıyla",
    quest: "respectively",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He showed great restraint in not arguing back when he was insulted .",
    back:
        "Hakaret edildiğinde karşılık vermeyerek büyük bir kısıtlama gösterdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kısıtlama",
    quest: "restraint",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The meeting was interrupted, but we will resume it later this afternoon .",
    back: "Toplantı yarıda kesildi, ancak öğleden sonra devam edeceğiz .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sürdürmek",
    quest: "resume",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The enemy forces were forced to retreat after suffering heavy losses .",
    back:
        "Düşman güçleri, ağır kayıplar verdikten sonra geri çekilmek zorunda kaldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "geri çekilmek",
    quest: "retreat",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He went back to his room to retrieve his forgotten phone .",
    back: "Unutmuş olduğu telefonunu almak için odasına geri döndü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "geri almak",
    quest: "retrieve",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The discovery of a new planet was a scientific revelation .",
    back: "Yeni bir gezegenin keşfi bilimsel bir vahiy niteliğindeydi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "vahiy",
    quest: "revelation",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He vowed to get revenge on those who had wronged him .",
    back: "Kendisine haksızlık edenlerden intikam almak için yemin etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "intikam almak",
    quest: "revenge",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The opposite of hot is cold, and the reverse of true is false .",
    back: "Sıcağın karşıtı soğuktur, doğrunun tersi ise yanlıştır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ters",
    quest: "reverse",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "There are signs of a revival in the city's cultural scene .",
    back: "Şehrin kültürel hayatında bir canlanma emareleri var .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "canlanma",
    quest: "revival",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The old painting was carefully restored to revive its former beauty .",
    back:
        "Eski resim, eski güzelliğini canlandırmak için dikkatlice restore edildi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "canlandırmak",
    quest: "revive",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The politician's speech was full of empty rhetoric and made no real promises .",
    back:
        "Politikacının konuşması boş güzel konuşmadan ibaret olup hiçbir gerçek vaatte bulunmadı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "güzel konuşma", // "Retorik" can be used here too, but it's less common .
    quest: "rhetoric",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The soldier aimed his rifle at the target .",
    back: "Asker tüfeğini hedefe doğrulttu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tüfek",
    quest: "rifle",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The angry protesters started a riot in the streets .",
    back: "Öfkeli göstericiler sokaklarda isyan çıkardı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "isyan etmek",
    quest: "riot",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He ripped a piece of paper out of his notebook .",
    back:
        "Defterinden bir sayfa kopardı .", // "Sökmek" can be used for tearing something off, but not necessarily ripping .
    list: "C1",
    answer: "koparmak", // A better translation for "rip" in this context
    quest: "rip",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The bridge is built with robust materials to withstand heavy traffic .",
    back:
        "Köprü, yoğun trafiğe dayanacak şekilde güçlü malzemelerden inşa edilmiştir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "güçlü",
    quest: "robust",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The music made her want to rock out all night .",
    back: "Müzik onu bütün gece sallanmak isteğine getirdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sallanmak",
    quest: "rock",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He used a metal rod to pry open the window .",
    back: "Pencereyi zorlamak için metal bir çubuk kullandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "çubuk",
    quest: "rod",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The Earth rotates on its axis once every 24 hours .",
    back: "Dünya kendi ekseni etrafında 24 saatte bir döner .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dönmek",
    quest: "rotate",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The team practiced their routine for the dance competition, focusing on precise rotations .",
    back:
        "Takım, dans yarışması için rutini denedi ve hassas rotasyonlara odaklandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "rotasyon",
    quest: "rotation",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The judge drew a blue line with a ruler to mark the boundary .",
    back: "Hakim, sınırı işaretlemek için cetvelle mavi bir çizgi çekti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "cetvelle çizmek",
    quest: "ruling",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "There is a rumour going around that the company is going bankrupt .",
    back: "Şirketin iflas edeceğine dair bir söylenti ortalıkta dolaşıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "söylenti",
    quest: "rumour",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He was sacked from his job for poor performance .",
    back: "Düşük performans nedeniyle işinden kovuldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "kovulmak", // "Çuvala koymak" is not a common expression for getting fired .
    quest: "sack",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Many cultures consider cows to be sacred animals .",
    back: "Birçok kültür inekleri kutsal hayvanlar olarak görür .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kutsal",
    quest: "sacred",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He did it for the sake of his family .",
    back: "Bunun için ailesinin hatırına yaptı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hatır",
    quest: "sake",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The country is facing economic sanctions due to its human rights violations .",
    back:
        "Ülke, insan hakları ihlalleri nedeniyle yaptırımlarla karşı karşıyadır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yaptırım",
    quest: "sanction",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Can you say that again?",
    back: "Bunu tekrar söyleyebilir misin?",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "söylemek",
    quest: "say",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The toys were scattered all over the floor .",
    back: "Oyuncaklar yere dağınık bir şekilde saçılmıştı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dağınık",
    quest: "scattered",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He was skeptical of the claims made by the salesperson .",
    back: "Satış görevlisinin yaptığı iddialara şüpheyle yaklaştı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kuşkucu",
    quest: "sceptical",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The project falls outside the scope of my current responsibilities .",
    back: "Proje şu anki sorumluluk alanımın dışında kalıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "faaliyet alanı",
    quest: "scope",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He carefully screwed the two pieces of wood together .",
    back: "İki tahta parçasını dikkatlice vidaladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "vidalamak",
    quest: "screw",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The company's financial records are under close scrutiny by the government .",
    back:
        "Şirketin mali kayıtları hükümet tarafından sıkı inceleme altındadır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "inceleme",
    quest: "scrutiny",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The envelope was sealed with a red wax stamp .",
    back: "Zarf, kırmızı bir mum mührü ile mühürlenmişti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "mühürlemek",
    quest: "seal",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The situation seemed calm on the surface, but tensions were high beneath it .",
    back: "Görünürde durum sakince görünse de, altında gerginlik yüksekti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "görünürde",
    quest: "seemingly",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The market can be segmented into different groups based on customer demographics .",
    back:
        "Pazar, müşteri demografik özelliklerine göre farklı segmentlere ayrılabilir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bölmek",
    quest: "segment",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The police seized the drugs that were found in the car .",
    back: "Polis, arabada bulunan uyuşturucuları ele geçirdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "el koymak",
    quest: "seize",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She seldom visits her hometown anymore .",
    back: "Artık memleketine nadiren gidiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "nadiren",
    quest: "seldom",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The university has a selective admissions process .",
    back: "Üniversitenin seçici bir kabul süreci vardır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "seçici",
    quest: "selective",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The sight of blood caused a wave of nausea and sensation .",
    back: "Kan görüntüsü bir mide bulantısı ve his dalgasına neden oldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "his", // "Duyu" can also be used here .
    quest: "sensation",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "People with allergies often have a heightened sensitivity to dust and pollen .",
    back:
        "Alerjisi olan kişiler genellikle toz ve polene karşı yüksek hassasiyete sahiptir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hassasiyet",
    quest: "sensitivity",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The public sentiment was overwhelmingly in favor of the new law .",
    back: "Kamuoyu yeni yasadan yana ezici bir çoğunlukla duygu besliyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "düşünce",
    quest: "sentiment",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The separation of powers is a fundamental principle of democracy .",
    back: "Yetkilerin ayrılması, demokrasinin temel ilkelerinden biridir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ayırma",
    quest: "separation",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He is a big fan of crime serial dramas .",
    back: "O, polisiye dizi filmlerinin büyük hayranıdır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "seri",
    quest: "serial",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The peace talks aimed to find a lasting settlement between the warring parties .",
    back:
        "Barış görüşmeleri, savaşan taraflar arasında kalıcı bir yerleşim bulmayı amaçlıyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yerleşim",
    quest: "settlement",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "How long does it take to set up the new printer?",
    back: "Yeni yazıcıyı kurmak ne kadar sürer?",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "kurmak", // "Set-up" can be translated as "kurmak" or "hazırlamak" depending on the context .
    quest: "set-up",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He is a major shareholder in the company .",
    back: "Şirketin büyük hissedarlarından biridir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hissedar",
    quest: "shareholder",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The vase fell from the table and shattered into pieces .",
    back: "Vazo masadan düşüp paramparça oldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kırmak",
    quest: "shatter",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He shed a tear as he said goodbye to his old friend .",
    back: "Eski dostuna veda ederken bir damla gözyaşı döktü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dökmek",
    quest: "shed",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She possessed sheer determination to succeed .",
    back: "Başarılı olmak için düpedüz bir kararlılığa sahipti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "düpedüz",
    quest: "sheer",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The cost of shipping the furniture overseas was very high .",
    back: "Mobilyaların yurt dışına gönderim masrafı çok yüksekti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "nakliye",
    quest: "shipping",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "They are going to shoot a movie on location in Italy next summer .",
    back: "Gelecek yaz İtalya'da bir film çekimi yapacaklar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "film çekmek",
    quest: "shoot",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The sweater shrunk in the wash, so I can't wear it anymore .",
    back: "Kazak yıkandığında küçüldü, bu yüzden artık giyemiyorum .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "küçültmek",
    quest: "shrink",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He shrugged his shoulders and said he didn't know .",
    back: "Omuzlarını silkti ve bilmediğini söyledi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "omuz silkmek",
    quest: "shrug",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She let out a sigh of relief when she finished the exam .",
    back: "Sınayı bitirdiğinde rahatlama iç çekti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "iç çekme",
    quest: "sigh",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The flight simulator is designed to simulate the experience of flying a real airplane .",
    back:
        "Uçuş simülatörü, gerçek bir uçak kullanma deneyimini simüle etmek için tasarlanmıştır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "taklidini yapmak",
    quest: "simulate",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The fire drill was a simulation of a real fire emergency .",
    back: "Yangın tatbikatı, gerçek bir yangın acil durumu simülasyonuydu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "simülasyon",
    quest: "simulation",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He translated the text into English simultaneously .",
    back: "Metni aynı anda İngilizceye çevirdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "eş zamanlı",
    quest: "simultaneously",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Lying is a sin according to many religions .",
    back: "Yalan söylemek birçok dine göre günahtır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "günah",
    quest: "sin",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The village is situated in a beautiful valley surrounded by mountains .",
    back: "Köy, dağlarla çevrili güzel bir vadide konumlanmıştır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "konumlanmış",
    quest: "situated",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He made a rough sketch of the building before starting to draw the final plan .",
    back: "Nihai planı çizmeye başlamadan önce binanın taslağını yaptı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "taslağını yapmak",
    quest: "sketch",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We can skip this chapter as it is not relevant to the exam .",
    back: "Sınavla ilgili olmadığı için bu bölümü atlayabiliriz .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "atlamak",
    quest: "skip",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The critics slammed the new movie, calling it a complete disaster .",
    back:
        "Eleştirmenler, yeni filmi yerden yere vurup tam bir felaket olarak nitelendirdiler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "eleştirmek",
    quest: "slam",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He received a slap on the wrist for his minor offense .",
    back: "Küçük suçundan dolayı tokat atar gibi bir ceza aldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tokat",
    quest: "slap",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The company's decision to outsource jobs was met with a slash in its stock price .",
    back:
        "Şirketin işleri dışarıya verme kararı, hisse senedi fiyatında büyük bir düşüşe yol açtı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "düşüş", // "Slash" can be translated as "düşüş" here to convey the idea of a sharp decrease .
    quest: "slash",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Slavery was finally abolished in the 19th century .",
    back: "Kölelik nihayet 19 . yüzyılda kaldırıldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kölelik",
    quest: "slavery",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He inserted a new SIM card into the slot on his phone .",
    back:
        "Telefonuna SIM kartı taktı .", // "Yerleştirmek" can be used for inserting an object into a designated space .
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yerleştirmek",
    quest: "slot",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The angry mob smashed the windows of the store .",
    back: "Öfkeli kalabalık mağazanın vitrinlerini paramparça etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "paramparça etmek",
    quest: "smash",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The twig snapped in half as he stepped on it .",
    back: "Üzerine bastığında dal parçası ikiye kırıldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "kırılmak", // "Snap" can be translated as "kırılmak" in this context .
    quest: "snap",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The eagle soared high above the mountains .",
    back: "Kartal, dağların çok yukarılarında süzüldü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yüksekten uçmak",
    quest: "soar",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The shoe has a rubber sole that provides good traction .",
    back: "Ayakkabının iyi tutuş sağlayan kauçuk tabanı vardır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "taban",
    quest: "sole",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He came to the party solely for the purpose of networking .",
    back: "Sadece network kurmak amacıyla partiye geldi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sadece",
    quest: "solely",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He hired a solicitor to represent him in court .",
    back: "Mahkemede kendisini temsil etmesi için bir avukat tuttu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "avukat",
    quest: "solicitor",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The workers showed solidarity by going on strike together .",
    back: "İşçiler birlikte greve giderek dayanışma gösterdiler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dayanışma",
    quest: "solidarity",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The sound of the music woke him up in the middle of the night .",
    back: "Müzik sesi onu gecenin ortasında uyandırdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ses",
    quest: "sound",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The project spans several years and involves researchers from different countries .",
    back:
        "Proje birkaç yılı kapsıyor ve farklı ülkelerden araştırmacıları içeriyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "kapsamak", // "Span" can be translated as "kapsamak" to convey the idea of covering a period of time or distance .
    quest: "span",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Do you have a spare tire in case of a flat?",
    back: "Lastiğiniz patlarsa yedek lastiğiniz var mı?",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yedek",
    quest: "spare",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "A spark from the campfire ignited the dry leaves .",
    back: "Kamp ateşinden çıkan bir kıvılcım kuru yaprakları tutuşturdu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kıvılcım",
    quest: "spark",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He is a specialized doctor who treats patients with heart problems .",
    back: "O, kalp hastaları tedavisinde uzmanlaşmış bir doktor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "uzmanlaşmış",
    quest: "specialized",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The architect provided detailed specifications for the construction of the new building .",
    back: "Mimar, yeni binanın yapımı için ayrıntılı birer özellikname sundu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "belirti",
    quest: "specification",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The scientists studied a specimen of the rare plant under a microscope .",
    back:
        "Bilimciler, nadir bitkinin bir örneğini mikroskop altında incelediler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "örnek",
    quest: "specimen",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The fireworks display was a spectacular sight to behold .",
    back: "Havai fişek gösterisi görsel bir şölendi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "gösteri", // "Spectacle" can be translated as "gösteri" to convey the idea of a public event .
    quest: "spectacle",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Can you spell the word 'believe' for me?",
    back: " 'İnanmak' kelimesini heceleyebilir misin?",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hecelemek",
    quest: "spell",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The Earth is a sphere, but most maps portray it as flat .",
    back: "Dünya bir küredir, ancak çoğu harita onu düz olarak gösterir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "küre",
    quest: "sphere",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He spun the wheel on the game show and waited to see where it would land .",
    back: " Oyun programında çarkı çevirdi ve nerede duracağını bekledi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "döndürmek",
    quest: "spin",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The doctor examined his spine for any signs of injury .",
    back:
        "Doktor, omurgasını herhangi bir yaralanma belirtisi olup olmadığına baktı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "omurga",
    quest: "spine",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The spotlight was on the actress as she delivered her opening monologue .",
    back:
        "Oyuncunun açılış monologunu sunduğu sırada spot ışığı onun üzerindeydi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "spot ışığı",
    quest: "spotlight",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He has been married to his spouse for over 20 years .",
    back: "Eşiyle 20 yılı aşkın süredir evli .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "eş",
    quest: "spouse",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The secret agent was a double spy working for both sides .",
    back: "Gizli ajan, her iki taraf için de çalışan bir çifte casustu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "casus",
    quest: "spy",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The police squad surrounded the building and arrested the suspects .",
    back: "Polis ekibi binayı çevirdi ve şüphelileri tutukladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ekip",
    quest: "squad",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He tried to squeeze through the narrow gap, but he got stuck .",
    back: "Dar aralıktan sıvışmaya çalıştı ama sıkıştı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sıkışmak",
    quest: "squeeze",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The country's political stability is essential for economic growth .",
    back: "Ülkenin siyasi kararlılığı ekonomik büyüme için gereklidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kararlılık",
    quest: "stability",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The medicine helped to stabilize his blood pressure .",
    back: "İlaç, kan basıncını dengeleştirmeye yardımcı oldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dengeleştirmek",
    quest: "stabilize",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He drove a stake into the ground to secure the tent .",
    back: "Çadırı sabitlemek için yere kazık çaktı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kazık",
    quest: "stake",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The crowd was standing in silence as the national anthem played .",
    back: "Milli marş çalınırken kalabalık ayakta sessizce duruyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ayakta durmak",
    quest: "standing",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The contrast between the rich and the poor was stark .",
    back: "Zenginlerle fakirler arasındaki tezat çok belirgindi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "belirgin", // "Stark" can be translated as "belirgin" to convey the idea of something very noticeable .
    quest: "stark",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The captain steered the ship away from the rocks .",
    back: "Kaptan, gemiyi kayalıklardan uzaklaştırdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yönlendirmek",
    quest: "steer",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Knowing the stem of a word can help you understand its meaning .",
    back:
        " Bir kelimenin kökünü bilmek, anlamını anlamanıza yardımcı olabilir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "kök,çıkmak", // "Stem" can be translated as "kökenlenmek" to convey the idea of origin .
    quest: "stem",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "A loud noise was the stimulus that startled the cat .",
    back: "Yüksek ses, kediyi ürküten uyaran oldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "uyarıcı",
    quest: "stimulus",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She stirred the soup to make sure it wasn't burning .",
    back: "Yanıp yanmadığından emin olmak için çorbayı karıştırdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "karıştırmak",
    quest: "stir",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "This warehouse is used for the storage of electronic equipment .",
    back: "Bu depo, elektronik eşyaların depolanması için kullanılır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "depolama", // "Storage" can be translated as "depolama" to convey the action of storing things .
    quest: "storage",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He gave her straightforward instructions that were easy to understand .",
    back: "Ona anlaşılması kolay, basit talimatlar verdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "doğrudan", // "Straightforward" can be translated as "doğrudan" to convey the idea of being clear and direct .
    quest: "straightforward",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He strained his back while lifting the heavy box .",
    back: "Ağır kutuyu kaldırırken sırtını zorladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "zorlamak",
    quest: "strain",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She wore a long strand of pearls around her neck .",
    back: "Boynunda uzun bir inci dizisi taktı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dizi",
    quest: "strand",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The advertisement featured a striking image of a beautiful waterfall .",
    back: "Reklamda, güzel bir şelalenin çarpıcı bir görüntüsü vardı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "çarpıcı",
    quest: "striking",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He stripped the paint off the old furniture before repainting it .",
    back: "Eski mobilyaların boyasını yeniden boyamadan önce soydu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "soymak",
    quest: "strip",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She always strives to do her best in everything she does .",
    back:
        "Yaptığı her şeyde her zaman elinden gelenin en iyisini yapmaya çalışır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "uğraşmak",
    quest: "strive",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The building had a strong structural foundation .",
    back: "Binanın sağlam bir yapısal temeli vardı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yapısal",
    quest: "structural",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He stumbled over his words and forgot what he was going to say .",
    back: "Sözlerinin üzerinde sendeledi ve ne söyleyeceğini unuttu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sendelemek",
    quest: "stumble",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The news of his death stunned the entire community .",
    back: "Ölüm haberi tüm toplumu şaşkına çevirdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "şaşkına çevirmek",
    quest: "stun",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The deadline for the essay submission is next Friday .",
    back: "Makalenin teslim tarihi önümüzdeki cuma günü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "teslim",
    quest: "submission",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He is a subscriber to a popular online magazine .",
    back: "Popüler bir online derginin abonesidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "abone",
    quest: "subscriber",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Many people get a monthly subscription to a streaming service .",
    back: "Birçok insan, aylık olarak bir streaming hizmetine abonelik alır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "abonelik",
    quest: "subscription",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The government provides subsidies to farmers to help them with their crops .",
    back:
        "Hükümet, çiftçilere mahsullerine yardımcı olmak için sübvansiyon sağlar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sübvansiyon",
    quest: "subsidy",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He made a substantial contribution to the project's success .",
    back: "Projenin başarısına önemli bir katkıda bulundu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "önemli",
    quest: "substantial",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Her income has substantially increased since she got a new job .",
    back: "Yeni bir iş bulduğundan beri geliri önemli miktarda arttı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "önemli ölçüde",
    quest: "substantially",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The teacher asked the students to find a substitute for the missing ingredient in the recipe .",
    back:
        "Öğretmen, öğrencilerden tarifteki eksik malzemenin yerine geçecek bir şey bulmalarını istedi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yerine geçmek",
    quest: "substitute",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The substitution of butter with olive oil made the cake healthier .",
    back:
        "Tereyağ yerine zeytinyağı kullanılması pastayı daha sağlıklı hale getirdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yerine koyma",
    quest: "substitution",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The difference in quality between the two products was subtle but noticeable .",
    back: "İki ürün arasındaki kalite farkı güç algılanan ama belirgindi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "güç algılanan",
    quest: "subtle",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "They live in a quiet suburban neighborhood with friendly people .",
    back:
        "Sessiz ve insanların birbirini tanıdığı bir banliyö mahallesinde yaşıyorlar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "banliyö",
    quest: "suburban",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The king's succession was peaceful, and his son took the throne without any conflict .",
    back:
        "Kralın ardıllığı barışçıl oldu ve oğlu herhangi bir çatışma yaşamadan tahta çıktı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ardıllık",
    quest: "succession",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He won three successive games of chess, proving his skills .",
    back: "Zeka yeteneğini kanıtlayarak üç ardışık satranç oyunu kazandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ardışık",
    quest: "successive",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The king's successor is his eldest son, who is now the crown prince .",
    back: "Kralın varisi, şu anda veliaht prens olan en büyük oğludur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "varis",
    quest: "successor",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He is planning to sue the company for wrongful termination of his contract .",
    back:
        "Haksız yere işten çıkarılması nedeniyle şirketi dava açmayı planlıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dava açmak",
    quest: "sue",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Suicide is a serious issue that needs to be addressed by society .",
    back:
        "İntihar, toplum tarafından ele alınması gereken ciddi bir sorundur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "intihar",
    quest: "Suicide",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He rented a luxurious suite at the hotel for his honeymoon .",
    back: "Balayı için otelden lüks bir suit kiraladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "suit",
    quest: "suite",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The world leaders met at a summit to discuss global issues .",
    back:
        "Dünya liderleri, küresel sorunları tartışmak için bir zirvede bir araya geldi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "zirve",
    quest: "summit",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The meal was absolutely superb! We enjoyed every bite .",
    back: "Yemek kesinlikle harikuladeydi! Her lokmasının tadını çıkardık .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "harikulade",
    quest: "superb",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He felt superior to his colleagues and often looked down on them .",
    back:
        "Kendisini meslektaşlarından üstün görüyordu ve onlara sık sık tepeden bakıyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "üstün",
    quest: "superior",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The teacher provided close supervision during the students' exams .",
    back: "Öğretmen, öğrencilerin sınavları sırasında yakın gözetim sağladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "gözetim",
    quest: "supervision",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The supervisor is responsible for ensuring that the employees are working efficiently .",
    back:
        "Denetmen, çalışanların verimli bir şekilde çalışmasını sağlamaktan sorumludur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "denetmen",
    quest: "supervisor",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He takes a daily vitamin supplement to ensure he is getting all the nutrients he needs .",
    back:
        "İhtiyacı olan tüm besin maddelerini aldığından emin olmak için günlük vitamin takviyesi alıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "takviye",
    quest: "supplement",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "She has a very supportive family who always encourages her to follow her dreams .",
    back:
        "Hayallerinin peşinden gitmesi için onu her zaman destekleyen çok destekleyici bir ailesi var .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "destekleyici",
    quest: "supportive",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The government is trying to suppress the spread of misinformation online .",
    back:
        "Hükümet, çevrimiçi yanlış bilginin yayılmasını bastırmaya çalışıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bastırmak",
    quest: "suppress",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The Supreme Court is the highest court in the land .",
    back: "Yargıtay, ülkenin en yüksek mahkemesidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yargıtay",
    quest: "Supreme",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The price of oil surged after the outbreak of the war .",
    back: "Savaşın patlak vermesinden sonra petrol fiyatları fırladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "fırlamak",
    quest: "surge",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He needed surgery to remove his appendix .",
    back: "Apanditini almak için ameliyata ihtiyacı vardı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ameliyat",
    quest: "surgical",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The company has a surplus of inventory that they are trying to sell .",
    back: "Şirket, satmaya çalıştıkları fazla stok fazlasına sahiptir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "fazla",
    quest: "surplus",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The enemy soldiers eventually surrendered after running out of ammunition .",
    back:
        "Düşman askerleri cephaneleri bittikten sonra sonunda teslim oldular .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "teslim olmak",
    quest: "surrender",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The house is under constant surveillance by security cameras .",
    back: "Ev, güvenlik kameraları tarafından sürekli gözetleme altındadır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "gözetleme",
    quest: "surveillance",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The athlete was given a two-year suspension from competition for doping .",
    back: "Sporcu, doping nedeniyle iki yıllık yarışmaya ara verildi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "askıya alma",
    quest: "suspension",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "There was a suspicion that he was cheating on the exam .",
    back: "Sınavda kopya çektiğine dair bir kuşku vardı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kuşku",
    quest: "suspicion",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The man looked suspicious as he lurked around the corner .",
    back: "Adam köşede pusu verirken şüpheli görünüyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "şüpheli",
    quest: "suspicious",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He was able to sustain himself on a diet of fruits and vegetables .",
    back: "Kendini meyve ve sebze ağırlıklı bir diyetle idame ettirebildi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "idame ettirmek",
    quest: "sustain",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The children were swinging on the swings in the playground .",
    back: "Çocuklar oyun parkındaki salıncakta sallanıyorlardı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sallanmak",
    quest: "swing",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The knight fought bravely with his sword against the dragon .",
    back: "Şövalye, ejderhaya karşı kılıcıyla cesurca savaştı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kılıç",
    quest: "sword",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The scientist's theory was a brilliant synthesis of different ideas .",
    back: "Bilimcinin teorisi, farklı fikirlerin parlak bir senteziydi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sentez",
    quest: "synthesis",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The government needs to tackle the issue of climate change .",
    back: "Hükümetin iklim değişikliği sorununu ele alması gerekiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ele almak",
    quest: "tackle",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Every taxpayer has a responsibility to pay their taxes .",
    back: "Her vergi verenin vergilerini ödeme sorumluluğu vardır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "vergi veren",
    quest: "taxpayer",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He was tempted to cheat on the test, but he knew it was wrong .",
    back:
        "Kopya çekmek için cazip geldi, ancak bunun yanlış olduğunu biliyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kışkırtmak",
    quest: "tempt",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "She is a tenant in the apartment building and pays rent to the landlord .",
    back: "Apartman dairesinde kiracıdır ve ev sahibine kira öder .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kiracı",
    quest: "tenant",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The company submitted a tender for the construction project .",
    back: "Şirket, inşaat projesi için bir ihale sundu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ihale",
    quest: "tender",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "In most universities, professors have tenure after a probationary period .",
    back:
        "Çoğu üniversitede, profesörler deneme süresinden sonra kadrolu hale gelir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kadrolu olmak",
    quest: "tenure",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The company was forced to terminate his contract due to budget cuts .",
    back:
        "Şirket, bütçe kesintileri nedeniyle sözleşmesini feshetmek zorunda kaldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "feshetmek",
    quest: "terminate",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The soldiers had to fight through difficult terrain to reach their objective .",
    back:
        "Askerler hedeflerine ulaşmak için zorlu araziden savaşarak geçmek zorunda kaldılar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "arazi",
    quest: "terrain",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We had a terrific time at the party! It was a lot of fun .",
    back: "Partilde müthiş vakit geçirdik! Çok eğlenceliydi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "müthiş",
    quest: "terrific",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The witness will testify in court about what they saw at the crime scene .",
    back: "Tanık, mahkemede olay yerinde gördükleri hakkında tanıklık edecek .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tanıklık etmek",
    quest: "testify",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The police are relying on eyewitness testimony to solve the case .",
    back: "Polis, davayı çözmek için görgü tanığı ifadesine güveniyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ifade",
    quest: "testimony",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "I love the soft texture of this cashmere sweater .",
    back: "Bu kaşmir kazağın yumuşak dokusunu seviyorum .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "doku",
    quest: "texture",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "Thankfully, the fire alarm went off in time and everyone was able to evacuate safely .",
    back:
        "Neyse ki, yangın alarmı zamanında devreye girdi ve herkes güvenli bir şekilde tahliye edilebildi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "Neyse ki",
    quest: "thankfully",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The actor gave a very theatrical performance that was full of overdramatic gestures .",
    back:
        "Oyuncu, abartılı jestlerle dolu çok teatral bir performans sergiledi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "abartılı",
    quest: "theatrical",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "His theory is based on theoretical concepts that have not been proven yet .",
    back: "Teorisi, henüz kanıtlanmamış teorik kavramlara dayanıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "teorik",
    quest: "theoretical",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We will discuss the details of the project thereafter .",
    back: "Projenin detaylarını ondan sonra tartışacağız .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ondan sonra",
    quest: "thereafter",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He achieved his goals by working hard and diligently . Thereby, he proved that anything is possible with hard work .",
    back:
        "Hedeflerine sıkı çalışarak ve özenle çalışarak ulaştı . Böylelikle, sıkı çalışma ile her şeyin mümkün olduğunu kanıtladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "böylelikle",
    quest: "thereby",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "She gave a thoughtful gift that showed she really cared about her friend .",
    back:
        "Düşünceli bir hediye verdi ve bu da arkadaşını gerçekten önemsediğini gösterdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "düşünceli",
    quest: "thoughtful",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The movie was a thought-provoking exploration of social issues .",
    back:
        "Film, sosyal sorunları düşündürücü bir şekilde ele alan bir incelemeydi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "düşündürücü",
    quest: "thought-provoking",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She used a strong thread to sew the button back on her shirt .",
    back: "Gomleğindeki düğmeyi tekrar dikmek için sağlam bir iplik kullandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "iplik",
    quest: "thread",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "We are on the threshold of a new era of technological advancements .",
    back: "Teknolojik gelişmelerin yeni bir çağının eşiğindeyiz .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "eşik",
    quest: "threshold",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "She was thrilled to win the competition and finally achieve her dream .",
    back: "Yarışmayı kazanıp sonunda hayaline ulaştığı için heyecanlanmıştı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "heyecanlanmış",
    quest: "thrilled",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Plants thrive in fertile soil with plenty of sunlight and water .",
    back: "Bitkiler, bereketli toprakta, bol güneş ışığı ve su ile gelişir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "gelişmek",
    quest: "thrive",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "He tightened his grip on the rope to prevent himself from falling .",
    back: "Düşmeyi önlemek için ipteki tutuşunu sıkılaştırdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sıkılaştırmak",
    quest: "tighten",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The house is built from a combination of brick and timber .",
    back: "Ev, tuğla ve kereste kombinasyonundan inşa edilmiştir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kereste",
    quest: "timber",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "It was a timely warning that helped us avoid a major disaster .",
    back:
        "Büyük bir felaketi önlememize yardımcı olan zamanında yapılan bir uyarıydı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "zamanında yapılan",
    quest: "timely",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Smoking tobacco can lead to serious health problems .",
    back: "Tütün içmek ciddi sağlık sorunlarına yol açabilir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tütün",
    quest: "tobacco",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He showed a great deal of tolerance for her mistakes .",
    back: "Hatalarına karşı büyük bir hoşgörü gösterdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hoşgörü",
    quest: "tolerance",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Children need to learn to tolerate frustration .",
    back: "Çocukların hayal kırıklığına tahammül etmeyi öğrenmeleri gerekir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tahammül etmek",
    quest: "tolerate",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "You have to pay a toll to cross the bridge .",
    back: "Köprüyü geçmek için çan çalmak zorundasınız .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: 'Geçit ücreti',
    quest: 'toll',
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The mountain peak was shrouded in mist .",
    back: "Dağın tepesi sisle örtülüydü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tepe",
    quest: "top",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The prisoners were tortured by their captors .",
    back: "Tutuklular, gardiyanları tarafından işkence gördü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "işkence",
    quest: "torture",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "They tossed a coin to decide who would go first .",
    back: "Kimin önce gideceğine karar vermek için yazı tura attılar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "atmak",
    quest: "toss",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The total cost of the repairs came to \$1000 .",
    back: "Tamiratın toplam maliyeti 1000 dolara ulaştı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "toplam",
    quest: "total",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Exposure to toxic chemicals can cause serious health problems .",
    back:
        "Zehirli kimyasallara maruz kalmak ciddi sağlık sorunlarına neden olabilir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "zehirli",
    quest: "toxic",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The police are trying to trace the suspect's movements .",
    back: "Polis, şüphelinin hareketlerini iz sürmek çalışıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "iz sürmek",
    quest: "trace",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Nike is a well-known trademark for athletic shoes .",
    back: "Nike, spor ayakkabıları için tanınmış bir markadır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "marka",
    quest: "trademark",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The hikers followed a well-marked trail through the forest .",
    back: "Yürüyüşçüler, orman boyunca iyi işaretlenmiş bir iz takip ettiler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "iz",
    quest: "trail",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "I watched the trailer for the new movie and it looks really good .",
    back: "Yeni filmin fragmanını izledim ve gerçekten çok iyi görünüyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "fragman",
    quest: "trailer",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The bank transaction was successful and the money has been transferred .",
    back: "Banka işlemi başarılı oldu ve para transfer edildi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "işlem",
    quest: "transaction",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The student requested a transcript of their grades from the university .",
    back: "Öğrenci, üniversiteden notlarının bir transkriptini talep etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "transkript",
    quest: "transcript",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The caterpillar undergoes a remarkable transformation into a butterfly .",
    back: "Tırtıl, kelebeğe dönüşen dikkat çekici bir dönüşüm geçirir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dönüşüm",
    quest: "transformation",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The cargo ship is transporting goods through the Panama Canal .",
    back: "Kargo gemisi, Panama Kanalı'ndan transit geçiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "transit, geçiş",
    quest: "transit",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The car wouldn't start because there was a problem with the transmission .",
    back: "Araba vites sorunu nedeniyle çalışmadı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "vites",
    quest: "transmission",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "There is a need for more transparency in government spending .",
    back: "Devlet harcamalarında daha fazla şeffaflık olması gerekiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "şeffaflık",
    quest: "transparency",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "I can see through the transparent window .",
    back: "Saydam pencereden görebiliyorum .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "saydam",
    quest: "transparent",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The soldier suffered a severe trauma from the war .",
    back: "Asker, savaştan kaynaklanan ciddi bir travma yaşadı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "travma",
    quest: "trauma",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The two countries signed a peace treaty to end the conflict .",
    back:
        "İki ülke, çatışmayı sona erdirmek için bir barış antlaşması imzaladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "antlaşma",
    quest: "treaty",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He made a tremendous effort to overcome the challenges he faced .",
    back:
        "Karşılaştığı zorlukların üstesinden gelmek için muazzam bir çaba gösterdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "muazzam",
    quest: "tremendous",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The case was brought before a tribunal for international crimes .",
    back: "Dava, uluslararası suçlar için bir mahkemeye getirildi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "mahkeme",
    quest: "tribunal",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The ancient city paid tribute to the emperor in the form of gold and jewels .",
    back: "Eski şehir, haraç olarak imparatora altın ve mücevher verdi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "haraç",
    quest: "tribute",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The news triggered a wave of panic buying in the supermarkets .",
    back: "Haber, süpermarketlerde bir panik satın alma dalgasını tetikledi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tetiklemek",
    quest: "trigger",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The band consists of a talented trio of musicians .",
    back: "Grup, yetenekli bir müzisyen üçlüsünden oluşuyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "üçlü takım",
    quest: "trio",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The team celebrated their triumph in the championship game .",
    back: "Takım, şampiyonluk maçındaki zaferlerini kutladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "zafer",
    quest: "triumph",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The winner of the competition received a golden trophy .",
    back: "Yarışmanın kazananı altın bir kupa aldı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ganimet",
    quest: "trophy",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He looked troubled and seemed to be deep in thought .",
    back: "Sıkıntılı görünüyordu ve derin düşüncelere dalmış gibiydi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sıkıntılı",
    quest: "troubled",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The cost of tuition has been rising steadily over the past few years .",
    back: "Son birkaç yılda okul ücreti maliyeti sürekli olarak artıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "okul ücreti",
    quest: "tuition",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The bakery sells a variety of delicious turnovers .",
    back: "Fırın, çeşitli lezzetli meyveli turtalar satıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "meyveli turta",
    quest: "turnover",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She gave the wire a little twist to tighten the connection .",
    back: "Bağlantıyı sıkmak için teli biraz büktü .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bükmek",
    quest: "twist",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "She is currently enrolled in an undergraduate program at the university .",
    back: "Şu anda üniversitede lisans programına kayıtlıdır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "lisans",
    quest: "undergraduate",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "There are many underlying factors that contribute to climate change .",
    back:
        "İklim değişikliğine katkıda bulunan birçok altta yatan faktör vardır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "altta yatan",
    quest: "underlying",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "His constant criticism served to undermine her confidence .",
    back: "Sürekli eleştirisi, onun güvenini baltalamaya yaradı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "baltalamak",
    quest: "undermine",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He is undoubtedly the most qualified candidate for the job .",
    back: "Şüphesiz olarak işe en uygun adaydır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "şüphesiz olarak",
    quest: "undoubtedly",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The countries are working together to unify their economies .",
    back: "Ülkeler, ekonomilerini birleştirmek için birlikte çalışıyorlar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "aynı yapmak",
    quest: "unify",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We are facing unprecedented challenges in the 21st century .",
    back: "21 . yüzyılda eşi benzeri görülmemiş zorluklarla karşı karşıyayız .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "eşi benzeri görülmemiş",
    quest: "unprecedented",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We are excited about the upcoming conference on climate change .",
    back:
        "İklim değişikliği hakkındaki yaklaşan konferans hakkında heyecanlıyız .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "olmak üzere olan",
    quest: "upcoming",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The company is constantly upgrading its software to improve functionality .",
    back:
        "Şirket, işlevselliği artırmak için yazılımını sürekli olarak geliştiriyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "geliştirmek",
    quest: "upgrade",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "It is important to uphold the values of democracy and freedom .",
    back: "Demokrasi ve özgürlük değerlerini savunmak önemlidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tutmak",
    quest: "uphold",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "A calculator is a useful utility for performing mathematical calculations .",
    back:
        "Hesap makinesi, matematiksel hesaplamalar yapmak için faydalı bir yardımcı yazılımdır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yardımcı yazılım",
    quest: "utility",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The company is looking for ways to better utilize its resources .",
    back: "Şirket, kaynaklarını daha iyi değerlendirmenin yollarını arıyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yararlanmak",
    quest: "utilize",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She was utterly devastated by the news of her friend's death .",
    back: "Arkadaşının ölümü haberiyle tamamen yıkılmıştı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tümüyle",
    quest: "utterly",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "His instructions were vague and left me feeling confused .",
    back: "Talimatları belirsizdi ve kafamı karıştırdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "şüpheli",
    quest: "vague",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The validity of the passport expired five years ago .",
    back: "Pasaportun geçerliliği beş yıl önce doldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "geçerlilik",
    quest: "validity",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The magician made the rabbit vanish in a puff of smoke .",
    back:
        "Sihirbaz, tavşanı bir duman bulutunda ortadan kaybolmasını sağladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ortadan kaybolmak",
    quest: "vanish",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The weather is very variable this week, with sunshine one day and rain the next .",
    back: "Bu hafta hava çok değişken, bir gün güneşli diğer gün yağmurlu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "değişken",
    quest: "variable",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We enjoyed a varied menu with dishes from all over the world .",
    back:
        "Dünyanın her yerinden yemeklerin bulunduğu çeşitli bir menünün tadını çıkardık .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "değişik",
    quest: "varied",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Blood travels through the veins to the heart .",
    back: "Kan, damarlar yoluyla kalbe taşınır .",
    list: 'C1',
    answer: "damar",
    quest: "vein",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "They decided to start their own business venture .",
    back: "Kendi iş girişimlerini başlatmaya karar verdiler .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "girişim",
    quest: "venture",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The witness gave a verbal account of what they saw .",
    back: "Tanık, gördüklerini sözlü olarak anlattı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "sözlü",
    quest: "verbal",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The jury reached a verdict of guilty after a long deliberation .",
    back: "Jüri, uzun bir müzakerenin ardından suçlu kararına vardı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hüküm",
    quest: "verdict",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The scientist was able to verify the results of the experiment .",
    back: "Bilim insanı, deneyin sonuçlarını doğrulayabildi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "doğrulamak",
    quest: "verify",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "My favorite poem is the first verse of Sonnet 18 by William Shakespeare .",
    back:
        "En sevdiğim şiir, William Shakespeare'ın Sonnet 18'inin ilk dizesidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dize",
    quest: "verse",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The football match will be played between Turkey versus France .",
    back: "Futbol maçı Türkiye - Fransa arasında oynanacak .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "aleyhinde, karşı",
    quest: "versus",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The cargo ship is a large vessel that can transport thousands of tons of goods .",
    back: "Kargo gemisi, binlerce tonluk malı taşıyabilen büyük bir gemidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "gemi",
    quest: "vessel",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He is a veteran soldier with many years of experience in combat .",
    back: "Uzun yıllar savaş tecrübesine sahip kıdemli bir askerdir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kıdemli",
    quest: "veteran",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Is this plan a viable option for solving the problem?",
    back: "Bu plan, sorunu çözmek için yaşayabilir bir seçenek mi?",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yaşayabilir",
    quest: "viable",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The city is known for its vibrant culture and nightlife .",
    back: "Şehir, canlı kültürü ve gece hayatı ile tanınır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "titreşimli",
    quest: "vibrant",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The president admitted to his vice in judgment .",
    back: "Başkan, verdiği yanlış kararın sorumluluğunu üstlendi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "özür",
    quest: "vice",
  ),

  Words(
    front: "The dog attacked the mail carrier in a vicious manner .",
    back: "Köpek, postacıya vahşi bir şekilde saldırdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "vahşi",
    quest: "vicious",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The villagers live a simple life close to nature .",
    back: "Köylüler, doğayla iç içe basit bir hayat sürüyorlar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "köylü",
    quest: "villager",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Smoking cigarettes violates the health code .",
    back: "Sigara içmek sağlık kurallarını çiğnemektir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ihlal etmek",
    quest: "violate",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Speeding is a violation of traffic laws .",
    back: "Hız yapmak trafik yasalarının bir ihlalidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ihlal",
    quest: "violation",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Honesty and compassion are important virtues to possess .",
    back: "Dürüstlük ve merhamet, sahip olunması gereken önemli erdemlerdir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "erdem",
    quest: "virtue",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He vowed to get revenge on his enemies .",
    back: "Düşmanlarından intikam almaya yemin etti .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yemin etmek",
    quest: "vow",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The computer system has several vulnerabilities that hackers could exploit .",
    back:
        "Bilgisayar sisteminin, hackerların faydalanabileceği birkaç güvenlik açığı var .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "yaralanabilirlik",
    quest: "vulnerability",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "She is very vulnerable to getting the flu because she hasn't been vaccinated .",
    back: "Aşı olmadığı için gribe yakalanmaya karşı çok kolay yaralanır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kolayca yaralanır",
    quest: "vulnerable",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The hospital staff were on ward duty throughout the night .",
    back: "Hastane personeli gece boyunca nöbet görevi başındaydı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "nöbet", // This is a better translation for "ward" in this context
    quest: "ward",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The company has a large warehouse where they store their products .",
    back: "Şirketin ürünleri depolamak için kullandığı büyük bir deposu var .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "depo",
    quest: "warehouse",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The world has seen many devastating wars throughout history .",
    back: "Dünya tarih boyunca birçok yıkıcı savaşa sahne olmuştur .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "savaş",
    quest: "warfare",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The product does not come with a warranty, so you cannot return it if it breaks .",
    back: "Ürün garantili değil, bu nedenle bozulursa iade edemezsiniz .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "garanti etmek",
    quest: "warrant",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The brave warrior fought valiantly to protect his village .",
    back: "Cesur savaşçı, köyünü korumak için kahramanca savaştı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "savaşçı",
    quest: "warrior",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "A lack of sleep can weaken your immune system .",
    back: "Uyku eksikliği, bağışıklık sisteminizi zayıflatabilir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "zayıflatmak",
    quest: "weaken",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The artist used colorful threads to weave a beautiful tapestry .",
    back: "Sanatçı, güzel bir halı dokumak için renkli iplikler kullandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "dokumak",
    quest: "weave",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We need to remove the weeds from the flower bed .",
    back: "Yataktaki otları temizlememiz gerekiyor .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ot",
    quest: "weed",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The well provided a source of fresh water for the village .",
    back: "Kuyu, köy için temiz bir su kaynağı sağladı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kuyu",
    quest: "well",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Exercise and a healthy diet are essential for well-being .",
    back: "Egzersiz ve sağlıklı beslenme, sağlıklı yaşam için gereklidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "iyi oluş",
    quest: "well-being",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "We don't need to discuss his mistakes whatsoever .",
    back: "Hatalarını hiçbir şekilde tartışmamıza gerek yok .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hiçbir",
    quest: "whatsoever",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The bridge was constructed whereby cars and trains could cross the river .",
    back:
        "Köprü, arabaların ve trenlerin nehrin üzerinden geçebileceği şekilde inşa edildi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer:
        "sayesinde", // "şöyle ki" or "böylelikle" are better translations for "whereby" in this context
    quest: "whereby",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The trainer used a whip to motivate the horse during the race .",
    back: "Eğitmen, yarış sırasında atı motive etmek için kamçı kullandı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "kamçılamak",
    quest: "whip",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He was wholly dedicated to his work and never gave up .",
    back: "Tamamen işine adanmıştı ve asla vazgeçmedi .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tamamen",
    quest: "wholly",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The construction project will widen the road to accommodate more traffic .",
    back:
        "İnşaat projesi, daha fazla trafiğe yer açmak için yolu genişletecek .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "genişletmek",
    quest: "widen",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The width of the door frame is not standard .",
    back: "Kapı çerçevesinin genişliği standart değildir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "genişlik",
    quest: "width",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Many people volunteered their time to help clean up the park .",
    back:
        "Parkın temizlenmesine yardım etmek için birçok kişi gönüllü olarak zaman ayırdı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "gönüllülük",
    quest: "willingness",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He was known for his sharp wit and clever humor .",
    back: "Keskin zekası ve esprili mizahı ile tanınıyordu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "ince espri",
    quest: "wit",
  ),
  Words(
    front:
        "The sudden withdrawal of troops from the warzone surprised everyone .",
    back: "Savaş bölgesinden ani asker çekilmesi herkesi şaşırttı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bırakma",
    quest: "withdrawal",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "She did a daily workout to stay in shape .",
    back: "Formda kalmak için günlük olarak spor yaptı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "egzersiz",
    quest: "workout",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Many people worship different gods and goddesses .",
    back: "Birçok insan farklı tanrı ve tanrıçalara tapar .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "tapmak",
    quest: "worship",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "Is it worthwhile spending so much money on this gadget?",
    back: "Bu alete bu kadar para harcamaya değer mi?",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "değer",
    quest: "worthwhile",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "He is a worthy candidate for the scholarship .",
    back: "Bursu hak eden bir adaydır .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "hak eden",
    quest: "worthy",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The children were yelling and playing in the park .",
    back: "Çocuklar parkta bağırıyor ve oynuyorlardı .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "bağırmak",
    quest: "yell",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The army eventually yielded to the enemy's superior forces .",
    back: "Ordu sonunda düşmanın üstün güçlerine teslim oldu .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "teslim olmak",
    quest: "yield",
  ),
  Words(
    front: "The youngsters are the future of our country .",
    back: "Gençler ülkemizin geleceğidir .",
    list: "C1",
    answer: "gençler",
    quest: "youngster",
  ),
];
